{"qnaData":[{"id":0,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"What is COVID-19?","response":"COVID-19 is the disease caused by a new coronavirus called SARS-CoV-2.  WHO first learned of this new virus on 31 December 2019, following a report of a cluster of cases of ‘viral pneumonia’ in Wuhan, People’s Republic of China."},{"id":1,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"What are the symptoms of COVID-19?","response":"The most common symptoms of COVID-19 areFeverDry coughFatigueOther symptoms that are less common and may affect some patients include:Loss of taste or smell,Nasal congestion,Conjunctivitis (also known as red eyes)Sore throat,Headache,Muscle or joint pain,Different types of skin rash,Nausea or vomiting,Diarrhea,Chills or dizziness. Symptoms of severe COVID‐19 disease include:Shortness of breath,Loss of appetite,Confusion,Persistent pain or pressure in the chest,High temperature (above 38 °C).Other less common symptoms are:Irritability,Confusion,Reduced consciousness (sometimes associated with seizures),Anxiety,Depression,Sleep disorders,More severe and rare neurological complications such as strokes, brain inflammation, delirium and nerve damage.People of all ages who experience fever and/or cough associated with difficulty breathing or shortness of breath, chest pain or pressure, or loss of speech or movement should seek medical care immediately. If possible, call your health care provider,\r\n            hotline or health facility first, so you can be directed to the right clinic."},{"id":2,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"What happens to people who get COVID-19?","response":"Among those who develop symptoms, most (about 80%) recover from the disease without needing hospital treatment. About 15% become seriously ill and require oxygen and 5% become critically ill and need intensive care. Complications leading to death may include respiratory failure, acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), sepsis and septic shock, thromboembolism, and/or multiorgan failure, including injury of the heart, liver or kidneys. In rare situations, children can develop a severe inflammatory syndrome a few weeks after infection."},{"id":3,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"Who is most at risk of severe illness from COVID-19?","response":"People aged 60 years and over, and those with underlying medical problems like high blood pressure, heart and lung problems, diabetes, obesity or cancer, are at higher risk of developing serious illness. However, anyone can get sick with COVID-19 and become seriously ill or die at any age."},{"id":4,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"Are there long-term effects of COVID-19?","response":"Some people who have had COVID-19, whether they have needed hospitalization or not, continue to experience symptoms, including fatigue, respiratory and neurological symptoms. WHO is working with our Global Technical Network for Clinical Management of COVID-19, researchers and patient groups around the world to design and carry out studies of patients beyond the initial acute course of illness to understand the proportion of patients who have long term effects, how long they persist, and why they occur.  These studies will be used to develop further guidance for patient care."},{"id":5,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"How can we protect others and ourselves if we don't know who is infected?","response":"Stay safe by taking some simple precautions, such as physical distancing, wearing a mask, especially when distancing cannot be maintained, keeping rooms well ventilated, avoiding crowds and close contact, regularly cleaning your hands, and coughing into a bent elbow or tissue. Check local advice where you live and work. Do it all!Read our public advice page for more information."},{"id":6,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"When should I get a test for COVID-19?","response":"Anyone with symptoms should be tested, wherever possible. People who do not have symptoms but have had close contact with someone who is, or may be, infected may also consider testing – contact your local health guidelines and follow their guidance.  While a person is waiting for test results, they should remain isolated from others. Where testing capacity is limited, tests should first be done for those at higher risk of infection, such as health workers, and those at higher risk of severe illness such as older people, especially those living in seniors’ residences or long-term care facilities."},{"id":7,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"What test should I get to see if I have COVID-19?","response":"In most situations, a molecular test is used to detect SARS-CoV-2 and confirm infection. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) is the most commonly used molecular test. Samples are collected from the nose and/or throat with a swab. Molecular tests detect virus in the sample by amplifying viral genetic material to detectable levels. For this reason, a molecular test is used to confirm an active infection, usually within a few days of exposure and around the time that symptoms may begin. Learn more about what kind of COVID-19 tests are available"},{"id":8,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"What about rapid tests?","response":"Rapid antigen tests (sometimes known as a rapid diagnostic test – RDT) detect viral proteins (known as antigens). Samples are collected from the nose and/or throat with a swab. These tests are cheaper than PCR and will offer results more quickly, although they are generally less accurate. These tests perform best when there is more virus circulating in the community and when sampled from an individual during the time they are most infectious. - Learn more about rapid diagnostic test"},{"id":9,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"I want to find out if I had COVID-19 in the past, what test could I take?","response":"Antibody tests can tell us whether someone has had an infection in the past, even if they have not had symptoms. Also known as serological tests and usually done on a blood sample, these tests detect antibodies produced in response to an infection. In most people, antibodies start to develop after days to weeks and can indicate if a person has had past infection. Antibody tests cannot be used to diagnose COVID-19 in the early stages of infection or disease but can indicate whether or not someone has had the disease in the past."},{"id":10,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"What is the difference between isolation and quarantine?","response":"Both isolation and quarantine are methods of preventing the spread of COVID-19.Quarantine is used for anyone who is a contact of someone infected with the SARS-CoV-2 virus, which causes COVID-19, whether the infected person has symptoms or not. Quarantine means that you remain separated from others because you have been exposed to the virus and you may be infected and can take place in a designated facility or at home. For COVID-19, this means staying in the facility or at home for 14 days. Isolation is used for people with COVID-19 symptoms or who have tested positive for the virus. Being in isolation means being separated from other people, ideally in a medically facility where you can receive clinical care.  If isolation in a medical facility is not possible and you are not in a high risk group of developing severe disease, isolation can take place at home. If you have symptoms, you should remain in isolation for at least 10 days plus an additional 3 days without symptoms. If you are infected and do not develop symptoms, you should remain in isolation for 10 days from the time you test positive."},{"id":11,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"What should I do if I have been exposed to someone who has COVID-19?","response":"If you have been exposed to someone with COVID-19, you may become infected, even if you feel well. After exposure to someone who has COVID-19, do the following: Call your health care provider or COVID-19 hotline to find out where and when to get a test. Cooperate with contact-tracing procedures to stop the spread of the virus. If testing is not available, stay home and away from others for 14 days. While you are in quarantine, do not go to work, to school or to public places. Ask someone to bring you supplies.Keep at least a 1-metre distance from others, even from your family members. Wear a medical mask to protect others, including if/when you need to seek medical care.Clean your hands frequently.Stay in a separate room from other family members, and if not possible, wear a medical mask.Keep the room well-ventilated.If you share a room, place beds at least 1 metre apart.Monitor yourself for any symptoms for 14 days.  Stay positive by keeping in touch with loved ones by phone or online, and by exercising at home.If you live in an area with malaria or dengue fever, seek medical help if you have a fever. While travelling to and from the health facility and during medical care, wear a mask, keep at least a 1-metre distance from other people and avoid touching surfaces with your hands. This applies to adults and children. Read our malaria and COVID-19 Q&A for more information."},{"id":12,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"How long does it take to develop symptoms?","response":"The time from exposure to COVID-19 to the moment when symptoms begin is, on average, 5-6 days and can range from 1-14 days. This is why people who have been exposed to the virus are advised to remain at home and stay away from others, for 14 days, in order to prevent the spread of the virus, especially where testing is not easily available."},{"id":13,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"Is there a vaccine for COVID-19?","response":"Yes. The first mass vaccination programme started in early December 2020 and the number of vaccination doses administered is updated on a daily basis here. At least 13 different vaccines (across 4 platforms) have been administered. Campaigns have started in 206 economies.The Pfizer/BioNtech Comirnaty vaccine was listed for WHO Emergency Use Listing (EUL) on 31 December 2020. The SII/Covishield and AstraZeneca/AZD1222 vaccines (developed by AstraZeneca/Oxford and manufactured by the Serum Institute of India and SK Bio respectively) were given EUL on 16 February. The Janssen/Ad26.COV 2.S developed by Johnson & Johnson, was listed for EUL on 12 March 2021. The Moderna COVID-19 vaccine (mRNA 1273) was listed for EUL on 30 April 2021 and the Sinopharm COVID-19 vaccine was listed for EUL on 7 May 2021. The Sinopharm vaccine is produced by Beijing Bio-Institute of Biological Products Co Ltd, subsidiary of China National Biotec Group (CNBG).For further information, see here.Once vaccines are demonstrated to be safe and efficacious, they must be approved by national regulators, manufactured to exacting standards, and distributed. WHO is working with partners around the world to help coordinate key steps in this process, including to facilitate equitable access to safe and effective COVID-19 vaccines for the billions of people who will need them. More information about COVID-19 vaccine development is available here."},{"id":14,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"What should I do if I have COVID-19 symptoms?","response":"If you have any symptoms suggestive of COVID-19, call your health care provider or COVID-19 hotline for instructions and find out when and where to get a test, stay at home for 14 days away from others and monitor your health. If you have shortness of breath or pain or pressure in the chest, seek medical attention at a health facility immediately. Call your health care provider or hotline in advance for direction to the right health facility. If you live in an area with malaria or dengue fever, seek medical care if you have a fever.If local guidance recommends visiting a medical centre for testing, assessment or isolation, wear a medical mask while travelling to and from the facility and during medical care. Also keep at least a 1-metre distance from other people and avoid touching surfaces with your hands.  This applies to adults and children."},{"id":15,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"Are there treatments for COVID-19?","response":"Scientists around the world are working to find and develop treatments for COVID-19. Optimal supportive care includes oxygen for severely ill patients and those who are at risk for severe disease and more advanced respiratory support such as ventilation for patients who are critically ill. Dexamethasone is a corticosteroid that can help reduce the length of time on a ventilator and save lives of patients with severe and critical illness. Read our dexamethasone Q&A for more information.  Results from the WHO’s Solidarity Trial indicated that remdesivir, hydroxychloroquine, lopinavir/ritonavir and interferon regimens appear to have little or no effect on 28-day mortality or the in-hospital course of COVID-19 among hospitalized patients. Hydroxychloroquine has not been shown to offer any benefit for treatment of COVID-19. Read our hydroxychloroquine Q&A for more information. WHO does not recommend self-medication with any medicines, including antibiotics, as a prevention or cure for COVID-19. WHO is coordinating efforts to develop treatments for COVID-19 and will continue to provide new information as it becomes available."},{"id":16,"category":"General","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19","question":"Are antibiotics effective in preventing or treating COVID-19?","response":"Antibiotics do not work against viruses; they only work on bacterial infections. COVID-19 is caused by a virus, so antibiotics do not work. Antibiotics should not be used as a means of prevention or treatment of COVID-19.In hospitals, physicians will sometimes use antibiotics to prevent or treat secondary bacterial infections which can be a complication of COVID-19 in severely ill patients. They should only be used as directed by a physician to treat a bacterial infection."},{"id":17,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"Can adolescents catch COVID-19?","response":"Yes. All age groups can catch COVID-19.While we are still learning about how COVID-19 affects people, so far, data suggests that children under the age of 18 years have few deaths compared to other age groups and usually mild disease. However, cases of critical illness have been reported. As with adults, pre-existing medical problems like high blood pressure, heart and lung problems, asthma, diabetes, obesity, cancer and neurological and developmental conditions are risk factors for severe disease and intensive care admission in children. Further resources:Read our Q&A on Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) on who is most at risk of severe illness from COVID-19"},{"id":18,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"Can adolescents spread COVID-19 to other people even if they have mild or no symptoms?","response":"Yes. Infected people in all age groups – including adolescents - can transmit the virus to other people, even if they have mild symptoms or do not feel ill. The virus is spread from person to person through liquid particles such as aerosols (smaller) and droplets (larger) from the nose or mouth which are spread when a person with COVID-19 coughs, sneezes or speaks. People can catch COVID-19 if they breathe in these droplets from an adolescent infected with the virus.  Therefore, it is important to stay at least 1 meter away from others. These droplets can land on objects and surfaces. People can then become infected by touching these objects or surfaces, and then touching their eyes, nose or mouth. Further resources:Read our  Q&A on Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): How is it transmitted? for more information on how COVID-19 spreads between people"},{"id":19,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"Since there are few known cases of adolescents getting seriously ill with COVID-19, should I go to a health facility if I develop symptoms of the disease?","response":"If you have any symptoms suggestive of COVID-19,\r\ncontact your health care provider or COVID-19 hotline for instructions and find\r\nout what to do. If you have minor symptoms, such as a slight cough or a mild\r\nfever, and no risk factors for severe disease there is generally no need to go\r\nto a health care facility. Your health provider will assess the situation and\r\ngive instructions when and where to get a test, stay at home for 14 days away\r\nfrom others and monitor your health. Seek medical care immediately if your health gets\r\nworse, or if there is no one in your family that can take care of you at home. If\r\npossible, call your health care provider, hotline or health facility first, so\r\nyou can be directed to the right clinic. It is important that you follow the\r\nprocedures put in place by your country. Ask a family member or another trusted\r\nadult how you can find out what these procedures are where you live.Find out more on our main public advice page. Further resources:Read our  Q&A on Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) for more information on what to do if you have COVID-19 symptoms  Read our  Q&A on Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): Home care for families and caregivers on when someone who has tested positive for COVID-19 can be cared for at home"},{"id":20,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"What should I do if someone in my family gets really ill with COVID-19?","response":"Immediately seek medical care if a member of your family gets seriously ill, for example develops difficulty breathing or feels pain or pressure in the chest. If possible, either you or an adult should contact your health care provider or COVID-19 hotline for instructions and find out where and how you could get care. If your family member is confirmed as having COVID-19, you must be prepared that you and other known contacts will need to isolate for 14 days and monitor symptoms, even if you feel healthy.Find out more on our main public advice page. Further resources:Read our  Q&A on Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): Home care for families and caregivers on when someone who has tested positive for COVID-19 can be cared for at home WHO has developed the guidance on Considerations in the investigation of cases and clusters of COVID-19 that offers guidance to local, regional, or national health authorities what to do if a person is suspected or confirmed of having COVID-19"},{"id":21,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"I was due to get vaccinated for HPV, meningitis or tetanus, but immunization services have been disrupted. Should I be concerned?","response":"WHO recommends that countries continue routine immunization services wherever feasible. For example, school-based vaccination initiatives should continue only if infection prevention and control measures are implemented to avoid increased risk of transmission of the COVID-19 virus among the students, school personnel and health care providers. However, vaccines provided to adolescents have sufficiently flexible schedules to make sure you can get the vaccine in time when vaccination services start again. For example, the HPV vaccine that requires two doses can be started any time between 9 and 14 years of age and the interval between the two doses can be longer. The minimum interval between doses is 6 months, but it can be 12 or 15 months and, if necessary, even longer. It is most important that you receive the second dose at some point in time to be fully protected.Decisions to continue routine vaccination services are made by each country. Ask a family member or another trusted adult how you can get information about vaccination services where you live.  It is important you get the vaccines you are supposed to get, even if they have to be delayed due to the COVID-19 pandemic.  Further resources:Read our Q&A on Vaccines and immunization: What is vaccination? to find out more why is vaccination important and how does a vaccine workRead our Frequently Asked Questions on Immunization in the context of COVID-19 pandemicWHO has developed the guidance that provides Guiding principles for immunization activities during the COVID-19 pandemic"},{"id":22,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"I am on medication for a chronic health condition. Should I change anything?","response":"For people with chronic conditions such as such as asthma, diabetes, TB and HIV the most important thing is to continue your medication as prescribed, attend recommended check-ups and seek medical help if you have new symptoms.  Check with your health authorities and health provider if your regular check-ups should be done differently during the COVID-19 pandemic. Some services, such as counselling, may be available remotely. For treatment of clinically stable adolescents with HIV and adolescents with TB and/or other chronic conditions, your health provider should consider multi-month prescriptions and dispensing which will reduce the frequency of your visits to the clinic and ensure continuity of treatment, if movements are disrupted during the pandemic.  Seek advice from your health authorities and health care provider on how to be protected from COVID-19 and continue your treatment as prescribed.Find out more on our main public advice page. Further resources:Read our Q&A on Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): HIV and antiretrovirals on whether people living with HIV are at increased risk of being infected with the virus that causes COVID-19Read our Q&A on Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): Tuberculosis to find out if people with tuberculosis are likely to be at increased risk of COVID-19 infection and severe illness"},{"id":23,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"I am bored having to spend so much time at home. Since I am very unlikely to get severely ill even if I was to get COVID-19, why is it important that I follow the guidelines to prevent transmission such as keeping physical distance from other people?","response":"Spending more time at home is difficult and can get boring, but it may help to do something you enjoy. This could be reading a book, playing games or listening to music. Try to stay connected with friends and family every day either by communicating with them by phone or internet if you can, or, if you live close to them and the local rules allow you to, by talking in-person while keeping your distance. You can also get involved with your community to help fight the transmission of the virus. At the same time, it is still really important that you reduce your chances of being infected or spreading COVID-19 by washing your hands with soap and water or alcohol-based hand rub as often as possible, keeping at least 1 metre (3 feet) from other people, and avoiding crowded places. Even if adolescents with COVID-19 usually do not have symptoms and have mild disease, you might be one of the unlucky adolescents who does get severely ill from COVID-19, or you could spread it to others and be responsible for them getting really ill or even dying. You have the power to make choices that could save lives and together young people can play an important part in fighting COVID-19.Find out more on our main public advice page. Further resources:Read about 10 Ways Young People are Leading the Way Against COVID-19"},{"id":24,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"Some of my friends are not sticking to the rules about physical distancing. What should I do?","response":"Explain to your friends why it is important to protect themselves and others by washing their hands, avoiding touching their face, always coughing or sneezing into their elbow, sleeve, or a tissue, and cooperating with physical distancing measures and movement restrictions when called on to do so. Maybe you can share ideas for fun virtual activities that your friends can participate in, and you can encourage them to do them together with you or with other friends. For example, you can encourage them to join YouthAgainstCOVID19 campaign that aims to help teach young people around the world about COVID-19 and what they can do to keep their friends, families and communities safe. This way you are giving them alternatives rather than just telling them to stay at home. But, remember that you do not have control over other peoples’ actions so do not get into an argument or a fight to try to change their minds."},{"id":25,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"I know there is a risk of getting COVID-19, but can I still play sports?","response":"Yes. You can play sports that are in line with the physical distancing measures and movement restrictions that are in place in your country. If you are able to go for a bicycle ride, or if you go to a park or public open space to walk, run or exercise always practice physical distancing and wash your hands with water and soap before you leave, when you get to where you are going, and as soon as you get home.  If water and soap are not immediately available, use alcohol-based hand rub. Being physically active is good for your health, both physical and mental. Set up a regular routine to practice activities or sports that do not require close contact with others every day for 1 hour. You can do individual sports, like jogging, walking, dancing or yoga. There are many options to try. You can set up playground games indoors, such as jump rope and hop-scotch, play with your brothers and sisters, and practice some strength training activities, using improvised weights like bottles full of water or sand. If you have access to the internet, you can also join in online active games or fitness classes, or set up your own online physical exercises with your friends or classmates. Find an activity that is fun, can be done within the restrictions that are in place in your country, and makes you feel good.Do not exercise if you have a fever, cough and difficulty breathing. Stay home and rest, seek medical attention and follow the directions of your local health authority. Further resources:Read our Q&A on How to be active during COVID-19"},{"id":26,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"COVID-19 makes me really anxious. I feel worried and at times have difficulty coping with stress. What should I do?","response":"In situations like a pandemic it is very normal to feel anxious and powerless, and that is ok. Here are a few suggestions on things that could help you proactively manage your anxiety:TIP 1: DO THINGS THAT ARE GOOD FOR YOUR BODY AND MINDYour body and mind are connected. Here are some things you can do to keep them healthy:• Stay active! Being physically active is good for your body and can help your mind feel better too. If you can go outside, try a walk, run, bike ride, or any other sport. If indoors, try dancing, stretching, or any other movement you can do. Find what works for you – and do it! • Eat well! Try to make healthy choices about what you eat if you can.• Take notice of yourself and the world around you. This means becoming more aware of your breathing, your body and your surroundings. Try to BE PRESENT in the moment! • Sleep! Try to get the right balance of sleep each night. This will help you grow well, stay healthy, and keep clear thoughts.•  Find things that make you happy and do those things more! Listening to music, reading, playing games, chatting with friends, growing plants, cooking, drawing, playing sports…there are many possibilities! Perhaps even try something new! Just make sure that during these activities you respect physical distancing and other protection measures that are in place in your country.TIP 2: STAY CONNECTED TO LOVED ONESKeep in touch with your family and friends however you can. Use social media, email, phone calls, write a letter! Be creative. And if you can’t connect, then think about a memory of a shared time together.TIP 3: RECOGNISE HOW YOU ARE FEELINGUnderstanding how you feel is important. Don’t ignore it. Sometimes writing your feelings down can help you to describe it. It might sound easy or simple, but try this “I feel ....... right now”.TIP 4: BE KIND TO YOURSELF It is okay to feel however it is that you’re feeling. Putting pressure on yourself to always ‘be happy’ or ‘stay positive’ or ‘stay productive’ can sometimes make you feel worse. Instead, if you notice you are experiencing difficult emotions, try telling yourself: “I feel worried and scared, but that does not mean I am not coping.” “It’s been a tough time, it’s okay to be upset.” “I am feeling [insert how you are feeling] and that is okay.” “These are difficult times, it’s normal to feel upset.” Or think of something to tell yourself that works for you. TIP 5: LISTEN TO YOUR BODYOur body experiences and reacts to how we feel. Do you often get headaches? Do your shoulders, chest, or stomach sometimes feel tense? Try closing your eyes, and listening to your own breathing. Notice how you feel in each part of your body, starting from your head down to your toes. Notice if you are feeling any tightness, pain, or pressure in your body. Being aware of where you are feeling tension can help you release it.TIP 6: TRY USING YOUR BREATH TO CALM YOURSELFSlow breathing is one of the quickest ways of calming down the body when we experience feelings such as fear, worry or anger. Close your eyes and think of a calm place. Imagine yourself there, feeling relaxed.• Focus on breathing slowly. • Breathe in for a slow count of 3 and out for a slow count of 3. • Practice this for a few minutes. How do you feel after?TIP 7: AVOID UNHEALTHY WAYS OF COPING WITH STRESSWhen you are experiencing difficult feelings, it is important to find healthy ways to take care of yourself.Find out more on our #HealthyAtHome - Mental health page. Further resources:Read our guide “Doing What Matters in Times of Stress: An Illustrated Guide” Read more from Voices of Youth on how to take care of yourself and your relationships in stressful timesRead about Coping with stress during the 2019-nCoV outbreakYour parents or legal guardians may access this resources on Helping children cope with stress during the 2019-nCoV outbreakThe #CopingWithCOVID is a webinar series that provides young people with a platform for genuine connection amid uncertainty, encouraging them to field their questions to the experts from UNICEF and WHO, and generate mental health awareness among young people. If you missed any of the sessions, you can watch them still!Teamup at home: support for children during the coronavirus pandemic is a resource specifically developed for children aged 6 to 11 but can be enjoyed by people of all ages – it provides a simple, safe and above all fun way to play and exercise in pairs or individually."},{"id":27,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"COVID-19 is everywhere in the news, and I am finding it difficult to know what is true and what is false. What should I do?","response":"A near-constant stream of news, sometimes contradictory, can cause anyone to feel lost and distressed. Make sure to use reliable sources such as UNICEF and WHO’s sites to get information, or to check any information you might be getting through less reliable channels.If you have a phone, you can use the WHO Health Alert on WhatsApp to get the latest information about the pandemic. This is a new service, which is free to use, designed to give prompt, reliable and official information 24 hours a day, worldwide. Start by clicking the WHO Health Alert, then simply text the word ‘Hi’ in a WhatsApp message to get started. Many countries have similar initiatives to provide context-specific information and updates. Keep in mind that overloading yourself with information about the COVID-19 pandemic can also be stressful, so seek information updates and practical guidance at specific times during the day and avoid listening to or following rumours that make you feel uncomfortable.Find out more on our Mythbusters pageFind out more on our #HealthyAtHome - Mental health page. Further resources:Read about Coping with stress during the 2019-nCoV outbreak"},{"id":28,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"Schools are reopening in some areas of my country. Is it safe to go back to school?","response":"A decision to reopen schools in every country and area is made based on careful assessment of the situation, with consensus among all the key parties involved, including the health and education policy-makers, teachers and other school staff, parents and health and community workers. In addition, reopening of schools is carefully planned and prepared, with all necessary measures in place to protect the safety and health of everyone in the school community.Therefore, if your school reopens, you should feel assured it is safe for you to go back to school – provided that you strictly follow the guidelines and rules that will be provided by your school.Of course, if you have any concerns with going back to school, do not hesitate to speak out to your teachers and parents or guardians. Further resources:Read what WHO recommends for safe schools reopening in Considerations for school-related public health measures in the context of COVID-19  Read our Q&A on Schools and Covid-19"},{"id":29,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"What should I do if I missed out on my education due to the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"Your school or place where you are studying are likely to make arrangements for you to catch up on what you have missed when your school was closed. Many schools have put in place accelerated learning modalities to help pupils catch up on learning loss.  If your school is still closed, and you cannot attend classes in person, follow the procedures that your school has put in place to give you access to educational materials and technologies (internet, texting radio, radio, or television). If you have access to the internet, you can also consult your teachers and other trusted adults to identify and access reliable online learning opportunities and resources, including those included in the distance learning solutions recommended by UNESCO, the United Nations agency that helps countries improve their education systems. In addition, UNESCO is collecting stories from students, teachers and parents about how they are coping and continuing to learn during school closures. Access those stories, they might inspire you. You can also contact UNESCO and share your story! Find out how to share it here.In places where internet connectivity is a problem, many governments have started to broadcast educational programmes on TV and radio channels during school closures. If you live in such a place, look out for educational programmes on your local TV and radio channels.Further resources:Studying at home due to coronavirus? This is how young people around the world are keeping their mood up"},{"id":30,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"Should I wear a mask at school or when playing sports?","response":"You should not wear a mask when playing sports or doing physical activities, such as running, jumping or playing on the playground, so that it doesn’t compromise your breathing. However, remember to maintain at least a 1-metre distance from others, limit the number of friends playing together, and respect hand hygiene.Regarding wearing masks in schools and other public places, WHO advises that people always consult and abide by local authorities on recommended practices in their area. In countries or areas where there is intense community transmission of the virus and in settings where physical distancing cannot be achieved, WHO and UNICEF advise decision makers to apply the following criteria for use of masks in schools (either in classes, corridors or communal areas) when developing national policies:• Children aged 5 years and under should not be required to wear masks.• For children between six and 11 years of age, the decision to use a mask will vary from place to place, and will depend on several factors, such as the intensity of transmission in the area where the child lives, local norms that influence social interactions, the child’s capacity to comply with the appropriate use of masks and availability of appropriate adult supervision, and other factors. • Children and adolescents 12 years or older should follow the national mask guidelines for adults.Watch our ‘How to wear a fabric mask’ video for a demonstration. Watch our ‘WHO’s recommended fabric mask materials and composition’ video for more information.Further resources:Read our Q&A on children and masks related to COVID-19 for more information on      precautions for younger age groups.Watch our animation on medical and      fabric masks, explaining who wears what, when and where.Read more in our guidance  Considerations for school-related public      health measures in the context of COVID-19 what are the considerations in      schools for wearing masks"},{"id":31,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"I am spending much more time online in social media, playing games and studying. Should I be worried about this?","response":"COVID-19 has abruptly pushed many people’s daily lives online, and you may be spending even more hours online than before. While online solutions provide huge opportunities for continuing your learning, socializing and playing, you should try to limit the amount of screen time that is not related to your studies or physical activity. This is because you need to be physically active to keep healthy and a positive attitude. In addition, some people are sensitive to flickering lights and may get headaches, nausea, and dizziness, and even seizures if they spend too much time in front of a screen. Therefore, it is important to replace some of the recreational screen time with non-screen activities, like listening to music, reading, playing board games, and physical activity, like going for a walk or jog. Excessive gaming can lead to “gaming disorder” that leads to reduced sleep or day-night reversal, loss of appetite, aggression, headaches, and attention problems. If you experience these symptoms, seek help from your parents or a trusted adult. Further resources:Read our brief on Addictive behaviours: Gaming disorder  Find out more about COVID-19 and its implications for protecting children online"},{"id":32,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"I heard I can be hurt by online contacts. What are my risks and how I can protect myself online.","response":"Since you might be spending even more time online than before, it is wise to be aware of some of the risks. First, be careful what content you share online. Risky behaviour, such as sexting or sharing of sexualized content, can expose you to risks of blackmail, harassment and humiliation. Second, spending more time online may increase the chances that you could come into contact with online predators who seek to sexually exploit young people. When in front of webcams wear appropriate clothing and avoid using private instant messaging services in your communication with teachers. In addition, it’s important to note that some adolescents – for example those with disabilities and those perceived to be different or at greater risk of catching or spreading COVID-19 - may be at increased risk of cyberbullying and discrimination. Hurtful, discriminatory or inappropriate online contact is never okay. If in doubt, or if you feel uncomfortable or distressed about some interactions you have online, tell a parent or another trusted adult immediately.Further resources:Find out more about COVID-19 and its implications for protecting children online"},{"id":33,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"Since my parents stopped going out to work, they have been arguing with each other much more, and in some instances, I have seen one parent harm or hurt the other either verbally or physically. I don’t feel safe at home. What should I do?","response":"This is a difficult time. Many people – including perhaps your parents - are worrying about security, health, and money. When people are in cramped and confined living conditions, these tensions and stress can become even greater. It is normal to have disagreements. However, if the disagreements become verbal or physical, then it is right to take action. If you are worried about what is happening in your home, or don’t feel safe, talk to a trusted adult about what worries you, and seek their advice. During an argument or a fight, try not to draw attention to yourself so that you don’t end up getting hurt. It might be useful to have a safety plan in case the violence escalates. This includes preparing a bag with essential items, like clothing, documents and electric charger, and having a neighbour, friend, relative, or shelter identified to go to should you need to leave the house immediately for safety reasons. Arrange with the trusted adult to help you alert the relevant authorities who can help you stay safe, including the police, emergency health services and social services.In many of the countries that have been most affected by COVID-19, essential services are still available, including shelters or protection services. If there are no trusted adults for you to share your concerns with, your country may have helplines, including text services so that you can communicate with someone who can help you or give you advice.Further resources:Read more in the  COVID-19 and Ending Violence Against Women and Girls briefFind out more how COVID-19 can exacerbate risks of violence for womenin this brief COVID-19 and violence against womenRead our Guidelines for the health sector response to child maltreatment"},{"id":34,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"Is it safe to have sex at this time?","response":"There is no evidence that COVID-19 is transmitted through semen or vaginal fluids. However, having sex with someone means that you are very close to them. This puts one person at risk if the other person has COVID-19. Masturbation does not involve another person and carries no risk of COVID-19. Depending on the government guideline, there might be restrictions in place to meet people outside your household, so it is important you follow these guidelines. Your risk of COVID-19 is not increased if you already live in the same household as your sexual partner and you are both taking steps to protect yourself from the virus. Make sure to use condoms and contraception to avoid sexually transmitted infections and unintended pregnancy.Further resources:Read our Q&A on Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): Contraception and family planning Find out more about contraceptive counselling and services for young people during COVID-19 in this brief Not in Pause.  Responding to the Sexual and Reproductive Health Needs of Adolescents During the COVID-19 Crisis"},{"id":35,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"I don’t like the way someone touches me at home and we are both at home all the time because of the pandemic. What should I do?","response":"It is wrong for anyone to do this. And it is not your fault in any way. If you are staying in the same house as the person and/or are dependent on him (it will usually be a man), that may make some of the things that you could do difficult, especially during stay-at-home restrictions due to COVID-19. Here are some things that you can consider doing to improve your safety while in the house.You could      tell him politely but firmly that you do not want him to touch you and ask      him to please stop.You could      inform your parents or other caregivers or trusted adult in the house      about what is happening.You could      inform a trusted adult outside your home such as a neighbour or a teacher      or family friend or relative.If you have      access to a phone, you could call or text for help and support. This      includes calling hotlines/helplines for children and women who are in need      of help or feeling distressed or subjected to abuse, or calling a child      protection service in your area. Be careful not to leave your phone calls      or text messages where anyone else could access them. If you need      to leave the house immediately because he is hurting or harming you, think      of discretely (without him overhearing) pre-arranging with a neighbour or      trusted relative or family friend to help you leave the house and stay      with them until it is safe for you to return home. If you have been sexually abused or raped and need urgent medical help or care, go as soon as possible to the nearest hospital or clinic to ask for medical care.   Further resources: Find out more what can you do if you feel home is not a safe place in our Q&A Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): Violence against womenFind out more how COVID-19 can exacerbate risks of violence for women in this brief COVID-19 and violence against women"},{"id":36,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"When will this pandemic end so things can go back to normal?","response":"We don’t know when the pandemic will end, but we know it depends on every person’s contribution in helping stop the spread of the virus. The sacrifices you have made by not seeing your friends and by not going to school for a while, and other activities, are your contributions to fighting the pandemic. By putting societies and economies on hold, we have reduced the ability of the virus to spread through our communities. These defensive measures have helped to limit the damage the virus can cause, and bought us time to learn more about the virus and find solutions so that we can get back to a more familiar way of living. This is why it was possible to reopen schools and businesses in many places. It is important that you continue to practice the recommended measures and encourage your friends to do the same to prevent the situation from getting worse.Further resources:Find out more on our main public advice page. Read more about COVID-19 vaccine development."},{"id":37,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"I feel like my future has been affected. I am not able to apply for the jobs I wanted, and now that I have a new job I find it hard to be noticed when remote working","response":"The anonymity of working from home is really taking a toll on people and it is normal if you are feeling a bit forgotten and lost. It can feel difficult to get the attention you deserve and get your work noticed, especially if this is a new job and you do not yet know your manager and other colleagues well.  If you have a comfortable relationship with your supervisor it may be helpful to discuss whether adjustments to your workload, work schedule or other work-related matters can be made. This conversation could also be held with the person responsible for human resources at work.There are many things you can do to feel more comfortable in the new job while working remotely. Ask your supervisor to access a training on remote working and personal effectiveness skills.  Using your time to access learning and training opportunities can not only help you develop skills for your current role but also prepare you for future roles you may desire. Agree with your manager to have regular check-in calls where you can keep your supervisor aware of accomplishments with an informative summary. If you have regular team meetings use this as an opportunity to flag your key successes, and let your co-workers to know you better. Invite your colleagues with whom you haven’t connected yet to virtual coffee dates. Don’t be shy to volunteer for new projects, and offer help to your colleagues when you can.When solutions to problems are hard to find, it can help to talk through with people who you trust, who may be able to help or can be a person to discuss ideas with - ranging from friends, to our work colleagues or supervisors or HR or to external advisors such as career guidance and job-seeking support. Many public employment offices have moved their services online and can offer you great insights about the labour market, vacancies and training opportunities. If you feel your mental health is taking a big toll and its affecting you much more than expected (such as affecting how well you work) then consider the following 1) engaging in stress management techniques – as reduced stress can help to improve our problem solving thinking (see Doing What Matters in Times of Stress and Managing work-related psychosocial risks during the COVID-19 pandemic); 2) if you are still in work, consider reaching out to your staff health or human resources services who may be able to help you find to mental health and psychosocial support at work or through your local health services including online support.  Further resources:Read Tips for teens to learn about 5 ways to stay safe at workAccess this resource for young people who are about to enter, or have recently entered, the labour market to know more about [email protected] for youth. It has hands-on examples on workplace situations and tips how to manage them.Watch these videos on      Positive wellbeing in the workplace during COVID-19 pandemicRead this piece on how      human factors/ergonomic considerations can improve your teleworking      experienceRead and get inspired by the stories of young people volunteering and leading collective action to mitigate the impacts of the pandemic."},{"id":38,"category":"Adolescents and youth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-adolescents-and-youth","question":"What can we do so that other diseases like COVID-19 do not affect us in future?","response":"COVID-19 is a zoonotic disease which means that it existed naturally in animals before it spilled over to humans. Most new or emerging infectious diseases —whether in wildlife, domestic animals, plants or people — are driven by human activities that lead to environmental degradation. Human pressures, from deforestation, to intensive and polluting agricultural practices, to unsafe management and consumption of wildlife, increase the risk of new or emerging infectious diseases. This is why the number of emerging infectious disease outbreaks has increased steadily since 1980.   To prevent the disastrous effects of emerging infectious diseases, we have to recognize that human health is intimately connected to the health of animals and our shared environment, and take action. Millions of young people have already mobilized to demand action not only on climate and biodiversity - but also for the right to breathe clean air, and for their future on a liveable planet. You can join them to add your voice and talents to this global movement:Read and disseminate the WHO Manifesto for a healthy recovery from COVID-19 by disseminating it and taking personal steps Support actions in your country to implement the 6 prescriptions of the WHO Manifesto for a healthy recovery from COVID-19.Further resources:Find out more about in these Q&A about Biodiversity and infectious diseases Read our Manifesto for a healthy recovery from COVID-19Find out what actions can be taken for a healthy, green recovery from COVID-19"},{"id":39,"category":"Breastfeeding","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-breastfeeding","question":"Can COVID-19 be passed through breastfeeding?","response":"Transmission of active COVID-19 (virus that can cause infection) through breast milk and breastfeeding has not been detected to date. There is no reason to avoid or stop breastfeeding."},{"id":40,"category":"Breastfeeding","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-breastfeeding","question":"In communities where COVID-19 is prevalent, should mothers breastfeed?","response":"Yes. In all socio-economic settings, breastfeeding improves survival and provides lifelong health and development advantages to newborns and infants. Breastfeeding also improves the health of mothers."},{"id":41,"category":"Breastfeeding","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-breastfeeding","question":"Following delivery, should a baby still be immediately placed skin-to-skin and breastfed if the mother is confirmed or suspected to have COVID-19?","response":"Yes. Immediate and continued skin-to-skin care, including kangaroo mother care, improves the temperature control of newborns and is associated with improved survival among newborn babies. Placing the newborn close to the mother also enables early initiation of breastfeeding which also reduces mortality.The numerous benefits of skin-to-skin contact and breastfeeding substantially outweigh the potential risks of transmission and illness associated with COVID-19."},{"id":42,"category":"Breastfeeding","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-breastfeeding","question":"Can women with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 breastfeed?","response":"Yes. Women with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 can breastfeed if they wish to do so. They should:Wash hands frequently with soap and water or use alcohol-based hand rub and especially before touching the baby;Wear a medical mask during any contact with the baby, including while feeding;Sneeze or cough into a tissue. Then dispose of it immediately and wash hands again;Routinely clean and disinfect surfaces that mothers have touched.It is important to replace medical masks as soon as they become damp and dispose of them immediately. Masks should not be reused or touched in the front."},{"id":43,"category":"Breastfeeding","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-breastfeeding","question":"If a mother confirmed or suspected to have COVID-19 does not have a medical face mask should she still breastfeed?","response":"Yes. Breastfeeding unquestionably reduces mortality in newborns and infants and provides numerous lifelong health and brain development advantages to the child. Mothers with symptoms of COVID-19 are advised to wear a medical mask, but even if this is not possible, breastfeeding should be continued. Mothers should follow other infection prevention measures, such as washing hands, cleaning surfaces, sneezing or\n    coughing into a tissue.Non-medical masks (e.g. home-made or cloth masks) have not been evaluated. At this time, it is not possible to make a recommendation for or against their use."},{"id":44,"category":"Breastfeeding","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-breastfeeding","question":"I have confirmed or suspected COVID-19 and am too unwell to breastfeed my baby directly. What can I do?","response":"If you are too unwell to breastfeed your baby due to COVID-19 or other complications, you should be supported to safely provide your baby with breast milk in a way possible, available, and acceptable to you. This could include:Expressing milk;Donor human milk. If expressing breast milk or donor human milk are not feasible then consider wet nursing (another woman breastfeeds the child) or infant formula milk with measures to ensure that it is feasible, correctly prepared, safe and sustainable."},{"id":45,"category":"Breastfeeding","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-breastfeeding","question":"I had confirmed or suspected COVID-19 and was unable to breastfeed, when can I start to breastfeed again?","response":"You can start to breastfeed when you feel well enough to do so. There is no fixed time interval to wait after confirmed or suspected COVID-19. There is no evidence that breastfeeding changes the clinical course of COVID-19 in a mother. Health workers or breastfeeding counsellors should support you to relactate."},{"id":46,"category":"Breastfeeding","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-breastfeeding","question":"I have confirmed or suspected COVID-19, is it safer to give my baby infant formula milk?","response":"No. There are always risks associated with giving infant formula milk to newborns and infants in all settings. The risks associated with giving infant formula milk are increased whenever home and community conditions are compromised, such as reduced access\nto health services if a baby becomes unwell, reduced access to clean water and/or access to supplies of infant formula milk are difficult or not guaranteed, affordable and sustainable.\nThe numerous benefits of breastfeeding substantially outweigh the potential risks of transmission and illness associated with the COVID-19 virus."},{"id":47,"category":"Children and masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/q-a-children-and-masks-related-to-covid-19","question":"Should children wear a mask?","response":"WHO advises that people always consult and abide by local authorities on recommended practices in their area. An international and multidisciplinary expert group brought together by WHO reviewed evidence on COVID-19 disease and transmission in children and the limited available evidence on the use of masks by children. Based on this and other factors such as childrens’ psychosocial needs and developmental milestones, WHO and UNICEF advise the following: Children aged 5 years and under should not be required to wear masks. This is based on the safety and overall interest of the child and the capacity to appropriately use a mask with minimal assistance. WHO and UNICEF advise that the decision to use masks for children aged 6-11 should be based on the following factors:Whether there is widespread transmission in the area where the child residesThe ability of the child to safely and appropriately use a maskAccess to masks, as well as laundering and replacement of masks in certain settings (such as schools and childcare services) Adequate adult supervision and instructions to the child on how to put on, take off and safely wear masksPotential impact of wearing a mask on learning and psychosocial development, in consultation with teachers, parents/caregivers and/or medical providersSpecific settings and interactions the child has with other people who are at high risk of developing serious illness, such as the elderly and those with other underlying health conditions WHO and UNICEF advise that children aged 12 and over should wear a mask under the same conditions as adults, in particular when they cannot guarantee at least a 1-metre distance from others and there is widespread transmission in the area.More on the types of masks, how to choose them, and how to wear them is available here:  https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public/when-and-how-to-use-masks"},{"id":48,"category":"Children and masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/q-a-children-and-masks-related-to-covid-19","question":"Are there situations where children aged 5 years and under may wear or be required to wear a mask?","response":"In general, children aged 5 years and under should not be required to wear masks. This advice is based on the safety and overall interest of the child and the capacity to appropriately use a mask with minimal assistance. There may be local requirements for children aged 5 years and under to wear masks, or specific needs in some settings, such as being physically close to someone who is ill. In these circumstances, if the child wears a mask, a parent or other guardian should be within direct line of sight to supervise the safe use of the mask."},{"id":49,"category":"Children and masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/q-a-children-and-masks-related-to-covid-19","question":"Should children with developmental disabilities wear masks?","response":"The use of masks for children of any age with developmental disorders, disabilities or other specific health conditions should not be mandatory and be assessed on a case by case basis by the child’s parent, guardian, educator and/or medical provider. In any case, children with severe cognitive or respiratory impairments with difficulties tolerating a mask should not be required to wear masks."},{"id":50,"category":"Children and masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/q-a-children-and-masks-related-to-covid-19","question":"Should children who have health issues or a medical condition that compromises their immune system wear a mask?","response":"Children with underlying health conditions such as cystic fibrosis or cancer should wear a medical mask in consultation with their medical providers. A medical mask provides protection to the person wearing the mask and prevents transmission to others. It is recommended for anyone who has underlying health conditions that put them at greater risk of serious illness."},{"id":51,"category":"Children and masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/q-a-children-and-masks-related-to-covid-19","question":"What type of mask should children wear?","response":"Children who are in general good health can wear a non-medical or fabric mask. This provides source control, meaning it keeps the virus from being transmitted to others if they are infected and are not aware that they are infected. The adult who is providing the mask should ensure the fabric mask is the correct size and sufficiently covers the nose, mouth and chin of the child. Children with underlying health conditions such as cystic fibrosis, cancer or immunosuppression, should, in consultation with their medical providers, wear a medical mask. A medical mask controls spreading of the virus and protection to the wearer, and is recommended for anyone who is at higher risk of getting seriously ill from COVID-19."},{"id":52,"category":"Children and masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/q-a-children-and-masks-related-to-covid-19","question":"How should children wear a mask?","response":"Children should follow the same principles as adults for wearing masks. This includes cleaning hands at least 20 seconds if using an alcohol-based hand rub, or at least 40 seconds if using soap and water, before putting on the mask. Make sure the mask is the right size to cover the nose, mouth and chin.  Children should be taught how to wear the mask properly, including not touching the front of the mask and not pulling it under the chin or into their mouth. They should store the mask in a bag or container, and not share the mask with others. More information, including videos on how to put on, take off and care for a mask, can be found here: https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public/when-and-how-to-use-masks"},{"id":53,"category":"Children and masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/q-a-children-and-masks-related-to-covid-19","question":"Should a child wear a mask at home?","response":"Any child who has symptoms suggestive of COVID-19 should wear a medical mask, as long as they can tolerate it. The child should be isolated, and medical advice sought as soon as they start to feel unwell, even if symptoms are mild. Family members/caregivers who come within 1 metre of the sick child at home should also wear a mask.  A household member who is sick or has tested positive with the virus that causes COVID-19 should be isolated from everyone else if possible. If the child comes within 1 metre of the sick person at home, the adult and child should wear a medical mask during that time."},{"id":54,"category":"Children and masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/q-a-children-and-masks-related-to-covid-19","question":"Should teachers or other adults working with children wear a mask?","response":"In areas where there is widespread transmission, all adults under the age of 60 and who are in general good health should wear fabric masks when they cannot guarantee at least a 1-metre distance from others. This is particularly important for adults working with children who may have close contact with children and one another. Adults aged 60 or over, or who have any underlying health conditions such as heart disease, diabetes or lung cancer, should wear a medical mask because of their higher risk of getting seriously ill from COVID-19. More information, including videos on how to put on, take off and care for a mask, can be found here: https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public/when-and-how-to-use-masks"},{"id":55,"category":"Children and masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/q-a-children-and-masks-related-to-covid-19","question":"Should children wear a mask when playing sports or doing physical activities?","response":"Children should not wear a mask when playing sports or doing physical activities, such as running, jumping or playing on the playground, so that it doesn’t compromise their breathing. When organizing these activities for children, it is important to encourage all other critical public health measures: maintaining at least a 1-metre distance from others, limiting the number of children playing together, providing access to hand hygiene facilities and encouraging their use."},{"id":56,"category":"Children and masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/q-a-children-and-masks-related-to-covid-19","question":"Are there alternatives to fabric masks such as face shields?","response":"In the context of COVID-19, some children may not be able to wear a mask due to disabilities or specific situations such as speech classes where the teacher needs to see their mouths. In these cases, face shields may be considered an alternative to masks, but they do not provide the equivalent protection in keeping the virus from being transmitted to others.  If a decision is made to use a face shield, it should cover the entire face, wrap around the sides of the face and extend to below the chin. Caution should be taken while wearing one to avoid injuries that could break it and harm the eyes or face."},{"id":57,"category":"Cleaning and disinfecting surfaces in non-health care settings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-cleaning-and-disinfecting-surfaces-in-non-health-care-settings","question":"What areas should be prioritized for disinfection in non-health care settings?","response":"Disinfection practices are important to reduce the potential for COVID-19 virus contamination in non-healthcare settings, such as in the home, office, schools, gyms, publicly accessible buildings, faith-based community centres, markets, transportation and business settings or restaurants. High-touch surfaces in these non-health care settings should be identified for priority disinfection such as door and window handles, kitchen and food preparation areas, counter tops, bathroom surfaces, toilets and taps, touchscreen personal devices, personal computer keyboards, and work surfaces."},{"id":58,"category":"Cleaning and disinfecting surfaces in non-health care settings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-cleaning-and-disinfecting-surfaces-in-non-health-care-settings","question":"Which surface disinfectants are effective against COVID-19 in non-health care setting environments?","response":"In non-health care settings, sodium hypochlorite (bleach / chlorine) may be used at a recommended concentration of 0.1% or 1,000ppm (1 part of 5% strength household bleach to 49 parts of water). Alcohol at 70-90% can also be used for surface disinfection. Surfaces must be cleaned with water and soap or a detergent first to remove dirt, followed by disinfection.  Cleaning should always start from the least soiled (cleanest) area to the most soiled (dirtiest) area in order to not spread the dirty to areas that are less soiled. All disinfectant solutions should be stored in opaque containers, in a well-ventilated, covered area that is not exposed to direct sunlight and ideally should be freshly prepared every day.In indoor spaces, routine application of disinfectants to surfaces via spraying is not recommended for COVID-19. If disinfectants are to be applied, these should be via a cloth or wipe which is soaked in the disinfectant."},{"id":59,"category":"Cleaning and disinfecting surfaces in non-health care settings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-cleaning-and-disinfecting-surfaces-in-non-health-care-settings","question":"What protection measures should people take when using disinfectants?","response":"It is important to reduce your risk when using disinfectants:The disinfectant and its concentration should be carefully selected to avoid damaging surfaces and to avoid or minimize toxic effects on household members (or users of public spaces).Avoid combining disinfectants, such as bleach and ammonia, since mixtures can cause respiratory irritation and release potentially fatal gases.Keep children, pets and other people away during the application of the product until it is dry and there is no odour. Open windows and use fans to ventilate. Step away from odours if they become too strong. Disinfectant solutions should always be prepared in well-ventilated areas.Wash your hands after using any disinfectant, including surface wipes. Keep lids tightly closed when not in use. Spills and accidents are more likely to happen when containers are open. Do not allow children to use disinfectant wipes. Keep cleaning fluids and disinfectants out of the reach of children and pets. Throw away disposable items like gloves and masks if they are used during cleaning. Do not clean and re-use.Do not use disinfectant wipes to clean hands or as baby wipes.The minimum recommended personal protective equipment when disinfecting in non-health care settings is rubber gloves, waterproof aprons and closed shoes. Eye protection and medical masks may also be needed to protect against chemicals in use or if there is a risk of splashing.Note: Where cleaning and disinfection are not possible on a regular basis due to resource limitations, frequent hand washing and avoiding touching the face should be the primary prevention approaches to reduce any potential transmission associated with surface contamination."},{"id":60,"category":"Cleaning and disinfecting surfaces in non-health care settings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-cleaning-and-disinfecting-surfaces-in-non-health-care-settings","question":"What is the guidance for the disinfection of outdoor spaces such as open markets, roads?","response":"In outdoor spaces, large-scale spraying or fumigation in areas such as streets or open market places for the COVID-19 virus or other pathogens is not recommended. Streets and sidewalks are not considered as routes of infection for COVID-19. Spraying disinfectants, even outdoors, can be noxious for people’s health and cause eye, respiratory or skin irritation or damage.This practice will be ineffective since the presence of dirt or rubbish for example, inactivates the disinfectant, and manual cleaning to physically remove all matter is not feasible. This is even less effective on porous surfaces such as sidewalks and unpaved walkways. Even in the absence of dirt or rubbish, it is unlikely that chemical spraying would adequately cover surfaces allowing the required contact time to inactivate pathogens."},{"id":61,"category":"Cleaning and disinfecting surfaces in non-health care settings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-cleaning-and-disinfecting-surfaces-in-non-health-care-settings","question":"Are public systems for disinfecting individuals such as spraying via tunnel or chambers safe to use?","response":"No. Spraying of individuals with disinfectants (such as in a tunnel, cabinet, or chamber) is not recommended under any circumstances. This practice could be physically and psychologically harmful and would not reduce an infected person’s ability to spread the virus through droplets or contact. Even if someone who is infected with COVID-19 goes through a disinfection tunnel or chamber, as soon as they start speaking, coughing or sneezing they can still spread the virus.  The toxic effect of spraying with chemicals such as chlorine on individuals can lead to eye and skin irritation, bronchospasm due to inhalation, and potentially gastrointestinal effects such as nausea and vomiting. In addition to health safety concerns, the use of chlorine in large-scale spraying practices may prevent this resource from being used for important interventions such as drinking water treatment and environmental disinfection of health care facilities."},{"id":62,"category":"Cleaning and disinfecting surfaces in non-health care settings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-cleaning-and-disinfecting-surfaces-in-non-health-care-settings","question":"What are the recommended practices once back home after outdoor activities?","response":"Thorough hand hygiene: washing hands with soap and water or using alcohol-based hand gel, should be performed before touching surfaces, items, pets, and people within the household environment. Please see: https://www.who.int/gpsc/clean_hands_protection/en/. While outside, people should always follow physical distancing measures, staying at least one metre from another person; perform hand hygiene by washing hands frequently with soap and water or using alcohol-based hand rub; follow good respiratory hygiene by covering your mouth and nose with your bent elbow or tissue when coughing or sneezing; avoid touching your eyes, nose and mouth; and avoid crowded places."},{"id":63,"category":"Cleaning and disinfecting surfaces in non-health care settings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-cleaning-and-disinfecting-surfaces-in-non-health-care-settings","question":"Are gloves recommended for the community in public spaces to protect against COVID-19, for example when going to the grocery store supermarket?","response":"No. The use of gloves by the public in public spaces is not a recommended or proven prevention measure. Wearing gloves in public spaces does not replace the need for hand hygiene, nor does it offer any additional measure of protection against the COVID-19 virus than hand hygiene. Gloves do not provide complete protection against hand contamination, as pathogens may gain access to the hands via small defects in gloves or by contamination of the hands during glove removal. People can also transfer pathogens from one surface to another by touching with gloved hands, or even transfer pathogens to the mouth, nose, or eyes if they touch their face with gloved hands."},{"id":64,"category":"Cleaning and disinfecting surfaces in non-health care settings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-cleaning-and-disinfecting-surfaces-in-non-health-care-settings","question":"How should I clean food items from the grocery store, for example fruit, vegetables or packaged items?","response":"There is no evidence to date of viruses that cause respiratory illnesses being transmitted via food or food packaging. Coronaviruses cannot multiply in food; they need an animal or human host to multiply.The COVID-19 virus is generally thought to be spread from person to person through respiratory droplets. Currently, there is no evidence to support transmission of the COVID-19 virus associated with food. Before preparing or eating food it is important to always wash your hands with soap and water for at least 40-60 seconds. Regular food safety and handling guidance should be followed.See: https://www.who.int/activities/promoting-safe-food-handling. For food service businesses, please see the below guidance on COVID-19 and Food Safety: https://www.who.int/teams/risk-communication/food-and-agriculture-sectors."},{"id":65,"category":"Climate change","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-climate-change","question":"Where can I find the latest information on COVID-19?","response":"For the latest information on COVID-19, check regularly on the WHO’s coronavirus pages: https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019"},{"id":66,"category":"Climate change","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-climate-change","question":"Do weather and climate determine where COVID-19 occurs?","response":"No. There is currently no conclusive evidence that either weather (short term variations in meteorological conditions) or climate (long-term averages) have a strong influence on transmission. The SARS-CoV-2 virus which causes COVID-19 disease has been transmitted in all regions of the world, from cold and dry, to hot and humid climates.SARS-CoV-2 is thought to be mainly transmitted directly from person-to-person through close contact, or through respiratory droplets produced when an infected person coughs or sneezes. People may be infected by touching exposed surfaces, but this is not thought to be a major transmission route. While temperature and humidity may influence how long the virus survives outside of the human body, this effect is likely to be small compared to the degree of contact between people.Physical distancing and washing hands are therefore essential to breaking the chain of transmission, and are the most effective way to protect yourself, in all locations and all seasons of the year."},{"id":67,"category":"Climate change","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-climate-change","question":"Will climate change make COVID-19 worse?","response":"There is no evidence of a direct connection between climate change and the emergence or transmission of COVID-19 disease. As the disease is now well established in the human population, efforts should focus on reducing transmission and treating patients.However, climate change may indirectly affect the COVID-19 response, as it undermines environmental determinants of health, and places additional stress on health systems. More generally, most emerging infectious diseases, and almost all recent pandemics, originate in wildlife, and there is evidence that increasing human pressure on the natural environment may drive disease emergence. Strengthening health systems, improved surveillance of infectious disease in wildlife, livestock and humans, and greater protection of biodiversity and the natural environment, should reduce the risks of future outbreaks of other new diseases."},{"id":68,"category":"Climate change","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-climate-change","question":"Have measures to contain COVID-19 reduced air pollution and emissions of greenhouse gases?","response":"Air pollution is a serious health risk. It kills approximately 7 million people every year and is responsible for one third of all deaths from stroke, lung cancer and heart disease. Over 90% of the global population lives in places where the WHO outdoor air quality guideline levels are not met, and about two-thirds of this exposure is caused by burning of fossil fuels, which also drives climate change.Efforts to control COVID-19 transmission have reduced economic activity and led to temporary improvements in air quality in some areas. In contrast, as carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases that drive climate change persist for a long time in the atmosphere, temporary emissions reductions only have a limited effect on atmospheric concentrations. Carbon dioxide levels at observing stations around the world in the first months of 2020 have been higher than in 2019.Environmental improvements resulting from the COVID-19 response may be reversed by a rapid expansion of polluting economic activities once the measures have ended, unless there is a clear focus to promote equity, environmental health, around a just transition to a green economy.Any short-term environmental benefits as a result of COVID-19 come at an unacceptable human and economic cost, and are no substitute for planned and sustained action on air quality and climate."},{"id":69,"category":"Climate change","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-climate-change","question":"How does water scarcity affect infectious diseases like COVID-19?","response":"Access to adequate and safe water and sanitation is essential for communities to practice basic hygiene and reduce transmission of COVID-19. Access to these services in health facilities is crucial to preventing infections, reducing the spread of antimicrobial resistance and providing quality care. One in four health care facilities around the world lacks basic water services, directly impacting over two billion people. Around 80% of the world’s population is already experiencing some level of water scarcity. Climate change further threatens the availability of water for consumption, food production, personal hygiene, and medical care, including for infectious disease."},{"id":70,"category":"Climate change","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-climate-change","question":"What can the global response to COVID-19 teach us about our response to climate change?","response":"The COVID-19 pandemic is a Public Health Emergency of International Concern (PHEIC), which has claimed lives, and severely disrupted communities. Climate change is a gradually increasing stress that may be the defining public health threat of the 21st century. Nonetheless, common lessons can be drawn:Ensuring universal health coverage (UHC), through well-resourced, equitable health systems, is essential to protect the public from both short and long-term health threats.Guaranteeing global health security requires an all-hazards approach to preparedness, from infectious disease outbreaks, to extreme weather events, to climate change.  Ensuring access to the environmental determinants of health, such as clean air, water and sanitation, safe and nutritious food, is an essential protection against all health risks. WHO estimates that avoidable environmental risks cause about a quarter of the global health burden.Early action saves lives. Delay in responding to clear evidence of threats, whether from pandemics, or from climate change, increases human and socioeconomic costs. Inequality is a major barrier in ensuring health and wellbeing, especially for the most vulnerable in society. Social and economic inequality manifests in unequal health risks. When faced with public health threats of a global scale, such as COVID-19 or climate change, we are only as strong as our weakest health system."},{"id":71,"category":"Contact tracing","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contact-tracing","question":"What is contact tracing?","response":"Contact tracing is the process of identifying, assessing, and managing people who have been exposed to someone who has been infected with the COVID-19 virus. Contact tracing and quarantine of contacts identified through contact tracing interrupt transmission between people and are essential public health tools for controlling the virus. Contact tracing can also help people who are at a higher risk of developing severe disease know earlier that they have been  exposed so that they can  get medical care quicker if they go on to develop symptoms."},{"id":72,"category":"Contact tracing","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contact-tracing","question":"Can contact tracing help in controlling spread of the virus?","response":"Yes. Contact  tracing is an essential public health tool for controlling infectious disease  outbreaks, such as those caused bythe COVID-19 virus. Contact tracing can break the chains of transmission through the rapid identification, isolation and clinical care of cases, and providing supported quarantine of      contacts, meaning that virus transmission can be stopped."},{"id":73,"category":"Contact tracing","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contact-tracing","question":"Does contact tracing still work against new variants of the COVID-19 virus     ?","response":"Yes, the principles of contact tracing remain the same for  newly identified variants of the COVID-19 virus. While some of the variants of the virus are more transmissible, thorough and timely contact tracing and supported quarantine of contacts is even more important to control the spread of the virus."},{"id":74,"category":"Contact tracing","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contact-tracing","question":"How do I know if I’m a contact? What should I do if I am?","response":"If you think you may be a contact of someone who has  recently been infected, you should be contacted by health authorities to  determine if you meet the contact definition. You may also be informed  directly by someone you were in contact with who later tested positive. If you  have downloaded a COVID-19 proximity tracing application, you may also get  notified through your mobile phone.        If you are  identified as a contact, you should undertake quarantine, which means that you separate yourself from others in your household, stay there and monitor your health for any signs of illness. Some countries have set up dedicated  facilities to enable contacts to complete quarantine outside their household.  Contact your local health authorities to find out how you can safely  quarantine. WHO recommends that you stay in quarantine for 14 days after you were last in contact with the person infected with the COVID-19 virus,  but the duration of quarantine may vary by country. Check with your local or  national health authority."},{"id":75,"category":"Contact tracing","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contact-tracing","question":"How is digital proximity tracing data stored and protected?","response":"The data storage for tracing apps can either be stored and processed on a central server managed by the national public health authority, or stored and processed  on the users’ phones. There is a consensus by several data protection authorities that storing data on  users’ phones enhances privacy, since users have greater control over the amount of information that they share with health authorities. The collection and use of such data by health authorities can therefore be limited to what is strictly necessary for the operation of a digital tracing system.Whichever approach is selected, governments and third parties should ensure digital tracing systems  follow WHO guidance on ethical considerations on the use of digital proximity tracing for COVID-19 contact tracing. Protecting the personal data and privacy of individuals participating in digital tracing is critical to ensure the protection of human rights and civil liberties as well as the establishment of public trust."},{"id":76,"category":"Contact tracing","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contact-tracing","question":"What is quarantine? And how is it different from isolation?","response":"Quarantine is   the separation of contacts from others after exposure to a probable or   confirmed COVID-19 case – you may or may not be infected. Isolation is   the separation of people who are known to be infected with the COVID-19   virusfrom other who are not infected.   Both quarantine and isolation help to stop the spread of the virus."},{"id":77,"category":"Contact tracing","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contact-tracing","question":"How do I manage quarantine and how do I take care of myself during quarantine?","response":"WHO recommends   supported quarantine for 14 days from the last contact with a confirmed case   to minimize risk of infecting others. You should remain separated from others   in the household for the duration of quarantine. If you cannot be in a   separate room, stay at least one metre away from others, the farther the   better. Make sure you have enough foodand water, and a way to communicate with others. The quarantine space should be well ventilated.   You should minimize your contact with others. If you do have someone visit   you during quarantine, you should both wear medical masks, keep windows  open if possible and clean your   hands before and after being together. Ideally, you should have only one visitor   provide food and supplies during the quarantine period and this should be   someone at low risk of developing severe COVID-19.Quarantinemay cause   worry or anxiety, and this is normal. Thiscan also be an opportunity to take time to care for yourself.   Consider reconnecting with loved ones via telephone or phone apps, watch movies or read books, exercise indoors, make   crafts, or catch up on things you haven’t had time for.  To help you get groceries, medicine and   other necessities, ask family and friends or use delivery services.  To learn more about taking care of   yourself during quarantine, watch this video:"},{"id":78,"category":"Contact tracing","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contact-tracing","question":"What can I do as an individual to support contact tracing measures in my community?","response":"Everyone has a part to play to   bring COVID-19 under control, and contact tracing begins with informed, engaged and enabled communities. Understand the local public health and social measures and  collaborate with health authorities for case and contact investigation. Agree  to monitoring, report signs or symptoms of COVID-19  promptly, and be prepared to quarantine or go into isolation if you become a confirmedcase of COVID-19.        In addition, you can, while respecting physical distancing  and all other protective measures, provide support to relatives or friends who  have to be isolated or undertake quarantine. Check in on them by phone  or offer to bring supplies to their house, if needed. Transmission of the COVID-19 virus can only be stopped if we all play our role to protect our family, friends and community."},{"id":79,"category":"Contact tracing","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contact-tracing","question":"If I’m travelling outside my country, do I need to provide accurate information to contact tracing personnel at the airport or at my destination? What if I’m concerned about how my private information is going to be used?","response":"Yes, providing accurate information when requested is important to successful contact tracing   activities. National authorities may ask incoming travelers to report their   health status at the time of travel, possible exposures to confirmed or   probable COVID-19 cases within the previous two weeks, and to provide their contact   details so they can be located for health monitoring or international contact   tracing purposes. Authorities may also require arriving passengers to   download and use a national COVID-19 digital proximity tracing app on   arrival.  Please consult national authorities/airline    companies to verify details before you travel."},{"id":80,"category":"Contact tracing for responders","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-contact-tracing-for-responders","question":"How does contact tracing work?","response":"Contact tracing identifies, and monitors people who have been exposed to someone who has been infected with SARS-CoV-2, and involves several steps: Defining contacts: Contact definitions may vary by country. WHO defines a contact as a person who has been exposed to someone else who has had recent probable or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection: 1. face-to-face contact with a probable or confirmed case within 1  meter and for at least 15 minutes; 2. direct physical contact with a probable  or confirmed case; 3. direct care for a patient with probable or confirmed  COVID-19 disease without the use of recommended PPE; or 4. other situations as  indicated by local risk assessments. Exposure is considered any time between 2 days before to at least 13 days after the case started to show symptoms. For  asymptomatic cases, a contact is anyone who has been exposed between 2 days  before and 10 days after the date on which the sample that led to confirmation  of infection was taken. Identifying contacts: this is usually done through an interview with the person infected with SARS-CoV-2 to find out who they have been in contact with during the period of time described above.  There are other ways to identify contacts depending on the setting, for  example through membership or attendance lists of places the case visited  during the period described above, or through public notices. Digital  proximity tracing applications have also been developed to help identify and  notify contacts through automated processes.  Informing contacts: each identified contact should be contacted to confirm whether they meet the definition of a contact. This  may be done through health authorities and/or via digital tracing proximity  applications. Cases may also be encouraged to  inform their own contacts. Each person identified as a contact will be informed about the goal of contact tracing, the process (including how their personal data will be protected), how to undertake quarantine and for how long, and who to contact with any concerns or questions. Additional information should be provided on symptoms to monitor throughout the quarantine period, and what to do if a contact returns  a positive test or becomes unwell. Managing and monitoring contacts: contacts should be encouraged and supported during the  quarantine period. WHO recommends that the quarantine period ends 14 days after the contact was last exposed to the person who has been infected with SARS-CoV-2. However, the duration of the quarantine period may vary between countries. Data processes and analysis: The information collected from each contact is stored in a secure database. These processes vary from country to country. See question What should be considered for data protection?"},{"id":81,"category":"Contact tracing for responders","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-contact-tracing-for-responders","question":"Who is defined as a contact?","response":"A contact is currently   defined as anyone who had direct  contact with, or was  within 1 metre for at least 15 minutes, with a person who may be infected or  is infected with SARS-CoV-2 while they were infectious or potentially   infectious, even if the person with  the infection did not have symptoms. National and local public health   authorities may have additional considerations to define contacts according   to local risk assessments.Contacts should be supported  to quarantine to limit the possibility of exposing other people to infection      if they become ill.(The complete definition of a  contact can be found here)."},{"id":82,"category":"Contact tracing for responders","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-contact-tracing-for-responders","question":"What is backward contact tracing?","response":"Backward contact tracing refers to the process of trying to understand how the case   became infected, also known as case or source investigation. While   traditional contact tracing identifies people who were exposed to cases and may   become cases themselves, backward contact tracing or source investigation   looks back in time to identify settings or events where exposure to the virus   may have occurred. This may help public health authorities identify more cases (such as at an event or setting where the case may have   been infected) and identify settings that have led to infection. This can   inform the development of targeted public health and social measures to   reduce the overall number of cases."},{"id":83,"category":"Contact tracing for responders","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-contact-tracing-for-responders","question":"When should contact tracing be implemented?","response":"Comprehensive contact tracing should be implemented each time cases or clusters (groups of  linked cases) are identified. During intense transmission, contact tracing capacities may be overwhelmed, so contact tracing     activities may  focus on household contacts, healthcare workerscontacts, contacts in high-risk closed settings (such as dormitories, institutions, long-term living facilities),and contacts at higher risk of developing severe COVID-19. It is important to maintain contact tracing and quarantine of contacts even when the number of new cases may be decreasing, and/or public health and social measures may be being relaxed, in order to ensure that transmission continues to reduce."},{"id":84,"category":"Contact tracing for responders","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-contact-tracing-for-responders","question":"How do you form a contact tracing workforce?","response":"A contact tracing workforce can be   drawn from many settings, including individuals connected with local   government, civil society, non-governmental organizations, universities and   community volunteers. Ideally, a gender-balanced contact tracing team should   be recruited from the community and have general literacy, strong   communication skills, local language proficiency and an understanding of the   local context and culture.They should be provided with   adequate training to ensure efficiency, accuracy and good communication   skills when implementing case and contact investigations, and integrated   within the wider COVID-19 response team.Several training materials have   been developed by WHO and partners and may be adapted to local needs. Many   are available through the Global Outbreak Alert and Response Network (GOARN) knowledge platform, and OpenWHO. Training should include the basics of virus   transmission, prevention and control measures; how to monitor signs and   symptoms; and standard operating procedures for contact tracing, including   interview tips and ethics of public health surveillance and quarantine.   Contact tracers should also be briefed on their rights, roles and   responsibilities, including for occupational safety and health.It is important for public health   authorities to train the contact tracing workforce when there is no or low   transmission, and anticipate ways to be able to scale the size of the trained   contact tracing workforce, if transmission increases."},{"id":85,"category":"Contact tracing for responders","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-contact-tracing-for-responders","question":"What are some of the challenges to effective contact tracing for COVID-19?","response":"Some of the   challenges are the availability of a trained contact tracing workforce,   availability of resources for contact tracing and community engagement.Another main challenge is the intensity of the COVID-19   transmission. In situations of intense transmission, public health resources   can quickly become overwhelmed and often cannot cope with the workload of   identifying contacts and monitoring them. In such situations, WHO recommends   focusing on the contacts with highest exposure and those most at risk of   developing severe disease."},{"id":86,"category":"Contact tracing for responders","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-contact-tracing-for-responders","question":"What are some digital tools used to support contact tracing? How can they enhance contact tracing processes?","response":"Classic interview-based contact tracing  relies heavily on the presence of a trained workforce to carry out      essential activities such as contact elicitation,  notification and follow-up. However, this workforce can be quickly overwhelmed  in the context of widespread SARS-CoV-2 transmission. Electronic tools and information technology have been  used to enhance the efficiency of contact tracing processes, and are currently being used  in the COVID-19 pandemic.  So far, no single digital tool addresses  all the steps required to monitor end-to-end contact tracing and quarantine of  contacts. Oversight from public health workforce is still required. The  technical and ethical requirements related to the use of such digital tools should be considered  when making decisions as to the use of  these tools. Digital tools that support contact tracing processes may be  broadly divided into three categories based on their public health function  during specific steps of the contact tracing process:Identifying and  notifying contacts: These solutions are  intended for use by the general public, health professionals and the contact  tracing team. They include digital proximity tracing tools that use systems based on Bluetooth or GPS  location signaling, to notify users who have been in close proximity and  prolonged contact to individuals who tested positive for COVID-19 and  registered their status in the tool. There are also location-based digital contract tracing tools that use quick  response (QR) codes that can be scanned by smartphones users when they visit a  venue, so that if they later test positive for COVID-19, other application  users who attended the same venue, at the same time may be sent an alert, if  local public health authorities deem it necessary.Monitoring contacts: These tools are intended for use by those   identified as contacts, health professionals and the contact tracing team.   They include symptoms checker tools that can help contacts  to self-monitor   and report the presence or absence of symptoms to health professionals who may   conduct further assessments, health counselling and connect them with the public   health authorities for testing and other supportive services. These tools may   be particularly helpful in settings where contact tracing workforce personnel   may be limited and/or there are physical or security barriers preventing in-person   visits by contact tracing teams.Surveillance data management and analysis:  These solutions   are used by public health professionals to collect, manage, analyse and   visualize data collected by contact tracing teams which link cases and   contacts. They include outbreak response tools (such as Go.Data, Commcare, SORMAS, etc.) that can be used   for case investigation, listing and monitoring of contacts, and analysis. It is important to note that these tools cannot  substitute a well-trained health and community workforce, qualified  supervisors, decentralized operations and good coordination; which are all  necessary criteria for successful and effective contract tracing. More information  on digital tools for contact tracing can be accessed here and ethical considerations to guide the use of digital proximity tracking  technologies is available here."},{"id":87,"category":"Contact tracing for responders","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-contact-tracing-for-responders","question":"What should be considered for data protection?","response":"The ethics of public health information, data protection, and data privacy must be considered at all levels of contact tracing activities, including training and use of tools. In particular:Safeguards must be in place to guarantee privacy and data protection in accordance with the legal frameworks of the countries where systems are implemented.Everyone involved in contact tracing must adhere to the ethical principles of handling personal information, to ensure responsible data management and respect for privacy throughout the process.How data will be handled, stored, and used needs to be communicated to those concerned in a clear and transparent manner. This is important for buy-in and engagement as well as to avoid misperceptions that could jeopardize the effectiveness of a contact tracing programme.Digital tools used for contact tracing should be assessed before use to ensure safeguarding data protection according to national regulations.See WHO’s interim guidance   on ethical considerations to guide the use of digital   proximity tracking technologies for COVID-19 contact tracing."},{"id":88,"category":"Contraception and family planning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contraception-and-family-planning","question":"Is contraception/ family planning safe to use during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"Yes. All modern methods of contraception are safe to use, including during the COVID-19 pandemic.  If you have had a baby in the last six months or have a health condition, such as diabetes, high blood pressure, or breast cancer – or if you smoke – seek advice from a health care professional to ensure you are using a method of contraception which is suitable and safe for you."},{"id":89,"category":"Contraception and family planning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contraception-and-family-planning","question":"I want to avoid getting pregnant during the COVID-19 pandemic. What can I do?","response":"If you do not want to become pregnant, you should start or continue to use your contraceptive method of choice. You may be able to access information and contraceptive services from a healthcare provider by phone or online.  If you cannot access these services you may opt for a method that is available without a prescription (such as condoms, spermicides, diaphragm, pills, or emergency contraceptive pills) from a nearby pharmacy or drug shop."},{"id":90,"category":"Contraception and family planning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contraception-and-family-planning","question":"I can’t access my contraceptive method of choice. What do you advise?","response":"If you cannot access your contraceptive method of choice – perhaps because it requires a prescription, or because it can only be given to you by a health worker – consider using condoms, fertility awareness-based methods, lactational amenorrhea (if you are exclusively breastfeeding), or other contraceptive methods that are recommended for self-care in your country.  Depending on the situation in your country, methods recommended for self-care could include the pill or mini-pill, emergency contraception pills, and DMPA-SC (Sayana Press®)."},{"id":91,"category":"Contraception and family planning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contraception-and-family-planning","question":"What is the best contraceptive method to use during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"All modern methods of contraception help to prevent pregnancy. Women and their partners can choose any modern contraceptive method that is acceptable to and safe for them. The best method of contraception is the one that works well for you.  There is a wide variety of modern methods, one of which may suit you best.  For more information see here.  Condoms, when they are used consistently and correctly, are the only method of contraception that help to prevent unintended pregnancy and protect against sexually transmitted infections, including HIV.  They can be used together with other methods of contraception to protect against both unintended pregnancy and sexually transmitted infections. Emergency contraceptive pills can prevent up to 95% of pregnancies when taken within 5 days after intercourse, and they can be taken by anyone with or without a health condition."},{"id":92,"category":"Contraception and family planning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contraception-and-family-planning","question":"I want to change my contraceptive method – is this possible?","response":"Yes. It may be difficult however, to access all the methods of contraception that are normally available in your country due to restrictions on movement, lack of supply, as well as increased demands on health providers and services. If you are experiencing side effects or desire urgent removal for other reasons, contact a provider to find out what options suit you best, and which are available and feasible.If you have a pre-existing health condition, consult a provider to find out what options suit you best, and which are available and feasible. Seek advice and information from your health provider and consider using methods that do not have medical restrictions like minipills, condoms, fertility awareness-based methods, diaphragm, spermicides or lactational amenorrhea if you are exclusively breastfeeding."},{"id":93,"category":"Contraception and family planning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contraception-and-family-planning","question":"I want to remove or replace my implant or IUD – can I do this during COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"Removal of long acting methods such as implants or IUDs, after the recommended period of use (and routine follow up appointments) may not be prioritized by your country’s health system during this health emergency. Seek advice from your health provider. If, due to restrictions on movement due to the COVID-19 pandemic you cannot have your long acting method removed straight away, it is important to use another method of contraception to avoid pregnancy at this time.   There are no medical problems caused by delaying removal of long acting methods such as implants or IUDs. Do not try to remove the contraception method yourself; wait until you are able to access health care from a trained provider."},{"id":94,"category":"Contraception and family planning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contraception-and-family-planning","question":"Why is providing contraception/ family planning, as well as family planning services and information, important during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"Contraception and family planning information and services are life-saving and important at all times. Sexual activity does not cease with the COVID-19 pandemic, it is therefore crucial to ensure that people are able to access rights-based services and information to initiate and / or continue use of contraception. By preventing unintended pregnancies, contraception helps to protect girls and women from the negative health consequences of unintended pregnancies, which can save their lives. Contraception reduces the need for abortion, meaning that women and girls are less at risk of unsafe abortion, which again can be lifesaving.  Condoms, when used consistently and correctly, help to prevent both unintended pregnancies and sexually transmitted infections (including HIV).  In addition, by preventing the negative health consequences associated with unintended pregnancies, unsafe abortion and sexually transmitted infections (including HIV), contraception can help alleviate unnecessary additional pressure on already-stretched health systems which are working hard to address COVID-19."},{"id":95,"category":"Contraception and family planning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contraception-and-family-planning","question":"I am a policy maker. What can I do to make sure people can access contraception and family planning information and services?","response":"Plan and develop innovative strategies to ensure as many eligible people as possible can access information and contraception during this period.Increase use of mobile phones and digital technologies to help people make decisions about which contraceptive methods to use, and how they can be accessed. Enable health care workers to provide contraceptive information and services as per national guidelines to the full extent possible. This is particularly important where pregnancy poses a high risk to health.  Expand availability of contraceptive services (including both information and methods) through places other than healthcare facilities, such as pharmacies, drug shops, online platforms and other outlets.  This can be with or without prescription depending on national guidelines and contraceptive method.  Relax restrictions on the number of repeat issues of prescription-only hormonal contraceptives that can be issued.Ensure access to emergency post-coital contraception, including consideration of over the counter provision.Enable access to contraception for women and girls in the immediate post-partum and post abortion periods when they may access health services."},{"id":96,"category":"Contraception and family planning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contraception-and-family-planning","question":"I am a programme manager. What can I do to help people access contraception and family planning information and services?","response":"Increase use of telehealth for counselling and sharing of messages related to safe and effective use of contraception and for selection and initiation of contraceptives.Ensure adequate inventory to avoid potential stock outs at all levels of the health system.Prepare advisories for users on how they can access contraceptive information, services and supplies.Monitor contraceptive consumption in your area to identify any potential pitfall and shortageIncrease availability and access to the contraceptives which can be used by the client without service provider support."},{"id":97,"category":"Contraception and family planning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-contraception-and-family-planning","question":"I am a healthcare provider. I have heard that persons with COVID-19 may have increased risk of blood clots. How should I advise individuals who are using or want to use combined hormonal contraception?","response":"According to currently available evidence, most women of childbearing age with COVID-19 will likely be asymptomatic or have mild COVID-19 symptoms and should continue to take combined hormonal contraception (CHC). Here are the most common possible scenarios: Women who are asymptomatic or with mild symptoms of known COVID-19: combined hormonal contraception can be continued and is considered safe in this population. If women are concerned, their provider should explain that there is no evidence of increased risk of thrombosis among combined hormonal contraception users with mild COVID-19 symptoms. If a combined hormonal contraception user wishes to discontinue this method, she can be offered a progestin-only or non-hormonal method, if available and acceptable. Women with serious symptoms[1] of COVID-19 who are not hospitalized: Discontinuation of combined hormonal contraception should be considered, based on a patient’s clinical symptoms of COVID-19 (e.g. immobilization for more than 7 days, difficulty breathing or shortness of breath, pneumonia). Considerations around stopping combined hormonal contraception should also take into account if the user has other medical conditions that may increase the risk of thrombosis during COVID-19. If combined hormonal contraception is discontinued, progestin-only or non-hormonal methods can be offered, if available and acceptable. Women hospitalized with severe COVID-19: Combined hormonal contraception should be discontinued during hospitalisation. The risk of thrombosis in this acutely ill population may outweigh the benefits of continuing combined hormonal contraception. Progestin-only and non-hormonal contraceptive methods can be used. Women resuming contraception: It is important that all women who discontinue contraception during COVID-19 illness are given counselling about when to resume contraception and are provided with the method of their choice. Any new or existing medical conditions need to be considered when choosing a contraceptive method. Combined hormonal contraception can be resumed 2 weeks after any prolonged period of prolonged limited mobility (immobilization). the end of immobilization. Other methods can be started without delay.  [1] Serious symptoms may include difficulty breathing or shortness of breath, chest pain or pressure, or loss of speech or movement. Coronavirus. In: World Health Organization/Health topics [website]. Geneva: World Health Organization. (https://www.who.int/health-topics/coronavirus#tab=tab_3, accessed 5 November 2020)."},{"id":98,"category":"COVID-19 vaccines and people living with HIV","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-covid-19-vaccines-and-people-living-with-hiv","question":"Are COVID-19 vaccines safe for people living with HIV?","response":"Many of the COVID-19 vaccines studies have included a small number of people living with HIV in their trials. Despite limited data, available information suggests current WHO recommended COVID-19 vaccines (Pfizer/BioNtech, Oxford/AstraZeneca, Johnson&Johnson) are safe for people living with HIV. The currently available vaccine products are not live vaccines, they include genetic material from SARS-CoV-2 which cannot replicate. Therefore these vaccines are not expected to be less safe in people who are immunocompromised. In addition to this, no pharmacological interactions have been reported between COVID-19 vaccines and antiretroviral medications which people living with HIV should continue to take after vaccination to maintain health. Recently, a debate in the scientific literature has led to broader concerns about a potential association observed more than a decade ago between adenovirus vector-based vaccines and an increased risk of acquiring HIV infection among men who received this type of vaccine[1]. This unexpected finding was detected in two HIV vaccine trials that used adenovirus vector containing products[2],[3]. The reason for this observed HIV risk remains uncertain, although several follow-up studies have suggested a possible interference in the HIV specific vaccine response or in the CD4 cell susceptibility to HIV infection induced by this kind of vaccine[4],[5]. However, a third study using another adenovirus vector-based vaccine, conducted more recently has not reported this finding[6]. Specific studies on this topic with COVID-19 vaccines are needed. Despite these potential concerns, it is important to highlight that the benefits of all authorized COVID-19 vaccines in a pandemic context currently outweigh the potential risks. WHO will continue to monitor the situation as new data become available and SAGE recommendations will be updated accordingly."},{"id":99,"category":"COVID-19 vaccines and people living with HIV","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-covid-19-vaccines-and-people-living-with-hiv","question":"Do COVID-19 vaccines provide protection for people living with HIV?","response":"It is theoretically possible that people living with HIV with low CD4 cell counts might have a weaker immune response to vaccines. However, in practice this has not been documented for all vaccines and there is no evidence to support a less robust immune response to COVID-19 vaccines among people living with HIV and low CD4 cell counts. WHO is reviewing new evidence as it emerges and will provide updates.  More importantly, advocacy is needed so that no one person is left behind and that national COVID-19 vaccination programmes do not exclude people from key and vulnerable populations, at risk of HIV, who may have limited access to health services. It is also important to advocate for the inclusion of people living with HIV, including those with more advanced disease, in COVID-19 vaccine trials to provide information to confirm efficacy."},{"id":100,"category":"COVID-19 vaccines and people living with HIV","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-covid-19-vaccines-and-people-living-with-hiv","question":"Should people living with HIV get vaccines early in the roll out?","response":"WHO recommends that countries refer to the WHO SAGE Roadmap For Prioritizing Uses Of COVID-19 Vaccines In The Context Of Limited Supply[7] which was created under the assumption  that there would not be substantive differences in vaccine efficacy among subgroups (for example, in people with comorbidities that increase the risk of severe COVID-19 such as HIV-positive status). Therefore countries can make plans for people to receive the vaccine in order of priority based on their age, health, occupation and other factors such as people in living in care or residential homes, or closed settings such as prisons. Some countries are prioritizing vaccination for all people living with HIV or for those who are immunocompromised (as indicated by having a CD4 cell count <200/mm3) [8],[9]. An informal poll of 52 countries revealed 24 that have an immunization policy that prioritizes vaccinations for people living with HIV. These policies are supported by recent literature which suggests that people living with HIV at any CD4 count appear to be at increased risk for severe outcomes and death due to COVID-19 compared with people without HIV[10],[11],[12]. Independent of the immune status, many people living with HIV have one or more comorbidities that may put them at increased risk for a more severe COVID-19. Therefore, people living with HIV with co-morbidities (such as COPD, asthma, diabetes, heart disease, kidney disease, liver disease, Parkinson’s disease, multiple sclerosis, motor neurone disease, severe obesity) should be prioritized for early vaccination in most settings. People living with HIV should not be excluded from COVID-19 vaccine access plans regardless of their immune status, and countries ought to consider including people living with HIV as a priority group for COVID-19 vaccination according to their epidemiological context."},{"id":101,"category":"COVID-19 vaccines and people living with HIV","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-covid-19-vaccines-and-people-living-with-hiv","question":"What can WHO and the world do to support people living with HIV to live a healthy life?","response":"While WHO is working with countries to ensure fair and equitable access to safe and effective COVID-19 vaccines, it is important to continue actions to prevent SARS-CoV-2 transmission and to reduce COVID-19 deaths. Alongside the response to COVID-19, it is critical to maintain access to essential health services. This includes:Supporting people living with HIV to continue taking antiretroviral therapy (ART) and adapting services to make this easier and more efficient during the COVID-19 response. Continuing to provide HIV prevention and testing services with linkage to ART initiation as a priority. Ensuring those who start ART can remain on it to reduce health risks and complications during COVID-19. This must be classified as an essential service, together with prevention, diagnosis and treatment of co-morbidities and co-infections.  Monitoring all people living with HIV and SARS-CoV-2 infections, especially those with advanced HIV disease or with co-morbidities.Although there may be an increase in the risk of developing severe disease from COVID-19 among people living with HIV, making sure that people have access to effective ART and other health care they need will help to minimize this risk. For further information on COVID-19 vaccines and all WHO guidance related to COVID-19 see https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance.For community friendly resources please see: https://i-base.info/covid-19/"},{"id":102,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"What is dexamethasone and does it work against COVID-19?","response":"Dexamethasone is a corticosteroid used in a wide range of conditions for its anti-inflammatory and immunosuppressant effects.It was tested in hospitalized patients with COVID-19 in the United Kingdom’s national clinical trial RECOVERY and was found to have benefits for critically ill patients.According to preliminary findings shared with WHO (and now available as a preprint), for patients on ventilators, the treatment was shown to reduce mortality by about one third, and for patients requiring only oxygen, mortality was cut by about one fifth."},{"id":103,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"Were all patients in RECOVERY given dexamethasone?","response":"Eligible patients were randomly allocated between several treatment arms. Dexamethasone was administered as an oral (liquid or tablets) or intravenous preparation, at a dose of 6 mg once daily for ten days, in one of the arms.In pregnancy or breastfeeding women, patients were randomized to prednisolone (a milder corticosteroid) 40 mg administered by mouth."},{"id":104,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"Does WHO recommend the use of dexamethasone for COVID-19 patients?","response":"On 2 September 2020, WHO issued an interim guideline on the use of dexamethasone and other corticosteroids for the treatment of COVID-19. The guidelines were developed by a panel of WHO and international experts and investigators and is based on evidence collected from seven clinical trials.\n\n\nThe guidelines make two recommendations:\n\n\nRecommendation 1:\n\n\nWHO strongly recommends that corticosteroids (i.e. dexamethasone, hydrocortisone or prednisone) be given orally or intravenously for the treatment of patients with severe and critical COVID-19.\n\n\nRecommendation 2:\n\n\nWHO advises against the use of corticosteroids in the treatment of patients with non-severe COVID-19, unless the patient is already taking this medication for another condition.\n\n\nTime and duration of medication should be once daily for 7-10 days.\n\n\nDaily dose should be 6 mg of dexamethasone, equivalent to 160 mg of hydrocortisone (i.e. 50 mg every 8 hours or 100 mg every 12 hours), 40 mg of prednisone, 32 mg of methylprednisolone (8 mg every 6 hours).\n\n\nThe panel of experts made its recommendation on the basis of the moderate certainty evidence of a mortality reduction of 8.7% and 6.7% in patients with COVID-19 who are critically or severely ill."},{"id":105,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"Is dexamethasone on the WHO Essential Medicines List?","response":"Yes, dexamethasone has been on the WHO Model List of Essential Medicines (EML) since 1977 for several indications in multiple formulations. Since 2013, dexamethasone (Injectable formulation) has been indicated for respiratory distress syndrome in new-borns. Prednisolone is also on the EML and was included in 1984.Dexamethasone and prednisolone are included on the EML for the following indications:allergic or hypersensitivity conditions, without further specifying the typepain and oedema due to malignancy in palliative carenausea and vomiting,as part of treatment protocols for some blood tissue cancers.These indications are broad and can also include cytokine-related lung injury and as prevention or treatment of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) associated with severe acute respiratory infections (i.e. viral pneumonia). Both medicines are also recommended in children."},{"id":106,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"Is dexamethasone prequalified by WHO?","response":"Yes, dexamethasone solution for injection 4mg/ml in 1ml ampoules, manufactured by Kern Pharma SL, Spain, has been prequalified for its use in the management of diseases associated with HIV/AIDS, but not for COVID-19.Another dexamethasone injection product is currently under assessment.Manufacturers interested in prequalifying their product can contact the Prequalification Team at [email protected]  for further information."},{"id":107,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"What dose was used in the Recovery trial?","response":"Dexamethasone was used in the Recovery Trial in oral (liquid or tablets) or intravenous preparation 6 mg once daily for ten days.In pregnancy or breastfeeding women, prednisolone 40 mg administered by mouth (or intravenous hydrocortisone 80 mg twice daily) should be used instead of dexamethasone.Note: It is permitted to switch between the two routes of administration according to clinical circumstances.Source: Page 9 of 35 RECOVERY [V6.0 2020-05-14] ISRCTN50189673 EudraCT 2020-001113-21"},{"id":108,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"What are the typical side effects of dexamethasone?","response":"Dexamethasone is generally safe. It presents a favourable benefit-risk profile, particularly in patients with severe forms of pneumonia, while the benefit is less prominent in patients with non-severe pneumonia. As the treatment is short, even at high doses, corticosteroids are not associated with serious side effects. Potentially higher blood glucose levels (hyperglycaemia) are temporary.Prolonged use (I.e., used for more than two weeks) may be associated with adverse events such as glaucoma, cataract, fluid retention, hypertension, psychological effects (e.g., mood swings, memory issues, confusion or irritation), weight gain, or increased risk of infections and osteoporosis.To reiterate: All these adverse events are not associated with short term use (with the exception of hyperglycaemia that can worsen diabetes)."},{"id":109,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"How do the doses used in the RECOVERY trial compare with those used normally?","response":"The Recovery trial used dexamethasone 6mg daily oral or intravenous for ten days. Higher daily doses of dexamethasone have been used for other indications for a long time and are known to be safe."},{"id":110,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"Can steroids be used in the elderly/children/pregnancy?","response":"They can be used in children and the elderly. In pregnancy, the Recovery trial used prednisolone orally or hydrocortisone by intravenous infusion instead of dexamethasone. Steroids are ubiquitous in terms of geographic use."},{"id":111,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"Is dexamethasone available across the world?","response":"Yes. Dexamethasone is off-patent and has been marketed in different formulations (e.g., tablets, liquid, solution for injection) for many years. It is generally available in most countries. There are several manufacturers of the product. One manufacturer has already been prequalified by WHO (Kern Pharma in Spain) while another is under assessment.The most common formulations are:Tablets: 0.5mg, 0.75mg, 1mg, 1.5mg, 2mg, 4mg and 6mgOral Solution: 0.5mg/5ml, 20mg/5ml and 1mg/ml (concentrate) Injectable suspension: 4mg/ml, 20mg/5mlIn recent years there have been occasional reports of shortages of this product. It is important to quickly understand the projected volumes for COVID-19 utilization and manufacturing capacity to help assess the impact for existing indications and the potential need for substitute therapies, to ensure all patients retain access to a safe, effective, quality, affordable product to meet their therapeutic needs."},{"id":112,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"How many API suppliers are there?","response":"There are many manufacturers of Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients (API) around the world, ensuring a large and diversified capacity of production for this product. So far, we have identified ten potentially quality approved suppliers from Asia, North America, and Europe."},{"id":113,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"Is dexamethasone affordable/what is the price per treatment?","response":"Dexamethasone is an off-patent, common supportive treatment option and is generally affordable. WHO 2016 and 2019 surveys of different health facilities in low- and middle-income countries indicate that dexamethasone was available to patients at a median price of $0.33 per 4mg/ml injection ampoules (range: US$0.13-$3.5). Major UN procurers may be able to supply dexamethasone for a median price of $0.092 per 4mg/ml injection ampoule."},{"id":114,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"Are there any import restrictions?","response":"There are likely no restrictions, as dexamethasone is authorized worldwide."},{"id":115,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"What are the risks of Substandard or Falsified (SF) products?","response":"There are 21 records of falsified dexamethasone in the WHO Global Surveillance and Monitoring System database with the most recent one received from the Eastern Mediterranean in February 2020.It is expected that, following the high level of publicity given to the medicines, incidents of substandard and/or falsified dexamethasone products will occur. This is based on experience with reports of falsified chloroquine products when hydroxychloroquine was thought to be a potential treatment for COVID19Increased vigilance throughout all supply chains and due diligence in any procurement activities are essential. Member States and regulatory authorities are encouraged to promptly report any incidents of substandard or falsified dexamethasone to the WHO global surveillance and monitoring system."},{"id":116,"category":"Dexamethasone","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-dexamethasone","question":"What is the worldwide production capacity?","response":"Work is ongoing to determine producers of licensed and quality assured products. Further assessments of additional production capacity will be undertaken."},{"id":117,"category":"Environmental Surveillance","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/environmental-surveillance","question":"Why is environmental surveillance of wastewater important during disease outbreaks?","response":"Testing wastewater has a long history of use in public health. Environmental surveillance is already used to detect poliovirus in high risk settings, monitor antimicrobial resistance and complement surveillance for other public health programmes."},{"id":118,"category":"Environmental Surveillance","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/environmental-surveillance","question":"How is wastewater testing used for COVID-19?","response":"Wastewater testing can be used to monitor the presence of SARS-CoV-2 virus in untreated sewage.  Several countries are monitoring wastewater for SARS-CoV-2 virus, the virus that causes COVID-19, in a range of locations for different purposes. These include:early warning for COVID-19 cases in a community;detection of COVID-19 in locations with weak clinical surveillance;monitoring circulation of the virus during outbreaks; orto trigger case-finding in locations where there are or may be suspected cases, such as quarantine hotels, university campuses or prisons. Some countries are also analysing historical wastewater samples for evidence of past SARS-CoV-2 circulation."},{"id":119,"category":"Environmental Surveillance","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/environmental-surveillance","question":"What does it mean when a wastewater sample tests positive for SARS-CoV-2?","response":"Molecular tests such as polymerase chain reaction (PCR) tests can detect the presence of the SARS-CoV-2 virus via fragments of genetic material (RNA) in wastewater. Finding this RNA in wastewater means that one or more people in the community likely excreted virus through urine, faeces or by coughing or sneezing. The RNA suggests that the virus was in the community at the time it was excreted. However, the wastewater test does not identify who was or is infected or indicate if the persons excreting the virus are still infectious to others."},{"id":120,"category":"Environmental Surveillance","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/environmental-surveillance","question":"Can I get sick with COVID-19 through contact with urine, faeces or sewage?","response":"While fragments of SARS-CoV-2 genetic material (RNA) have been detected in the urine or faeces of some patients, there have been no reports to date of transmission of COVID-19 through urine or faeces. It remains important to protect yourself with personal protective equipment whenever contact with bodily fluids may occur and to clean your hands frequentlyInfectious SARS-CoV-2 has also not been detected in wastewater, suggesting transmission through contact or contamination with sewage is highly unlikely.Guidance for water, sanitation, hygiene and waste management can be found here."},{"id":121,"category":"Environmental Surveillance","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/environmental-surveillance","question":"Can I get sick with COVID-19 from swimming in the sea, rivers, lakes or swimming pools?","response":"Available evidence suggests that SARS-CoV-2 does not spread from water. Natural bodies of water and swimming pools do not appear to pose a risk for COVID-19 transmission even if polluted by faeces or wastewater. Pools are usually treated regularly to prevent contamination with a range of pathogens which could be present.However, crowded beaches or swimming pools do pose a risk of spreading COVID-19 through close contact with infected people or contaminated surfaces. To reduce the risk of this transmission, clean hands frequently, stay at least 1 metre away from others in and out of the water, and wear a mask when this distancing is not possible."},{"id":122,"category":"Environmental Surveillance","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/environmental-surveillance","question":"Can I get sick with COVID-19 from drinking water?","response":"The risk coronaviruses pose to drinking water is considered to be low and SARS-CoV-2 virus has not been detected in drinking water supplies.Drinking water treatment methods neutralize infectious pathogens present in the water. SARS-CoV-2 is an enveloped virus, which means it has a fragile fatty envelope that is easily destroyed by the treatment process. Therefore, treated drinking water does not pose a risk for COVID-19."},{"id":123,"category":"Environmental Surveillance","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/environmental-surveillance","question":"Can wastewater testing be conducted in low-resource settings?","response":"Putting in place wastewater testing requires a good understanding of how environmental surveillance could add value in monitoring the spread of disease. The laboratory capacity needed to test wastewater samples may be limited in some settings. Clinical testing and epidemiological surveillance are higher priority strategies, as they lead directly to public health measures that can reduce transmission. Water, sanitation and hygiene (WASH) activities are also top public health priorities, such as ensuring access to hand washing facilities for all. The cost-benefit of wastewater testing relative to other public health measures should be carefully evaluated."},{"id":124,"category":"Environmental Surveillance","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/environmental-surveillance","question":"Does WHO recommend environmental surveillance of wastewater for COVID-19?","response":"At present more evidence is needed regarding use of environmental surveillance for COVID-19. Wastewater monitoring may be considered as an optional and complementary approach to COVID-19 surveillance in addition to more standard clinical surveillance.  Scientists and public health authorities continue to assess effectiveness and validate testing methods in different settings. WHO encourages efforts to continue to explore potential uses of wastewater testing and recognizes its potential as an emerging tool for improving control of COVID-19."},{"id":125,"category":"Ethics, resource allocation and priority setting","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ethics-resource-allocation-and-priority-setting","question":"Can I adapt previous frameworks for pandemic influenza to guide resource allocation for COVID-19?","response":"Many ethical frameworks have been produced for resource allocation, some of which have\r\nbeen included in pandemic plans. Those frameworks provide useful guidance in the current\r\nscenario. Yet, when applying them, we must take into account the type of health care\r\nresource, the context, and the stage of the pandemic. That is, while the ethical principles that\r\napply to resource allocation might be the same in different pandemics, they can lead to\r\ndifferent decisions, given contextual circumstances. For example, this pandemic appears to\r\nsignificantly impact older adults (those 60 years of age or older), and such characteristics are\r\nrelevant to shaping priorities for the allocation of resources during COVID-19. As a result, it\r\nmay be inappropriate to use critical care triage guidelines that have age cut-offs that\r\ndeprioritize or exclude those aged over 60 years.When applying ethical guidelines for resource allocation, we should consider the extent to\r\nwhich resources are overwhelmed in the current context. It would be inappropriate, for\r\ninstance, to exclude population groups from being allocated a resource (for example,\r\nventilators) at the outset of a pandemic when capacity remains. When resources are scarce,\r\nthough – when there is an insufficient supply to meet everyone’s needs – resource allocation\r\nshould be guided by well established, broadly applicable ethical principles, unless there are\r\ncharacteristics of the outbreak that justify different courses of action. Irrelevant\r\ncharacteristics of populations within countries, such as ethnicity, race or creed, should play\r\nno role in any resource allocation in any pandemic. This reflects our commitment to treating\r\npeople with equal respect."},{"id":126,"category":"Ethics, resource allocation and priority setting","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ethics-resource-allocation-and-priority-setting","question":"Are the ethical considerations the same for all medical countermeasures, including therapeutics, vaccines and personal protective equipment (PPE)?","response":"Generally, the considerations may be different. The allocation of different resources may find\r\nethical justifications in different principles or values. For instance, once a novel vaccine is\r\nfound to be safe and effective, to prioritize those at highest risk, as well as populations like\r\nhealth care workers who may be more likely to serve as vectors for transmission, is justified.Within those subgroups, some suggest that a lottery-based (i.e., random) allocation may be\r\njustified, given that resources will be limited and we can assume nearly equal benefits will be\r\nderived from any recipient within that group. This is not the case, however, for other\r\nresources such as ventilators, where some individuals may derive significantly more benefit\r\nthan others."},{"id":127,"category":"Ethics, resource allocation and priority setting","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ethics-resource-allocation-and-priority-setting","question":"What is the basis for deciding who should have priority access to scarce resources?","response":"The ethical basis for deciding which individuals or groups might be prioritized, including the principles to be applied, are presented in the below table:Ethical considerations when deciding who to prioritizePrincipleDescriptionPractice implicationEqualityEach person’s interest should count equally unless there are good reasons that justify the differential prioritization of resources.\r\n                Irrelevant characteristics of individuals, such as race, ethnicity, creed, ability or gender, should not serve arbitrarily as the basis for the differential allocation of resources.\r\n                This principle can be used to justify the allocation of resources by a lottery – that is, randomly by chance – or by a system of first come, first served. May be most appropriate to guide the allocation of scarce resources among individuals or populations who can be expected to derive the same benefit from the resource, for example, vaccines among high-risk populations, or ventilators among\r\n                    those with similar clinical indicators for benefit.Best outcomes (utility)This principle can be used to justify the allocation of resources according to their capacity to do the most good or minimize the most harm, for example, using available resources to save the most lives possible.\r\n                May be most appropriate to guide the allocation of scarce resources that confer substantially different benefits to different individuals, for example, ventilators to those expected to derive the most benefit.Prioritize the worst offThis principle can be used to justify the allocation of resources to those in greatest medical need or those most at risk.May be most appropriate to guide the allocation of resources that are designed or intended to protect those at risk, for example, PPE for health care workers, vaccines for those most at risk of infection and severe illness, or those most\r\n                    in need, as in the case of provision of drugs in short supply to those needing them most urgently.Prioritize those tasked with helping othersThis principle can be used to justify the allocation of resources to those who have certain skills or talents that can save many other people, or because something is owed to them on account of their participation in helping others.May be most appropriate to guide the allocation of resources to health care workers, first responders, etc.Allocation principles may be relevant or justified at different stages of resource scarcity (from less scarcity to more scarcity). For example, where little scarcity exists, the allocation of resources such as ventilators may be most justified by the\r\n    principle of first come, first served (which promotes the value of equality). When those resources become increasingly scarce, their allocation may be justified according to a principle that prioritizes those most in need. With even greater scarcity,\r\n    a principle that aims to maximize benefit from the resource may be most justified. At each stage, allocation should aim to promote equality – that is, first come, first served, or random allocation, when no relevant factors distinguish individuals\r\n    within a particular scheme of allocation (for example, among those with similar needs, or among those who can be expected to benefit similarly from the resources, or among those that are at similar levels of risk).In addition, multiple principles may be combined within an allocation scheme. For example, an allocation scheme for PPE might find its justification in a principle prioritizing those most at risk as well as a principle prioritizing those tasked with helping\r\n    others, which would support priority allocation of PPE to health care workers."},{"id":128,"category":"Ethics, resource allocation and priority setting","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ethics-resource-allocation-and-priority-setting","question":"How should decision-makers make considered ethical judgements about these matters, given the likelihood that there will not be enough of a resource? Who should be involved in decision-making on scarce resources?","response":"For most decisions, multiple ethical values and principles will be relevant to deliberations\r\nabout how to allocate resources. This is likely to generate some disagreement, because\r\ndifferent people may weigh the values differently. Some may prioritize equality while others\r\nmight put more emphasis on best outcomes or prioritization of the worst-off. For this reason,\r\nit is imperative that the different values be weighed and applied to specific allocation issues\r\nusing a fair process.A fair process for allocating scarce resources must promote certain ethical values:Transparency. In a transparent process, the decisions and their justifications should\r\nbe made public. This means that the population should be informed about the criteria\r\nguiding the decisions.Inclusiveness. Those affected by allocation decisions – including individuals,\r\ncommunities or countries – should be able to exert at least some influence over the\r\ndecision-making process as well as the decision itself. This also means that decisions \r\n4\r\nshould be open to challenge and potentially revisable, perhaps through an appeal\r\nprocess. Consistency. Decisions should be consistent so that all persons in the same categories\r\nare treated in the same way. This means that favouritism towards one’s own family,\r\nreligious or political compatriots, or otherwise, is not appropriate. All forms of\r\ncorruption that are at variance with this principle should be challenged and\r\ncondemned. Accountability. Those making decisions about allocation must be accountable for\r\nthose decisions – that is, they should justify their decisions and be held responsible for\r\nthem. A fair process means that allocation decisions should not be made by\r\nindividuals, by individual pharmaceutical companies, or, in the case of allocation\r\nbetween countries, by a single country. Resources such as vaccines and therapies\r\nshould not be stockpiled outside the system of fair allocation.The fair allocation of resources is one that is valuable in itself precisely because it is fair.\r\nHowever, it may also be valuable because a fair system engenders solidarity and trust,\r\nwhich are vital to the successful and sustained collective response necessary for dealing\r\neffectively with any outbreak."},{"id":129,"category":"Ethics, resource allocation and priority setting","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ethics-resource-allocation-and-priority-setting","question":"What are the key ethical considerations that governments, vaccine manufacturers and funders should take into account to ensure a fair distribution of vaccines globally?","response":"Countries are equally vulnerable to COVID-19 and have a shared responsibility, grounded in solidarity, to collaborate globally to mitigate the outbreak. Each government has special obligations to its own citizens, but the fair allocation of vaccines globally\r\n    requires us not to simply appeal to self-interest, claims of resource ownership and the prioritization of compatriots. Vaccines should be allocated in a way that prioritizes those who fall into the categories presented in the below table. (Where individuals\r\n    or populations fall into multiple categories, they should receive even higher priority.)Priority populations, and rationale for prioritizationPriority populationRationale for prioritizationThose at greatest risk of becoming infected and seriously illMaximize benefit of vaccineThose who, if vaccinated, would prevent the greatest spread of the virusMaximize benefit of vaccineThose who have volunteered to participate in research aimed at developing the vaccineReciprocal obligation to those who were voluntarily put at risk to aid in this effortThose falling into each category may change over time."},{"id":130,"category":"Ethics, resource allocation and priority setting","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ethics-resource-allocation-and-priority-setting","question":"What conclusions can we draw about the fair allocation of scarce resources within countries during the COVID-19 outbreak?","response":"Health care workers (caring for patients) and first responders can justifiably be\r\nprioritized when allocating some resources because of their contribution to the health\r\nand well-being of the community. Their health helps preserve the health of others.Participants of research aimed at developing vaccines, therapies or other critical\r\nresources should receive some priority in receiving those resources because they have\r\nalso helped save others by their participation. This is not an absolute priority – for\r\nexample, it should not take precedence over giving priority to those most at risk in the\r\ncase of resources such as vaccines.While the principle of first come, first served is often applied when allocating\r\nresources in health care settings, it is rarely appropriate in an emergency. In practice,\r\nit is very likely to favour certain groups, such as those closest to a distribution centre,\r\nthose with access to better information, or those who are most well-off.Younger populations appear to be at lower risk in the COVID-19 context.\r\nConsequently, the principle of youngest first should have low priority for vaccine, but\r\nperhaps may have more weight if they do become sick and need critical care\r\nresources.The allocation of different resources may find ethical justification in different\r\nprinciples or values. For instance, if a novel vaccine is found to be safe and effective,\r\na lottery-based allocation may be justified among those as highest risk, the old and\r\nthose with co-morbidities, if they outnumber available vaccines.Maximizing utility should be balanced with the principle of priority to the worst-off:\r\ncentralizing the availability of resources in larger centres may extend their benefits to\r\nmore people, but may exclude isolated populations and challenge our concern for\r\nthose at highest risk."},{"id":131,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"How can food businesses remain safe from virus contamination?","response":"The main priority is to keep the virus out of the food environment. Several key measures are required including upgrading of cleaning and sanitation measures, disinfecting surfaces and high-touch points, educating staff on the virus and how to protect themselves and others, reinforcing protocols such as physical distancing, hand washing, and improved security with people staying in their vehicles/sanitizing hands when handing out documents and other material."},{"id":132,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"Should grocery store workers wear gloves? Masks?","response":"Disposable GlovesGloves may be used by food workers but must be changed frequently and hands must be washed between glove changes and when gloves are removed. Gloves must be changed after carrying out non-food related activities such as opening/closing doors by hand, and emptying bins. Food workers should be aware that wearing gloves can allow bacteria to build up on the surface of the hands, so hand washing is extremely important when gloves are removed to avoid subsequent contamination of food. Food workers should not touch their mouth, nose and eyes when wearing gloves.Disposable gloves can give a false sense of safety and should not be used in the food work environment as a substitute for hand washing. The COVID-19 virus can contaminate disposable gloves in the same way it can get onto workers hands and contact surfaces. Removal of disposable gloves can lead to contamination of hands. Wearing disposable gloves can give you a false sense of security and may result in staff not washing hands as frequently as required.Handwashing is a greater protective barrier to infection than wearing of disposable gloves. Food businesses need to ensure adequate sanitary facilities are provided and ensure food workers thoroughly and frequently wash their hands. Soap and water is adequate for hand washing. Hand sanitisers can be used as an additional measure but should not replace hand washing.Wearing of Face MasksWHO advice on the use of masks in the context of COVID-19 should be followed. Face Masks do not have to be routinely used by food workers to protect against transmission of COVID-19. However, for some food processing activities, such as working in abattoirs or handling cooked, ready-to-eat foods, wearing face masks is a usual practice.WHO recommends that face masks should be used if a person is sick with symptoms of COVID-19 (especially coughing) or looking after someone with suspected or confirmed COVID-19.However, a food worker who is sick or who has symptoms of COVID-19 should not be allowed to work in grocery stores or other food businesses and should be excluded from work until free of symptoms or deemed fit for work by a medical doctor."},{"id":133,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"What is the protocol when an employee working in a food business becomes ill with COVID-19?","response":"Staff who are feeling unwell should not report to work and should seek medical advice. However, in the event that a food worker becomes unwell in the workplace with typical symptoms of COVID-19, they should be removed to an area away from other people.\r\n    If possible, find a room or area where they can be isolated behind a closed door, such as a staff office. If it is possible to open a window, do so for ventilation. Arrangements should be made for the unwell employee to be removed quickly from the\r\n    food premise.The employee who is unwell should follow national guidelines for reporting cases/suspect cases of COVID-19. Whilst they wait for medical advice or to be sent home, they should avoid any contact with other employees. They should avoid touching people,\r\n    surfaces and objects and be advised to cover their mouth and nose with a disposable tissue when they cough or sneeze and put the tissue in a bag or pocket and then dispose of the tissue in a bin. If they do not have any tissues available, they should\r\n    cough and sneeze into the crook of their elbow. If they need to go to the bathroom whilst waiting for medical assistance, they should use a separate bathroom, if available.All surfaces that the infected employee has come into contact with must be cleaned. Alcohol based sanitizers/surface disinfectants should be used for cleaning purposes. In general, alcohol-based disinfectants (ethanol, propan-2-ol, propan-1-ol) have been\r\n    shown to significantly reduce infectivity of enveloped viruses like COVID-19 virus, in concentrations of 70-80%. Common disinfectants with active ingredients based on quaternary ammonium compounds (QUATS) and chlorine would also have virucidal properties.\r\n    All staff should wash their hands thoroughly for 20 seconds with soap and water after any contact with someone who is unwell with symptoms consistent with coronavirus infection.If an employee is confirmed as a case of COVID-19 it will be necessary to notify all close contacts of the infected employee so they too can take measures to minimise further risk of spread. WHO definitions of a contact of a COVID-19 case can be found \r\n    here. Examples of contacts in the food businesses could include any employee who was in face-to-face or physical (i.e., touching) contact; any employee who was within 1 meter with the confirmed case; anyone who has cleaned up any bodily fluids\r\n        without adequate PPE (e.g. gloves, overalls, protective clothing); employees in the same working team or workgroup as the confirmed case, and any employee living in the same household as a confirmed case.WHO recommends that contacts be quarantined for 14 days from the last point of exposure to the confirmed case.22 At a minimum, staff who have had\r\n    close contact with the infected employee should be asked to stay at home for 14 days from the last time they had contact with the confirmed case and practice physical distancing. If they become unwell at any time within their 14-day isolation period\r\n    and they test positive for COVID-19, they will become a confirmed case, and should be managed as such.Staff who have not had close contact with the original confirmed case should continue taking the usual precautions and attend work as usual. Organising employees into small teams or workgroups will help to minimise disruption to work processes in the event of an employee reporting sick with symptoms of COVID-19. Closure of the workplace is not recommended.More detailed information can be found in COVID-19 and food safety: guidance for food businesses.For more information on contacts of COVID-19 confirmed cases, see WHO guidance on surveillance and case definitions."},{"id":134,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"When can an employee return to work following illness? Are temperature checks appropriate?","response":"A return to work policy for staff who have been infected and recovered from COVID-19 should be in place. WHO recommends that a confirmed patient could be released from isolation once their symptoms resolve and they have two negative PCR tests at least 24 hours apart.  If testing is not possible, WHO recommends that a confirmed patient can be released from isolation 14 days after symptoms resolve. Taking the temperature of food workers is not recommended. Fever is only one of the symptoms of COVID-19 and absence of fever alone is not a reliable indicator of wellness. As part of a food business ‘fitness to work’ guidelines, staff should report to management if they are sick with typical COVID-19 symptoms, particularly fever."},{"id":135,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"What specific precautions do food workers need to take?","response":"Physical distancing, good personal hygiene with frequent hand washing, and application of general food hygiene measures are the most important precautions food workers should adopt. Physical distancing is very important to help slow the spread of coronavirus. This is achieved by minimising contact between potentially infected individuals and healthy individuals. Frequent hand washing with soap and water and use of hand sanitizers are also important in reducing the risk of transmission. All food businesses should follow the physical distancing and hand washing guidance of WHO.The Codex Alimentarius Commission has adopted several practical guidelines on how to apply and implement best practices to ensure food hygiene (Codex General Principles of Food Hygiene, CXC 1- 1969), handle meats (Codex Code of Hygienic Practice for Meat, CXC 58 – 2005), and control viruses in foods (Guidelines for the Application of General Principles of Food Hygiene to the Control of Viruses in Food (CAC/GL 79-2012). Enhanced food safety practices at this time, such as those recommended in the Codex documents mentioned, will reduce the likelihood of contamination of foods with any pathogen and help lowering the public health burden caused by already established foodborne infections, reducing the stress on an already overburdened public health system."},{"id":136,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"How should employees maintain safe distance from one another during food production and processing?","response":"WHO guidelines are to maintain at least 1 metre (3 feet) between fellow workers. Where the food production environment makes it difficult to do so, employers need to consider what measures to put in place to protect employees. Examples of practical measures to adhere to physical distancing guidance in the food processing environment are to:stagger workstations on either side of processing lines so that food workers are not facing one another,provide personal protection equipment (PPE) such as face masks, hair nets, disposable gloves, clean overalls and slip reduction work shoes for staff. The use of PPE would be routine in high risk areas of food premises that produce ready-to-eat and cooked foods. When staff are dressed in PPE it is possible to reduce distance between workers,space out workstations, which may require reduction in the speed of production lines,limit the number of staff in a food preparation area at any one time,organise staff into working groups or teams to facilitate reduced interaction between groups, including during change of work shifts."},{"id":137,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"How should baked goods and fresh produce be displayed in a food market/grocery store?","response":"It is important to maintain good hygiene practices around open food displays, with ready-to-eat food products such as salad bars, fresh produce displays and bakery products. Consumers should always be advised to wash fruits and vegetables with potable water prior to consumption. Both customers and staff should strictly observe good personal hygiene practices at all times around open food areas.In order to hygienically manage open food displays and to avoid the transmission of COVID-19 through surface contact, food retailers should:Maintain frequent washing and sanitising of all food contact surfaces and utensils;Require food service workers to frequently wash hands, and, if using gloves, these must be changed;Require food service workers to frequently clean and sanitise counters, serving utensils and condiment containers;Make available hand sanitiser for consumers on their way in and out of the food premises;Should consider not openly displaying or selling unwrapped bakery products from self-service counters. Bakery products on open, self-service displays in retail stores should be placed in plastic/cellophane or paper packaging. Where loose bakery products are displayed in retail stores, these should be placed in plexiglass display cabinets and placed in bags using tongs when customers are served.Ready-to-eat salads available in retail for self-serve, should also be placed behind plexiglass display cabinets and serving utensils should be frequently sanitized."},{"id":138,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"How should shopping trolleys or carts be disinfected?","response":"The handles of shopping trolleys or carts should be frequently cleaned using either alcohol-based sanitizers or chlorine-based disinfectants (sodium hypochlorite). Sanitizers, paper towels and trash bins should be placed outside the retail premises close to the trolley park for customers to use."},{"id":139,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"What is the most appropriate sanitizer to use on surfaces in a food production environment?","response":"In general, alcohol-based disinfectants (ethanol, propan-2-ol, propan-1-ol) have been shown to significantly reduce infectivity of enveloped viruses like SARS-CoV-2, in concentrations of 70-80% with one-minute exposure time. Chlorine-based disinfectants (sodium hypochlorite) are effective for surface decontamination, as are disinfectants with active ingredients based on quaternary ammonium compounds (QUATS)."},{"id":140,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"Could the virus be transmitted from humans to food animals or vice versa?","response":"Currently, there is no evidence to suggest that food animals could be a possible route for transmission of COVID-19 to humans or that food animals can become infected by humans. Studies are underway to better understand the susceptibility of different animal species to the COVID-19 virus and to assess infection dynamics in susceptible animal species. Additional information can be found on the website of the World Organisation for Animal Health (OIE)."},{"id":141,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"What is known about various conditions affecting survivability of the virus?","response":"Very little is known about how the SARS-CoV-2 virus survives outside the human body. Probably the most up-to-date summary of scientific information we have on survival in the environment is from the European Centre for Disease control (ECDC) and the following is extracted from their recent technical report:Recent publications have evaluated the survival of SARS-CoV-2 on different surfaces. According to van Doremalen et al., the environmental stability of SARS-CoV-2 is up to three hours in the air post-aerosolization, up to four hours on copper, up to 24 hours on cardboard and up to two to three days on plastic and stainless steel, albeit with significantly decreased titres [3]. These findings are comparable with results obtained for environmental stability of SARS-CoV-1. These findings resulted from experiments in a controlled environment and should be interpreted with caution in the real-life environment. Moreover, different levels of environmental contamination have been detected in rooms of COVID-19 patients, ranging from 1 out of 13 to 13 out of 15 samples testing positive for SARS-CoV-2 before cleaning. No air samples were positive in these studies, but one sample from an air exhaust outlet was positive indicating that virus particles may be displaced by air and deposited on surfaces [4,5]. In a study of environmental contamination in a Chinese hospital during the COVID-19 outbreak, SARS-CoV-2 was detected in environmental samples from the COVID-19 dedicated intensive care units (ICU), the COVID-19 dedicated obstetric isolation ward and the COVID-19 dedicated isolation ward. SARS-CoV-2 was also detected on objects such as the self-service printers used by patients to self-print the results of their exams, desktop keyboards and doorknobs. Virus was detected most commonly on gloves (15.4% of samples) and rarely on eye protection (1.7%) [6]. This evidence shows the presence of SARS-CoV-2 in the environment of a COVID-19 patient, therefore reinforcing the belief that fomites play a role in transmission of SARS-CoV-2; however, the relative importance of this route of transmission compared to direct exposure to respiratory droplets is still unclear."},{"id":142,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"What measures should be taken to ensure safe transport of food during this pandemic?","response":"The general guidelines outlined in the Codex Code of Hygienic Practice for the Transport of Food in Bulk and Semi-Packed Food.1 should be followed, in addition to ensuring that employees delivering foods are free from COVID-19, coughing/sneezing etiquette is practiced by all involved in food transport and that frequent hand washing/sanitizing is practiced and staff practice physical distancing.See also other Codes of Hygienic Practice for various groups of food."},{"id":143,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"What measures should be taken to ensure safe water is used in food production during this pandemic?","response":"There is no evidence that COVID-19 is transmitted by water used in food processing. The WHO guidelines for drinking-water quality should be followed."},{"id":144,"category":"Food businesses","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-businesses","question":"How should food premises be cleaned/disinfected during this pandemic?","response":"The general guidelines outlined in the General Principles of Food Hygiene for food processing and manufacture premises should be followed. If a suspected or confirmed case of COVID-19 is identified in a food premises then there is a requirement to completely clean the area with a neutral detergent, followed by decontamination of surfaces using a disinfectant effective against viruses. All surfaces that the infected employee has come into contact with must be cleaned, including all surfaces and objects which are visibly contaminated with body fluids/respiratory secretions, and all potentially contaminated high-contact areas such as toilets, door handles, telephones. Alcohol based sanitizers/surface disinfectants should be used for cleaning purposes. In general, alcohol-based disinfectants (ethanol, propan-2-ol, propan-1-ol) have been shown to significantly reduce infectivity of enveloped viruses like SARS-CoV-2, in concentrations of 70-80% with one-minute exposure time. Chlorine-based disinfectants (sodium hypochlorite) are effective for surface decontamination, as are disinfectants with active ingredients based on quaternary ammonium compounds (QUATS).All staff should wash their hands thoroughly for 20 seconds after any contact with someone who is unwell with symptoms consistent with coronavirus infection. Staff engaged in environmental cleaning should wear PPE when performing cleaning activities, such as overalls or uniform, single-use plastic aprons, gloves and a face mask. Protective clothing (e.g. uniforms, overalls, etc.) should be frequently washed at 60°C or above."},{"id":145,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Can I get COVID-19 from eating fresh foods, like fruits and vegetables?","response":"There is currently no evidence that people can catch COVID-19 from food, including fruits and vegetables. Fresh fruits and vegetables are part of a healthy diet and their consumption should be encouraged.  Read more in the COVID-19 and food safety: guidance for food businesses."},{"id":146,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"How should I wash fruits and vegetables in the time of COVID-19?","response":"Wash fruit and vegetables the same way you would in any other circumstance. Before handling them, wash your hands with soap and water. Then wash fruits and vegetables thoroughly with clean water, especially if you eat them raw."},{"id":147,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Can the virus that causes COVID-19 live on the surface of food packaging?","response":"Coronaviruses need a live animal or human host to multiply and survive and cannot multiply on the surface of food packages. It is not necessary to disinfect food packaging materials, but hands should be properly washed after handling food packages and before eating (see question 10 of Questions relating to food businesses)."},{"id":148,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Can the virus that causes COVID-19 be transmitted through the consumption of cooked foods, including animal products?","response":"There is currently no evidence that people can catch COVID-19 from food. The virus that causes COVID-19 can be killed at temperatures similar to that of other known viruses and bacteria found in food. Foods such as meat, poultry and eggs should always be thoroughly cooked to at least 70°C. Before cooking, raw animal products should be handled with care to avoid cross-contamination with cooked foods. The WHO 5-Keys to Safer Food provides further information."},{"id":149,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Is it safe to go to grocery stores and other food markets?","response":"Yes, it is generally safe to go grocery shopping and to markets by following the below prevention measures:Clean your hands with sanitizer before entering the store.Cover a cough or sneeze in your bent elbow or tissue. Maintain at least a 1-metre distance from others, and if you can’t maintain this distance, wear a mask (many stores now require a mask).Once home, wash your hands thoroughly and also after handling and storing your purchased products.  There is currently no confirmed case of COVID-19 transmitted through food or food packaging.More information on masks is available here. For more recommendations on how to minimize the risk of transmission of emerging pathogens in traditional food markets, see the WHO recommendations to reduce risk of transmission of emerging pathogens from animals to humans in live animal markets or animal product markets."},{"id":150,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Is it safe to have groceries delivered?","response":"Yes, it is safe to have groceries delivered if the provider follows good personal and food hygiene practices. After accepting food/grocery deliveries, hands should be properly washed."},{"id":151,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"What is the best household disinfectant for surfaces?","response":"Regular household cleaning and disinfection products will effectively eliminate the virus from household surfaces.  For cleaning and disinfecting households with suspected or confirmed COVID19, surface virucidal disinfectants, such as 0.05% sodium hypochlorite (NaClO) and products based on ethanol (at least 70%), should be used."},{"id":152,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"What foods should be consumed to support the immune system?","response":"The immune system requires the support of many nutrients. It is recommended to consume a variety of foods for a healthy and balanced diet, including whole grains, legumes, vegetables, fruits, nuts and animal source foods. There is no single food that will prevent you from catching COVID-19.  For more information on a healthy diet, see the Healthy diet fact sheet."},{"id":153,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Can micronutrient (vitamin and mineral) supplements prevent COVID-19 in healthy individuals or cure it in those with COVID-19 disease?","response":"No. There is currently no guidance on micronutrient supplementation for the prevention of COVID-19 in healthy individuals or for the treatment of COVID-19. Micronutrients are critical for a well-functioning immune system and play a vital role in promoting health and nutritional well-being. Wherever possible, micronutrient intakes should come from a nutritionally balanced and diverse diet, including from fruits, vegetables and animal source foods."},{"id":154,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Are vitamin D supplements needed if individuals are not exposed to sunlight due to lockdowns?","response":"Vitamin D can be made in the skin by exposure to sunlight or obtained through the diet from natural sources (e.g. fatty fishes such as salmon, tuna and mackerel, fish liver oils, beef liver, cheese and egg yolks), or from vitamin D-fortified foods or vitamin D-containing supplements. In situations where individuals’ vitamin D status is already marginal or where foods rich in vitamin D (including vitamin D-fortified foods) are not consumed, and exposure to sunlight is limited, a vitamin D supplement in doses of the recommended nutrient intakes (200-600 IU, depending on age) or according to national guidelines may be considered.See WHO guidance on Vitamin and mineral requirements in human nutrition."},{"id":155,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Are there any herbal teas or herbal supplements that may help prevent or cure COVID-19?","response":"No. There is currently no evidence to support the use of herbal teas or herbal supplements to prevent or cure COVID-19."},{"id":156,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Can probiotics help prevent COVID-19?","response":"No. Probiotics are live microorganisms that are generally added to foods or used as a supplement to the diet to confer a health benefit. However, there is currently no evidence to support the use of probiotics to help prevent or cure COVID-19."},{"id":157,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Can eating ginger help prevent COVID-19?","response":"No. There is no evidence that eating ginger has protected people from COVID-19. However, ginger is a food that may have some antimicrobial and anti-inflammatory properties."},{"id":158,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Can eating garlic help prevent COVID-19?","response":"No. There is no evidence that eating garlic has protected people from COVID-19. However, garlic is a food that may have some antimicrobial properties."},{"id":159,"category":"Food safety and nutrition","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-and-nutrition","question":"Can adding pepper to your soup or other meals help prevent or cure COVID-19?","response":"No. There is no evidence that adding hot peppers to your food can prevent or cure COVID-19."},{"id":160,"category":"Food safety authorities","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-authorities","question":"How should imported foods from countries with high prevalence of COVID-19 be treated?","response":"As food has not been implicated in the transmission of COVID-19, imported food should be subjected to the same import controls as before the pandemic. See FAO guidance on risk based imported food control."},{"id":161,"category":"Food safety authorities","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-authorities","question":"Do food inspectors need to wear any protective equipment?","response":"In the course of conducting a food inspection, food inspectors routinely wear protective equipment. There is no need for additional protective equipment to be used. The primary focus of the additional hygiene and sanitation measures implemented by food businesses should be on keeping the COVID-19 out of their businesses. COVID-19 virus will only enter business premises when an infected person enters, or contaminated fomites are brought into the premises. Food safety authorities should consider reducing the frequency of food inspections during this pandemic. If food inspectors continue to carry out food inspections, they will need to demonstrate that they are free from infection, they will need to practice physical distancing while in the food premises, changing clothes/shoes between inspections, washing hands before and after entering the food premises and good coughing/sneezing etiquette."},{"id":162,"category":"Food safety authorities","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-authorities","question":"What do food inspectors need to consider when reopening a food business when the pandemic is over?","response":"Food inspectors do not need to intervene when restaurants reopen after having closed upon the advice of national governments."},{"id":163,"category":"Food safety authorities","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-authorities","question":"What are the lab protocols for identifying the virus in food? On surfaces?","response":"As food has not been implicated in the transmission of COVID-19, testing of food or food surfaces for this virus is not recommended. Frequent cleaning of food contact surfaces with virucidal disinfectants such as 0.05% sodium hypochlorite (NaClO) or products based on ethanol (at least 70%) should be carried out. Alcohol-based disinfectants (ethanol, propan-2-ol, propan-1-ol) have been shown to significantly reduce infectivity of enveloped viruses like SARS-CoV-2, in concentrations of 70-80% with one-minute exposure time. Chlorine-based disinfectants (sodium hypochlorite) are effective for surface decontamination, as are disinfectants with active ingredients based on quaternary ammonium compounds (QUATS)."},{"id":164,"category":"Food safety authorities","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-authorities","question":"Is quarantine necessary for live animals imported from countries experiencing a large numbers of COVID-19 cases?","response":"No, food animals have not been implicated in the transmission of COVID-19 and the same import controls should apply as before this pandemic. See Q&A from the World Organisation for Animal Health for more about COVID-19 and animals."},{"id":165,"category":"Food safety authorities","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-authorities","question":"How do we ensure the food supply chain remains intact to prevent food shortages?","response":"While many businesses have introduced working from home and teleworking, these are not options for food workers who are required to continue to work as normal. Keeping all workers in the food production and supply chains healthy and safe is critical to avoid food shortage. Maintaining the movement of food along the food chain is an essential function of all sectors of the food industry and is extremely important for ensuring consumer confidence in the food supply. In order to ensure that the food supply chain remains intact to prevent food shortages there is an urgent requirement for the industry to introduce additional measures to protect food workers from contracting COVID-19; to prevent the risk of exposure to COVID-19, and to strengthen existing food hygiene and sanitation practices."},{"id":166,"category":"Food safety for consumers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-for-consumers","question":"Can I get COVID-19 from food?","response":"There is currently no evidence that people can catch COVID-19 from food or food packaging. COVID-19 is a respiratory illness and the transmission route is through person-to-person contact and through direct contact with respiratory droplets generated when an infected person coughs or sneezes."},{"id":167,"category":"Food safety for consumers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-for-consumers","question":"Can the virus live on the surface of foods (including fruits and vegetables, frozen foods, pre-packaged foods)?","response":"Coronaviruses cannot multiply in food – they need a live animal or human host to multiply and survive ( see question 10 of Questions relating to food businesses)."},{"id":168,"category":"Food safety for consumers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-for-consumers","question":"How to wash fruits and vegetables? Just with water, or something else?","response":"Washing fruit and vegetables with potable water is sufficient: it is recommended to follow the WHO 5-Keys to Safer Food."},{"id":169,"category":"Food safety for consumers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-for-consumers","question":"Can the virus live on the surface of food packaging? How long? Is it necessary to disinfect?","response":"See question 10 of Questions relating to food businesses.\r\n It is not necessary to disinfect food packaging materials, but hands should be properly washed after handling food packages and before eating."},{"id":170,"category":"Food safety for consumers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-for-consumers","question":"How long is it to cook food? To what temperature to kill the virus?","response":"This virus is not more resistant to heat than the usual viruses and bacteria found in food. As recommended for good hygiene practice, foods should be thoroughly cooked to at least 70°C. It is recommended to follow the WHO 5-Keys to Safer Food."},{"id":171,"category":"Food safety for consumers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-for-consumers","question":"What precautions should consumers take in grocery stores?","response":"Consumers should maintain a safe physical distance of at least one metre from all other shoppers and staff while queuing before entering the store and while shopping in the store. If a trolley or basket is used while shopping, sanitize the handle before and after use. Hands should be sanitized before entering the store. Practice good coughing/sneezing etiquette while in the store. Avoid touching mouth, nose or eyes during shopping. Minimise direct hand contact with food by using available tongs and serving utensils. Use contactless payment rather than cash/notes (where feasible)."},{"id":172,"category":"Food safety for consumers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-for-consumers","question":"Is food/grocery delivery safe?","response":"Yes, if the provider follows good personal and food hygiene practices. After accepting food/grocery deliveries, hands should be washed with soap and water."},{"id":173,"category":"Food safety for consumers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-for-consumers","question":"What is the best household disinfectant for surfaces?","response":"Regular household cleaning and disinfection products will effectively eliminate the virus from household surfaces.  For cleaning and disinfecting households with suspected or confirmed COVID19 illnesses - surface virucidal disinfectants, such as 0.05% sodium hypochlorite (NaClO) and products based on ethanol (at least 70%), should be used."},{"id":174,"category":"Food safety for consumers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-food-safety-for-consumers","question":"Is it still safe to go to food markets? Animal markets? Wet markets?","response":"It should be safe provided it is possible to maintain a safe physical distance of at least one metre from all other shoppers and staff, it is possible to wash/sanitize hands, and that Good Manufacturing Practices and Good Hygienic Practices (GMP/GHP) standards are maintained in the market. For more recommendations on how to minimise the risk of transmission of emerging pathogens in wet markets, see the WHO recommendations to reduce risk of transmission of emerging pathogens from animals to humans in live animal markets or animal product markets."},{"id":175,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"Can COVID-19 be transmitted at the workplace?","response":"COVID-19 spreads primarily through respiratory droplets or contact with contaminated surfaces. Exposure can occur at the workplace, while travelling to work, during work-related travel to an area with local community transmission, as well as on the way to and from the workplace."},{"id":176,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"What is the risk of contracting COVID-19 in the workplace?","response":"The risk of exposure to COVID-19 in the workplace depends on the likelihood of coming within 1 metre of others, in having frequent physical contact with people who may be infected with COVID-19, and through contact with contaminated surfaces and objects."},{"id":177,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"How can people assess the risk for exposure to COVID-19 in their workplace and plan for preventive measures?","response":"Managers with the support of an occupational health and safety advisor should carry out rapid risk assessments to determine the possibility of exposure risk in order to put in place preventive measures. This should be done for each specific work setting and each job.Low exposure risk Jobs or work without frequent, close contact with the general public or others. Workers in this group have minimal occupational contact with the public and other co-workers. Examples of such jobs may include remote workers (i.e., working from home), office workers without frequent close contact with others and workers providing teleservices.Medium exposure risk Jobs or tasks with close, frequent contact with the general public or others. This risk level may apply to workers who have frequent and close contact with the people in high-population-density work environments (e.g. food markets, bus stations, public transport, and other work activities where physical distancing of at least 1 metre may be difficult to observe), or tasks that require close and frequent contact between co-workers. This may also include frequent contact with people returning from areas with community transmission. Examples of such jobs may include frontline workers in retail, home deliveries, accommodation, construction, police and security, public transport, and water and sanitation. High exposure risk Jobs or tasks with close contact with people who may be more likely to have COVID-19, as well as contact with objects and surfaces possibly contaminated with the virus. Examples include transporting people known or suspected to have COVID-19 without separation between the driver and the passenger, providing domestic services or home care for people with COVID-19, and having contact with the deceased who were known or suspected of having COVID-19 at the time of their death. Jobs that may fall under this category include domestic workers, social care workers, personal transport  and home delivery providers and home repair technicians (plumbers, electricians) who have to provide services in the homes of people with COVID-19."},{"id":178,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"Who should carry out the workplace risk assessment?","response":"Employers and managers, in consultation with workers, should carry out and regularly update the risk assessment for work-related exposure to COVID-19, preferably with the support of occupational health services."},{"id":179,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"What are the key considerations for the workplace risk assessment?","response":"For each risk assessment, consider the environment, the task, the threat, resources available, such as personal protective equipment, and the feasibility of protective measures. The risk assessment should also extend to collective accommodation provided by the employer for workers, such as dormitories.  Essential public services, such as security and police, food retail, accommodation, public transport, deliveries, water and sanitation, and other frontline workers may be at an increased risk of exposure to occupational hazards for health and safety. Workers who may be at higher risk of developing severe COVID-19 illness because of age or pre-existing medical conditions should be considered in the risk assessment for individuals."},{"id":180,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"How should employers decide when to open, close or re-open workplaces and/or suspend or downscale work activities?","response":"Deciding to close or re-open a workplace or suspend or downscale work activities should rely on the risk assessment, the capacity to put in place protective measures and the level of compliance, and recommendations of national authorities."},{"id":181,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"What key measures to protect against COVID-19 should be undertaken in ALL workplaces?","response":"Measures to prevent transmission of COVID-19 that apply to all workplaces and all people at the workplace include frequent hand-washing or disinfection with alcohol based hand sanitizer, respiratory hygiene such as covering coughs, physical distancing of at least 1 metre or more according to the national recommendations, wearing of masks where distancing is not possible, regular environmental cleaning and disinfection, and limiting unnecessary travel. Clear policies and messages, training, and education for staff and managers to increase awareness of COVID-19 are essential. The management of people with COVID-19 or their contacts is also critical e.g. requiring workers who are unwell or who develop symptoms to stay at home, self isolate and contact a medical professional or the local COVID-19 information line for advice on testing and referral."},{"id":182,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"What additional measures should be taken at workplaces and for jobs at medium risk?","response":"Workplaces for jobs at medium risk require daily cleaning and disinfection at least two times a day of objects and surfaces that are touched regularly, including all shared rooms, surfaces, floors, bathrooms, and changing rooms. Consider suspending any activity where physical distancing of at least 1 metre cannot be implemented in full. If this is not possible, increase ventilation, implement enhanced regular hand hygiene, and require staff to wear appropriate face masks, goggles, gloves and work clothes during cleaning procedures that generate splashes, providing training on their use. Organize changing and washing of work clothes at the workplace, so that workers to do take them home."},{"id":183,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"What additional measures should be taken at workplaces and for jobs at high risk?","response":"In work areas at high risk, assess the possibility of suspending the activity; enhance regular hand hygiene; provide medical masks, disposable gowns, gloves, and eye protection for workers who must work in the homes of people who are suspected or known to have COVID-19; train workers in infection prevention and control practices and use of personal protective equipment; avoid assigning tasks with high risk to workers who have pre-existing medical conditions, are pregnant, or older than 60 years of age."},{"id":184,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"What should be taken into consideration when setting a physical distance at the workplace?","response":"WHO recommends keeping a physical distance of at least 1 metre between each person in all settings, including in workplaces. Because transmission can occur in crowded workplaces, WHO recommends providing sufficient space, at least 10 square meters, for every worker. National recommendations for physical distancing may require greater physical distance and should be complied with. In order to support compliance with national or local recommendations, implement physical distance guidelines in a way that is practical and feasible in the context of work tasks, and which is acceptable to both workers and employers. Stimulate workers to comply with physical distancing norms also at events outside the workplace, in the community, and in dormitories. Risk assessment and consultation between employers and workers is very important for setting up and implementing physical distancing measures at the workplace. This may require modification of workstations, changing the use of common spaces and transport vehicles, staggered work shifts, split teams and other measures to reduce social mixing at the workplace. If physical distancing measures at the workplace are not feasible for specific work tasks, consider whether the work can be suspended, and if this is not possible, apply additional protective measures, such as the use of screens, sneeze guards,  face masks, enhanced hand hygiene, ventilation and disinfection.Physical distancing alone can’t prevent COVID-19 transmission, it is important that it is combined with other public health measures, such as hand and respiratory hygiene, environmental clean-up and disinfection of commonly touched surfaces and objects, ventilation, wearing face masks and a policy of staying at home if unwell."},{"id":185,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"What are the rights, duties and responsibilities of employers?","response":"Employers, workers, and their organizations should collaborate with health authorities to prevent and control COVID-19. Cooperation between management and workers and their representatives is essential for workplace‐related prevention measures. International labour standards on the rights and responsibilities of workers and employers in occupational safety and health should be fully respected. Employers, in consultation with workers and their representatives, should plan and implement measures to prevent and mitigate COVID-19 at the workplace through engineering and administrative controls, and provide personal protective equipment and clothing according to the risk assessment. Such measures should not involve any expenditure on the part of the workers.Special measures are needed to protect workers at higher risk of developing severe disease, such as those age 60 and over, or with underlying medical conditions, upon recommendation of the occupational health services. Workers in the informal economy and digital labour platforms, those in small enterprises, domestic and migrant workers should not be left behind in the protection of their health and safety at work and their livelihood.   There should be no social stigma or discrimination at the workplace for any reason, including access to information and protection from COVID-19, occupational health services and mental health and psychosocial support. If COVID-19 is contracted through occupational exposure, it could be considered an occupational disease and, if so determined, should be reported and compensated according to the international labour standards and the national schemes for employment injury benefits."},{"id":186,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"What are the rights, duties and responsibilities of workers?","response":"Workers are responsible to follow the measures for occupational safety and health and infection prevention and control established for their workplace, and to participate in training provided by the employer. Workers should report to their supervisor any situation which may present an imminent and serious danger to their life or health. Workers have the right to remove themselves from any work situation that they have reasonable justification to believe presents an imminent and serious danger to their life or health, and should be protected from any undue consequences as a result of exercising this right."},{"id":187,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"How can workplaces plan for the prevention and mitigation of COVID-19?","response":"Workplaces should develop action plans to prevent and mitigate COVID-19 as part of the business continuity plan and according to the results of the risk assessments and the epidemiological situation. The action plan and preventive measures should be regularly monitored and updated. Workers and their representatives should be consulted and should participate in the development, monitoring and updating of the workplace COVID-19. It is very important to monitor the effectiveness of preventive measures, and the compliance of workers, visitors, customers, clients and sub-contractors with the measures. The plans should be updated when someone with known or suspected COVID-19 is at the workplace."},{"id":188,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"Can the return to the workplace be immediate after public measures are lifted?","response":"The return to work premises should be carefully planned ahead, with preventive measures put in place according to the risk assessment of the different jobs and work tasks. All possible risks for safety and health should be assessed, such as risks resulting from reduced maintenance of machines and facilities during the closure period.  If a return to work is rushed and not done in a phased and cautious manner, it puts lives at risk, and threatens to undermine efforts to restore social and economic activity."},{"id":189,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"Does WHO recommend thermal testing of people entering a workplace?","response":"Temperature screening cannot detect all cases of COVID-19, since infected individuals may not have fever early in the course of infection or illness, such as during the incubation period or just before other symptoms begin, even though they may already be infectious. Some people may reduce fever with a fever-reducing medication if they are concerned about the possible consequences of not coming to work. Relying on temperature screening alone will not stop the spread of COVID-19 at work. Thermal screening at the workplace can be considered part of a package of measures to prevent and control COVID-19 at the workplace. Workers should be encouraged to self-monitor their health, possibly with the use of questionnaires, and take their own temperature regularly at home. Workplaces should adopt “stay at home if unwell” and flexible sick leave policies to discourage workers with symptoms consistent with COVID-19 from coming to the workplaces."},{"id":190,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"Does WHO recommend workers wear masks at the workplace (office or others)? If yes, what type of masks?","response":"Wearing masks depends on the risk assessment. For jobs and tasks that carry a medium or high risk, for people aged 60 and older, and for those with underlying health conditions, a medical mask and other personal protective equipment should be provided. Fabric masks or face coverings are currently recommended for younger people and those with no symptoms where physical distancing is not achievable. This prevents the spread of virus from the wearer (who could have COVID-19 but no symptoms) to others. The policy on wearing a mask or face covering in low risk workplaces should be in line with national or local guidelines. Masks may carry some risks if not used properly."},{"id":191,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"Are there any directives on office ventilation and air conditioning use?","response":"There should be fresh, clean air in all workplaces. For jobs and work tasks at medium or high risk of exposure, WHO recommends an increased ventilation rate through natural aeration or artificial ventilation, preferably without re-circulation of the air. In case of air recirculation, filters should be cleaned regularly."},{"id":192,"category":"Health and safety in the workplace","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-health-and-safety-in-the-workplace","question":"What mental health and psychosocial support should be provided to workers during COVID-19?","response":"COVID-19 is associated with a range of concerns, such as fear of falling ill and dying, of being socially excluded, placed in quarantine, or losing a livelihood. Symptoms of anxiety and depression are common reactions for people in the context of COVID-19. Mental health and psychosocial support should be made available to all workers. Comprehensive risk assessments can help identify and mitigate related occupational hazards for mental healthFull Guideline Document Considerations for public health and social measures in the workplace in the context of COVID-19 is accessible at: https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/considerations-for-public-health-and-social-measures-in-the-workplace-in-the-context-of-covid-19"},{"id":193,"category":"Herd immunity, lockdowns and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/herd-immunity-lockdowns-and-covid-19","question":"What is ‘herd immunity’?","response":"'Herd immunity', also known as 'population immunity', is the indirect protection from an infectious disease that happens when a population is immune either through vaccination or immunity developed through previous infection. WHO supports achieving 'herd immunity' through vaccination, not by allowing a disease to spread through any segment of the population, as this would result in unnecessary cases and deaths.Herd immunity against COVID-19 should be achieved by protecting people through vaccination, not by exposing them to the pathogen that causes the disease. Read the Director-General’s 12 October media briefing speech for more detail. Vaccines train our immune systems to create proteins that fight disease, known as ‘antibodies’, just as would happen when we are exposed to a disease but – crucially – vaccines work without making us sick. Vaccinated people are protected from getting the disease in question and passing on the pathogen, breaking any chains of transmission. Visit our webpage on COVID-19 and vaccines for more detail. To safely achieve herd immunity against COVID-19, a substantial proportion of a population would need to be vaccinated, lowering the overall amount of virus able to spread in the whole population. One of the aims with working towards herd immunity is to keep vulnerable groups who cannot get vaccinated (e.g. due to health conditions like allergic reactions to the vaccine) safe and protected from the disease. Read our Q&A on vaccines and immunization for more information.The percentage of people who need to be immune in order to achieve herd immunity varies with each disease. For example, herd immunity against measles requires about 95% of a population to be vaccinated. The remaining 5% will be protected by the fact that measles will not spread among those who are vaccinated. For polio, the threshold is about 80%. The proportion of the population that must be vaccinated against COVID-19 to begin inducing herd immunity is not known. This is an important area of research and will likely vary according to the community, the vaccine, the populations prioritized for vaccination, and other factors.  Achieving herd immunity with safe and effective vaccines makes diseases rarer and saves lives. Find out more about the science behind herd immunity by watching or reading this interview with WHO’s Chief Scientist, Dr Soumya Swaminathan."},{"id":194,"category":"Herd immunity, lockdowns and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/herd-immunity-lockdowns-and-covid-19","question":"What is WHO’s position on ‘herd immunity’ as a way of fighting COVID-19?","response":"Attempts to reach ‘herd immunity’ through exposing people to a virus are scientifically problematic and unethical. Letting COVID-19 spread through populations, of any age or health status will lead to unnecessary infections, suffering and death.\nThe vast majority of people in most countries remain susceptible to this virus. Seroprevalence surveys suggest that in most countries, less than 10% of the population have been infected with COVID-19.\nWe are still learning about immunity to COVID-19. Most people who are infected with COVID-19 develop an immune response within the first few weeks, but we don’t know how strong or lasting that immune response is, or how it differs for different people. There have also been reports of people infected with COVID-19 for a second time.         \nUntil we better understand COVID-19 immunity, it will not be possible to know how much of a population is immune and how long that immunity last for, let alone make future predictions. These challenges should preclude any plans that try to increase immunity within a population by allowing people to get infected.\nAlthough older people and those with underlying conditions are most at risk of severe disease and death, they are not the only ones at risk.\nFinally, while most infected people get mild or moderate forms of COVID-19 and some experience no disease, many become seriously ill and must be admitted into hospital. We are only beginning to understand the long-term health impacts among people who have had COVID-19, including what is being described as ‘Long COVID.’ WHO is working with clinicians and patient groups to better understand the long term effects of COVID-19.  \nRead the Director-General’s opening remarks at the 12 October COVID-19 briefing for a summary of WHO’s position."},{"id":195,"category":"Herd immunity, lockdowns and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/herd-immunity-lockdowns-and-covid-19","question":"What do we know about immunity from COVID-19?","response":"Most people who are infected with COVID-19 develop an immune response within the first few weeks after infection.\nResearch is still ongoing into how strong that protection is and how long it lasts. WHO is also looking into whether the strength and length of immune response depends on the type of infection a person has: without symptoms (‘asymptomatic’), mild or severe. Even people without symptoms seem to develop an immune response.\nGlobally, data from seroprevalence studies suggests that less 10% of those studied have been infected, meaning that the vast majority of the world’s population remains susceptible to this virus.\nFor other coronaviruses – such as the common cold, SARS-CoV-1 and Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS) – immunity declines over time, as is the case with other diseases. While people infected with the SARS-CoV-2 virus develop antibodies and immunity, we do not yet know how long it lasts. \nWatch this conversation with Dr Mike Ryan and Dr Maria Van Kerkhove for more information on immunity."},{"id":196,"category":"Herd immunity, lockdowns and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/herd-immunity-lockdowns-and-covid-19","question":"What is WHO’s position on ‘lockdowns’ as a way of fighting COVID-19?","response":"Large scale physical distancing measures and movement restrictions, often referred to as ‘lockdowns’, can slow COVID‑19 transmission by limiting contact between people.\nHowever, these measures can have a profound negative impact on individuals, communities, and societies by bringing social and economic life to a near stop. Such measures disproportionately affect disadvantaged groups, including people in poverty, migrants, internally displaced people and refugees, who most often live in overcrowded and under resourced settings, and depend on daily labour for subsistence.\nWHO recognizes that at certain points, some countries have had no choice but to issue stay-at-home orders and other measures, to buy time.\nGovernments must make the most of the extra time granted by ‘lockdown’ measures by doing all they can to build their capacities to detect, isolate, test and care for all cases; trace and quarantine all contacts; engage, empower and enable populations to drive the societal response and more.\nWHO is hopeful that countries will use targeted interventions where and when needed, based on the local situation."},{"id":197,"category":"HIV and antiretrovirals","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hiv-and-antiretrovirals","question":"Are people living with HIV at increased risk of being infected with the virus that causes COVID-19?","response":"People living with HIV (PLHIV) who are not taking antiretroviral treatment (ART) and have a low CD4 cell count, particularly those with advanced HIV disease, are at increased risk of opportunistic infections and AIDS related complications. However, there\r\n    is evolving and conflicting evidence whether people living with HIV have an increased risk of acquisition of SARS-CoV-2 infection and and/or COVID-19 clinical complications in PLHIV compared to the general population. PLHIV can have a greater prevalence of the known risk factors for COVID-19 acquisition and complications, such as heart disease, kidney disease, diabetes, chronic pulmonary disease, obesity, as well as, other comorbidities and co-infections, like tuberculosis. Several case report series and small cohort studies among hospitalized PLHIV with COVID-19 have shown comparable clinical outcomes and similar risk of SARS CoV2 infection when compared with general population, particularly in those with well controlled HIV infection (on ART and with a CD4 count > 200 cells/mm3 and supressed viral load). These limited clinical data suggest the mortality risk in PLHIV is associated with known COVID-19 factors such as older age and presence of comorbidities including cardiovascular disease, diabetes, chronic respiratory disease and obesity [1-3].There have been several systematic and non-systematic reviews that evaluated COVID-19 outcomes among PLHIV; most have found comparable outcomes of mortality and morbidity when compared with HIV negative patients [4-8]. Methods did not always include assessment of outcomes while controlling for known COVID-19 risk factors [4]. There is also limited data in patients with advanced HIV disease (i.e. low CD4 cell count).  One systematic review, notably published as a pre-print, found of 144,795 hospitalized COVID-19 patients in North America, Europe, and Asia the pooled prevalence of HIV in COVID-19 patients was 1.22% [95% (CI): 0.61%-2.43%)] translating to a 2-fold increase compared to the respective local-level pooled HIV prevalence in the general population of 0.65% (95% CI: 0.48%-0.89%) – which hinted at a potential susceptibility among PLHIV [9].  Additional data on this topic come from several cohort studies from South Africa, the USA and the UK [10-12] have reported a moderate increased risk of death directly attributed to HIV infection after adjustments for age, sex, ethnicity and presence of\r\n    comorbidities; an unpublished meta-analysis including these studies found that the risk of death was almost double that of HIV-negative patients; however, confounding by comorbidities associated with increased risk of severe COVID-19 cannot be ruled\r\n    out [13]. Protecting people living with HIV during the COVID-19 pandemic, and ensuring they can maintain treatment, is critical. Researchers are currently investigating whether people with HIV have an increased risk of poor outcomes with COVID-19.Preliminary\r\n        evidence of moderate increased vulnerability of people with HIV makes it even more urgent that people with HIV have access to ARVs and treatments for co-morbidities – such as treatment for hypertension, cardiovascular disease, chronic pulmonary\r\n        disease, diabetes, tuberculosis, and maintenance of a healthy body weight.  A larger dataset from a broader geographical representation is required to expand understanding of how SARS-CoV-2 co-infection with HIV impacts the severity of illness, disease progression and outcomes from hospitalization with COVID-19. For this purpose, WHO has established a Global COVID-19 Clinical Platform. As of 4 November 2020, WHO has received clinical data from 79 000 patients hospitalised with confirmed or suspected COVID-19, including from 5 291 hospitalised patients living with HIV, from over 30 countries around the world. The platform is open to all Member States and health facilities to contribute data and inclusion will help inform future guidance on how best to ensure PLHIV are well protected during the COVID-19 pandemic.PLHIV are advised to take the same COVID-19 precautions as recommended for the general population [14-15]: wash hands often; practice cough etiquette; ensure physical distancing; wear masks when appropriate and according to local regulations; seek medical care if symptomatic; self-isolate if one develops symptoms or has contact with a positive  COVID-19 case; and other actions per the local and government response.  It is important to ensure that PLHIV have access to antiretroviral drugs for longer periods (3-6 month supply); and that programmes practice multi-month dispensing (MMD) of ARVs, as well as, other necessary medications, such as, opiate substitution therapy (OST), TB preventative therapy (TPT) and treatments for comorbidities. It is also important to ensure that some vaccinations are up to date (influenza and pneumococcal vaccines) and there is access to adequate supplies of medicines to treat or prevent co-infections and comorbidities."},{"id":198,"category":"HIV and antiretrovirals","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hiv-and-antiretrovirals","question":"Can antiretrovirals or direct-acting antivirals against hepatitis C virus be used to treat COVID-19?","response":"Antiretrovirals drugs were initially considered for use in the treatment of COVID-19 based on virtual screening and in vitro studies. Published data indicate that most of patients infected with the virus causing COVID-19 have mild to moderate symptoms, have good clinical outcomes and do not require hospitalization. In some cases, patients admitted to the hospital were given an antiretroviral drug, most often lopinavir boosted with ritonavir (LPV/r) or, less frequently, darunavir boosted with ritonavir (DRV/r). Studies assessing the potential benefit of an antiretroviral drug on COVID-19 were mostly carried out in HIV-negative individuals. A systematic review on use of antiretrovirals in patients with coronaviruses, conducted in March 2020 identified two randomized trials and 21 observational studies provided clinical outcome data on the use of LPV/r for the treatment of COVID‐19, SARS and MERS [16]. The randomized trials showed no clinical benefit, the observational studies were inconclusive, and the certainty of the body of evidence across all important outcomes was low or very low quality. A living systematic review and network meta-analysis on the efficacy and safety of drug treatments for COVID-19 published in September 2020 did not find any convincing evidence that antiretrovirals drugs such as lopinavir/ritonavir reduced the mortality or increased the rate of viral clearance [17].More recently, two additional randomized studies confirmed these findings and didn't support the use of LPV/r for treatment of hospitalized patients with COVID-19.A recently published clinical trial showed that in patients admitted to hospital with COVID-19, LPV/r was not associated with reductions in mortality, duration of hospital stay, or risk of progressing to invasive mechanical ventilation or death [18].  Similarly, in the WHO-coordinated Solidarity Trial recently published, LPV/r appears to have little or no effect on hospitalized COVID-19 patients, as indicated by overall mortality, initiation of ventilation and duration of hospital stay. [19].Based on available evidence, the use of LPV/r and other antiretrovirals are not likely to improve clinical outcomes in hospitalized individuals with COVID-19.Several randomized and nonrandomized studies have evaluated anti-hepatitis C drugs including sofosbuvir and daclatasvir for treating of SARS-CoV-2 and while these preliminary results suggested benefit in terms of clinical recovery, this evidence is insufficient (small sample size, inclusion of a nonrandomized study) to be able to recommend using these antivirals for treating SARS-CoV-2. [20]"},{"id":199,"category":"HIV and antiretrovirals","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hiv-and-antiretrovirals","question":"Can antiretrovirals be used to prevent COVID-19 infection?","response":"A number of small studies have assessed whether antiretrovirals can be used to prevent infection from SARS-CoV2, often with discordant results. A recent study suggests that people living with HIV who were using tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF) were less likely to contract SARS-CoV-2. However, other studies indicate that tenofovir-based HIV pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) does not provide protection against infection with the new coronavirus, nor does it ameliorate the course of COVID-19 disease [21]. In this study, prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 was actually higher among people taking PrEP compared to individuals who were not.Taken together, the available literature does not provide conclusive evidence that antiretrovirals could protect individuals from SARS-CoV-2 infection or from becoming seriously ill with the virus. However, the certainty of the evidence is very low due to small sample size, and uncertainty regarding intensity of exposure.People taking PrEP or who are taking ARVs with the hopes of preventing COVID-19 need to adopt the same COVID-19 prevention measures as recommended for people in the general population."},{"id":200,"category":"HIV and antiretrovirals","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hiv-and-antiretrovirals","question":"What is WHO’s position on the use of antiretrovirals for the treatment or prevention of COVID-19?","response":"WHO does not currently recommend the use of antiretrovirals as treatment or prevention of COVID-19, outside of the context of clinical trials. Existing published literature on antiretrovirals is mostly observational in nature, with few clinical trials; and does not provide good quality evidence in favour of these agents for these purposes. The current body of evidence does not show benefit of using LPV/r and other antiretrovirals reduce the risk of new coronavirus infection or improve clinical outcomes in symptomatic disease among patients with COVID‐19. More recently, two additional randomized studies confirmed these findings and didn't support the use of LPV/r for treatment of hospitalized patients with COVID-19. The Recovery trial showed that LPV/r was not associated with reduction in mortality, time of hospitalisation stay and risk of progressing to invasive mechanical ventilation or death. [18] The interim results of the WHO multicounty adaptative trial (Solidarity trial) also found that LPV/r had little or no effect on overall mortality, initiation of ventilation and duration of hospital stay in hospitalized patients with COVID-19 [19]."},{"id":201,"category":"HIV and antiretrovirals","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hiv-and-antiretrovirals","question":"How do we ensure human rights and reduce stigma and discrimination?","response":"As the world scales up public health responses to the COVID19 pandemic, countries are being urged to take decisive action to control the epidemic. WHO has urged all countries to ensure an appropriate balance between protecting health, preventing economic and social disruption, and respecting human rights. WHO is working with partners including the UNAIDS Joint Programme and the Global Network of People Living with HIV to ensure that human rights are not eroded in the response to COVID-19 and to ensure that people living with, or affected by, HIV are offered the same access to services as others and to ensure HIV-related services continue without disruption.To mitigate potential prison outbreaks of COVID-19 and reduce morbidity and mortality among people in prisons and other closed settings, it is crucial that prisons and immigration detention centres are embedded within the broader public health response. This requires close collaboration between health and justice ministries and includes protocols for entry screening, personal protection measures, physical distancing, environmental cleaning and disinfection, and restriction of movement, including limitation of transfers and access for non-essential staff and visitors.  In the current context it is of critical importance that countries work toward developing non-custodial strategies to prevent overcrowding in closed settings [22]. Governance of prison health by a ministry of health, rather than a ministry of justice or similar, is likely to facilitate this approach [23]."},{"id":202,"category":"HIV and antiretrovirals","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hiv-and-antiretrovirals","question":"How can programmes assure continued access to HIV services?","response":"Continuous access to essential HIV prevention, testing and treatment services must be assured, including in settings where measurements of confinement are implemented within the public health response to the COVID-19 pandemic. Adapted and evidence-based\r\n    measures to reduce possible transmission should be considered and implemented. These include [24]:Applying standard precautions for all patients (including ensuring that all patients cover their nose and mouth with a tissue or elbow when coughing or sneezing, offering a medical mask to patients with suspected COVID-19 infection while they are\r\n        in waiting in the service, perform hand hygiene etc.)Health care and outreach workers, as well as peer educators and clients should apply hand hygiene and other protective measuresEnsuring triage, early recognition, and source control (isolating patients with suspected COVID-19 infection)Ensure there is adequate ventilation in all areas in the healthcare facilitySpatial distance between 1 and 2 meters should ideally be maintained between all patients within all types of servicesCleaning and disinfection procedures should be followed consistently and correctlyDispensing medicines (for treatment of HIV, TB and other chronic conditions such as opioid dependence) for longer periods allowing reduced frequency of patient visitsConsider reduction of services to the most critical ones (provision of essential treatment and prevention services; services such as counselling sessions may be reduced or adapted)Many countries have developed virtual ways of delivering services and supporting people to reduce clinic attendance. Countries have also increased self-care options, for example HIV self-testing, often in combination with virtual support to keep services going.   There are many examples of innovations being used to support the continuation of PrEP services including virtual support, community and home distribution and using HIVST for monitoring during periods when clinic services have been suspended. \r\n        Learning from these may help guide future implementation in the post-COVID-9 era.   Generally, vulnerable populations, including members of key populations (men who have sex with men, sex workers, people who use drugs, transgender people and people in prisons) as well as homeless and/or displaced people may be at increased risk of infection – because of additional comorbidities impacting on their immune system, reduced ability to apply measures of confinement and social distancing, as well as generally limited access to health services. It is critical that services that reach these populations such as community-based services, drop-in centres and outreach services can continue providing life-saving HIV prevention (distribution of condoms, PrEP, needles and syringes), testing and treatment while securing safety of staff and clients. Services can be adapted according to above considerations where applicable.  Some prevention services, such as voluntary medical male circumcision (VMMC), which require clinic attendance, were initially suspended in the early phases of the response to the COVID-19 epidemic. Some countries, following assessing the covid situation, have adjusted their responses and are restating VMMC services with additional COVID-19 prevention measures."},{"id":203,"category":"HIV and antiretrovirals","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hiv-and-antiretrovirals","question":"What is the role of multi-month prescriptions and dispensing for antiretrovirals and other medicines?","response":"All PLHIV doing well on ART can benefit from simplified antiretroviral therapy delivery models which include multi-month prescriptions and dispensing (3-6 month supply) which will reduce the frequency of visits to clinical settings and ensures continuity of treatment during possible disruption of movements during the coronavirus outbreak.  Similar consideration should be given to providing people who are clinically stable on methadone or buprenorphine substitution therapy with an increased possibility for take-home medications to reduce additional burden on the health sector. Many countries have now implemented the provision of take-home dosages for stable patients on opioid substitution therapy as recommended by WHO [25].As is common practice, experienced preexposure prophylaxis (PrEP) users may be given multi-month prescriptions according to national guidance which may include regular STI testing. Individuals initiating PrEP should continue to return for a 1-month follow-up HIV testing and clinic visit before receiving multi-month prescriptions. This is to rule out acute HIV infection, assess adverse effects and determine intention to continue PrEP use. However, flexibility for the 1-month visit can be considered for motivated clients who have not had a recent (in the past 3 weeks) potential exposure to HIV. These decisions could be made on a case-by-case basis between providers and clients initiating PrEP for the first time. Telehealth and community dispensing can be considered for follow up. Quality-assured HIV self-testing can be considered for maintenance."},{"id":204,"category":"HIV and antiretrovirals","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hiv-and-antiretrovirals","question":"Can pregnant or postpartum women living with HIV transmit the COVID-19 virus to their unborn child or infant?","response":"There are few data on the clinical presentation of COVID-19 in specific populations, such as children, pregnant and breastfeeding women [26] but findings from a small published study suggest that there is currently no evidence for intrauterine infection caused by vertical transmission in women who develop COVID-19 pneumonia in late pregnancy, nor are data sufficient to conclude vertical transmission through breastfeeding [27]. Although no vertical transmission has been documented, transmission after birth via contact with infectious respiratory secretions is a concern. Infants born to mothers with suspected, probable, or confirmed COVID-19 should be fed according to standard infant feeding guidelines [28], while applying necessary precautions for infection prevention and control (IPC). As with all confirmed or suspected COVID-19 cases, symptomatic mothers who are breastfeeding or practicing skin-to-skin contact or kangaroo mother care should practice respiratory hygiene, including during feeding (for example, use of a medical mask when near a child if the mother has respiratory symptoms), perform hand hygiene before and after contact with the child, and routinely clean and disinfect surfaces with which the symptomatic mother has been in contact [29].   Q&A on COVID-19, pregnancy, childbirth and breastfeeding"},{"id":205,"category":"HIV and antiretrovirals","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hiv-and-antiretrovirals","question":"Should pregnant and breastfeeding women living with HIV with COVID-19 and their newborns be managed differently?","response":"There is currently no well-established difference between the clinical manifestations of COVID-19 or risk of severe illness or foetal compromise for pregnant and non-pregnant women with HIV. However, a recent large database study conducted by US-CDC\r\n    suggested that pregnant women with COVID-19 are more likely to need intensive care due an increased relative risk of developing severe disease [30]. Pregnant women with suspected or confirmed COVID-19 should be treated with supportive and management\r\n    therapies, considering the immunologic and physiologic adaptations during and after pregnancy which may overlap with COVID-19 symptoms. Data are limited but, until the evidence base provides clearer information, special consideration should be given\r\n    to pregnant women with concomitant medical illnesses who could be infected with COVID-19. There are no reported deaths in pregnant women at time of publishing this information [31]. However, COVID-19 testing of symptomatic pregnant women may need\r\n    to be prioritized to enable access to specialized care.  All recently pregnant women with COVID-19 or who have recovered from COVID-19 should be provided with information and counselling on safe infant feeding and appropriate IPC measures to\r\n    prevent COVID-19 virus transmission [32].With confirmed disease or under investigation, management is similar to non-pregnant women, with appropriate isolation of confirmed or under investigation.  Obstetric facilities must be notified and prepared, noting that each infant born to any mother\r\n    with confirmed COVID-19 should be considered a ‘person under investigation’ and should be isolated according to the IPC guidance.  Currently, it is unknown whether newborns with COVID-19 are at increased risk for severe complications."},{"id":206,"category":"Home care for families and caregivers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-home-care-for-families-and-caregivers","question":"Can someone who has tested positive for COVID-19 be cared for at home?","response":"People with no symptoms should be able to stay at home, if adequately isolated from others, but this should be confirmed by a doctor. Those with mild or moderate disease can be considered for home care if they are under the age of 60, do not smoke, are not obese, and do not have other diseases such as cardiovascular disease, diabetes mellitus, chronic lung disease, cancer, chronic kidney disease, immunosuppression. A health worker will assess risk factors along with the person’s symptoms, medical history and ability for the family to manage the care. Household members need to limit shared spaces, practice the recommended hygiene and know how to recognize and respond to signs of worsening health.A trained health worker will need to assess whether the home in question is suitable for the isolation and care of a COVID-19 patient, and proper infection prevention control measures are put in place. Trained health workers are also important to support the patient and family in the home, or by phone, telemedicine, or outreach teams."},{"id":207,"category":"Home care for families and caregivers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-home-care-for-families-and-caregivers","question":"What should be done to prevent other people in the house from becoming sick if a person with COVID-19 is being cared for at home?","response":"There are a number of precautions that can prevent the spread of COVID-19 to other people in the house:The ill person should stay in a separate room. If this is not possible, then keep at least a 1-metre distance from them. The sick person and anyone else in the same room should wear a medical mask. Provide good ventilation in the room of the ill person and shared spaces, and open windows if possible and safe to do so. See our  Q&A on ventilation. The ill person should wear a medical mask as much as possible, in particular when not alone in the room and when at least a 1-metre distance from others cannot be maintained.Visitors should not be allowed in the home.Limit the number of caregivers to one person with no underlying conditions, if possible.Caregivers and household members should wear a medical mask while in the same room with an ill person, not touch their mask or face during use, discard the mask after leaving the room, and wash their hands afterward.The ill person should have dedicated dishes, cups, eating utensils, towels and bed linens. They should be washed with soap and water, and not shared.Frequently touched surfaces by the ill person should be cleaned and disinfected at least daily.Everyone in the household should wash their hands with soap and water regularly, especially:\r\n        after coughing or sneezingbefore during and after you prepare foodbefore eatingafter using the toiletbefore and after caring for the ill personwhen hands are visibly dirtyA cough or sneeze should be covered with a flexed elbow or a disposable tissue that is discarded immediately after use.The waste from the ill person should be packed in strong closed bags before disposal."},{"id":208,"category":"Home care for families and caregivers","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-home-care-for-families-and-caregivers","question":"How long should people with COVID-19 stay at home and in isolation?","response":"People with COVID-19 who are cared for at home should stay in isolation until they are no longer able to transmit the virus to others:Those with symptoms should stay isolated for a minimum of 10 days after the first day they developed symptoms, plus another 3 days after the end of symptoms – when they are without fever and without respiratory symptoms.People without symptoms should stay isolated for a minimum of 10 days after testing positive."},{"id":209,"category":"Home care for health workers and administrators","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-home-care-for-health-workers-and-administrators","question":"When should a patient with COVID-19 be cared for at home?","response":"Ideally, all patients with COVID-19 are cared for in a healthcare facility. However, there may be some circumstances where patients may not require hospitalization or inpatient care is unavailable or unsafe, such as when capacity is insufficient to meet the demand for healthcare services. Patients should be assessed on a case-by-case basis by the health worker to determine where their care needs can best be met."},{"id":210,"category":"Home care for health workers and administrators","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-home-care-for-health-workers-and-administrators","question":"What factors determine whether a COVID-19 patient can be cared for at home?","response":"Patients with mild or moderate disease can be considered for home care if the home setting is suitable for the isolation and care of a COVID-19 patient, and if the patient is under the age of 60, does not smoke, is not obese, and does not have other diseases such as cardiovascular disease, diabetes mellitus, chronic lung disease, cancer, chronic kidney disease, immunosuppression. An assessment about home care for each patient should be based on the following factors:Clinical evaluation of the patient.Evaluation of the patient’s home setting according to infection prevention and control (IPC) criteria (e.g., ability to carry out hand and respiratory hygiene, environmental cleaning, adequate ventilation, limitations on movement around or from the house).Presence of vulnerable people at higher risk of COVID-19 in the home.Ability of a caregiver to provide care and closely monitor the evolution of the patient’s health, at least once per day, and to recognize signs and symptoms of any worsening of the health status. Availability of trained health workers to support the patient and caregiver (home-based, phone, telemedicine, trained community workers or outreach teams). If adequate isolation from others in the home and infection prevention control measures cannot be ensured, then isolation in designated community facilities or a health facility may need to be arranged, with consent from the patient and in agreement with the caregiver and household members. It is important to note that in areas with other endemic infections that cause fever, such as influenza, malaria, dengue, etc., febrile patients should seek medical care, be tested and treated for those endemic infections per routine protocols, irrespective of the presence of respiratory signs and symptoms.  Home care does not replace healthcare by professionals. Those patients who receive homecare should be regularly monitored by health workers."},{"id":211,"category":"Home care for health workers and administrators","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-home-care-for-health-workers-and-administrators","question":"What additional factors should be taken into consideration when assessing the home setting to determine if it is safe for patients and families to remain at home?","response":"There are a number of environmental and social factors to consider for patients to safely remain at home with their families or household members. An overall needs assessment of the patient and family that includes the availability of trained health workers\r\n    for support should be conducted. A detailed description is available in the Appendix, Box 2, of the guidance."},{"id":212,"category":"Home care for health workers and administrators","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-home-care-for-health-workers-and-administrators","question":"What precautions should health workers take when providing care to patients in home settings?","response":"Health workers should take the following precautions:Perform a risk assessment to select the use of appropriate personal protective equipment (PPE), such as a medical mask, eye protection, gloves and gown when caring for the patient.Implement infection prevention and control measures, including hand hygiene.Ensure the room where the patient is cared for is well ventilated, opening windows if necessary.Provide instructions to caregivers and household members on cleaning and disinfection in the home, and on management of waste, laundry and utensils related to the patient.Request the patient to wear a medical mask when providing care or within a 1-metre distance.Request limiting the number of household members during visits and maintaining at least a 1-metre distance.Remove PPE and discard what is disposable, then perform hand hygiene before leaving the home.Make sure that the waste generated from providing care to the patient be placed in strong bags or safety boxes as appropriate, closed completely, disposed as infectious waste and removed from the home."},{"id":213,"category":"Home care for health workers and administrators","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-home-care-for-health-workers-and-administrators","question":"Could pregnant women be cared for at home if they have COVID-19?","response":"Pregnant women with mild or moderate disease can be considered for home care if the home setting is suitable for the isolation and care of a COVID-19 patient, if they do not smoke, are not obese, and do not have other diseases such as cardiovascular disease, diabetes mellitus, chronic lung disease, cancer, chronic kidney disease, immunosuppression. An assessment about home care for each patient should be based on the following factors:Clinical evaluation of the patient.Evaluation of the patient’s home setting according to IPC criteria (e.g., ability to carry out hand and respiratory hygiene, environmental cleaning, limitations on movement around or from the house).Presence of vulnerable people at higher risk of COVID-19 in the home.Ability of a caregiver to provide care and closely monitor the evolution of the patient’s health, at least once per day, and to recognize signs and symptoms of any worsening of the health status. Availability of trained health workers to support the patient and caregiver (home-based, phone, telemedicine, trained community workers or outreach teams)."},{"id":214,"category":"Home care for health workers and administrators","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-home-care-for-health-workers-and-administrators","question":"Can children be cared for at home if they have COVID-19?","response":"Children should be kept together with their parents or caregivers wherever possible. Children with mild or moderate disease can be considered for home care if the home setting is suitable for the isolation and care of a COVID-19 patient, if they are not obese, do not smoke, and do not have other conditions such as cardiovascular disease, diabetes mellitus, chronic lung disease, cancer, chronic kidney disease, or immunosuppression.Caregivers of children with COVID-19 should monitor for signs and symptoms of clinical deterioration requiring urgent re-evaluation. These include difficulty breathing/fast or shallow breathing (for infants: grunting, inability to breastfeed), blue lips or face, chest pain or pressure, new confusion, inability to awaken/not interacting when awake, inability to drink or keep down any liquids. If caregivers are suspected or have confirmed COVID-19 infection, medical and non-medical factors must be taken into account due to the negative and possible long-term consequences of even a short period of family separation.Community protection focal points and caseworkers should help families plan–in advance–agreements for the care of children in case the caregiver becomes ill.  Children living with primary caregivers who are elderly, disabled or have underlying health conditions should be prioritized."},{"id":215,"category":"How is it transmitted?","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-how-is-it-transmitted","question":"How does COVID-19 spread between people?","response":"We know that the disease is caused by the SARS-CoV-2 virus, which spreads between people in several different ways.The virus can spread from an infected person’s mouth or nose in small liquid particles when they cough, sneeze, speak, sing or breathe. These particles range from larger respiratory droplets to smaller aerosols.Current evidence suggests that the virus spreads mainly between people who are in close contact with each other, typically within 1 metre (short-range). A person can be infected when aerosols or droplets containing the virus are inhaled or come directly\r\n        into contact with the eyes, nose, or mouth.The virus can also spread in poorly ventilated and/or crowded indoor settings, where people tend to spend longer periods of time. This is because aerosols remain suspended in the air or travel farther than 1 metre (long-range).People may also become infected by touching surfaces that have been contaminated by the virus when touching their eyes, nose or mouth without cleaning their hands.Further research is ongoing to better understand the spread of the virus and which settings are most risky and why. Research is also under way to study virus variants that are emerging and why some are more transmissible. For updated information on\r\n        SARS-CoV-2 variants, please read the weekly epidemiologic updates."},{"id":216,"category":"How is it transmitted?","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-how-is-it-transmitted","question":"When do infected people transmit the virus?","response":"Whether or not they have symptoms, infected people can be contagious and the virus can spread from them to other people.Laboratory data suggests that infected people appear to be most infectious just before they develop symptoms (namely 2 days before they develop symptoms) and early in their illness. People who develop severe disease can be infectious for longer.While someone who never develops symptoms can pass the virus to others, it is still not clear how frequently this occurs and more research is needed in this area."},{"id":217,"category":"How is it transmitted?","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-how-is-it-transmitted","question":"What is the difference between people who are asymptomatic or pre-symptomatic? Don’t they both mean someone without symptoms?","response":"Both terms refer to people who do not have symptoms. The difference is that ‘asymptomatic’ refers to people who are infected but never develop any symptoms, while ‘pre-symptomatic’ refers to infected people who have not yet developed symptoms but go on to develop symptoms later."},{"id":218,"category":"How is it transmitted?","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-how-is-it-transmitted","question":"Are there certain settings where COVID-19 can spread more easily?","response":"Yes, any situation in which people are in close proximity to one another for long periods of time increases the risk of transmission. Indoor locations, especially settings where there is poor ventilation, are riskier than outdoor locations. Activities where more particles are expelled from the mouth, such as singing or breathing heavily during exercise, also increase the risk of transmission.The “Three C’s” are a useful way to think about this. They describe settings where transmission of the COVID-19 virus spreads more easily:Crowded places;Close-contact settings, especially where people have conversations very near each other;Confined and enclosed spaces with poor ventilation.  The risk of COVID-19 spreading is especially high in places where these “3Cs” overlap.In health facilities where people are receiving treatment for COVID-19, there is an increased risk of infection during medical procedures called aerosol generating procedures. These can produce very small droplets that can stay suspended in the air for longer periods of time and spread beyond conversational distances (typically 1 meter). This is why health workers performing these procedures or in settings where these procedures are performed should take specific airborne protection measures, including using appropriate personal protective equipment such as respirators. This is also why visitors are not permitted in areas where these procedures are being performed."},{"id":219,"category":"How is it transmitted?","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-how-is-it-transmitted","question":"How can I reduce my risk of getting COVID-19?","response":"There are many things you can do to keep yourself and your loved ones safe from COVID-19. Know your risks to lower risks. Follow these basic precautions:Follow local guidance: Check to see what national, regional and local authorities are advising so you have the most relevant information for where you are.Keep your distance: Stay at least 1 metre away from others, even if they don’t appear to be sick, since people can have the virus without having symptoms.Wear a mask:  Wear a well-fitting three-layer mask, especially when you can’t physically distance, or if you’re indoors. Clean your hands before putting on and taking off a mask.Read our Masks and COVID-19 Q&A and watch our videos on how to wear and make masks.Avoid crowded places, poorly ventilated, indoor locations and avoid prolonged contact with others. Spend more time outdoors than indoors.Ventilation is important: Open windows when indoors to increase the amount of outdoor air.Avoid touching surfaces, especially in public settings or health facilities, in case people infected with COVID-19 have touched them. Clean surfaces regularly with standard disinfectants.Frequently clean your hands with soap and water, or an alcohol-based hand rub. If you can, carry alcohol-based rub with you and use it often.Cover your coughs and sneezes with a bent elbow or tissue, throwing used tissues into a closed bin right away. Then wash your hands or use an alcohol-based hand rub.Get vaccinated: When it’s your turn, get vaccinated. Follow local guidance and recommendations about vaccination.Read our public advice page for more information.Read our Q&A about how to stay safe when attending and organizing small gatheringsRead our Q&A about ventilation and air conditioning and COVID-19"},{"id":220,"category":"Hydroxychloroquine","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-hydroxychloroquine","question":"Does WHO recommend hydroxychloroquine to prevent COVID-19?","response":"WHO does not recommend hydroxychloroquine to prevent COVID-19. This recommendation is based on six trials with more than 6000 participants who did not have COVID-19 and received hydroxychloroquine. Using hydroxychloroquine for prevention had little or no effect on preventing illness, hospitalization or death from COVID-19. Taking hydroxychloroquine to prevent COVID-19 may increase the risk of diarrhea, nausea, abdominal pain, drowsiness and headache. More information can be found here. However, hydroxychloroquine and chloroquine are safe for use in patients with autoimmune diseases or malaria (not COVID-19)."},{"id":221,"category":"Hydroxychloroquine","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-hydroxychloroquine","question":"Does WHO recommend hydroxychloroquine as a treatment for COVID-19?","response":"WHO does not recommend hydroxychloroquine as a treatment for COVID-19. This recommendation is based on 30 trials with more than 10 000 COVID-19 patients. Hydroxychloroquine did not reduce mortality, the need for or duration of mechanical ventilation. Taking hydroxychloroquine to treat COVID-19 may increase the risk of heart rhythm problems, blood and lymph disorders, kidney injury, liver problems and failure. More information can be found here.However, hydroxychloroquine and chloroquine are safe for use in patients with autoimmune diseases or malaria (not COVID-19)."},{"id":222,"category":"Hydroxychloroquine","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-hydroxychloroquine","question":"Why did WHO stop clinical trials on hydroxychloroquine as a treatment for COVID-19?","response":"The Solidarity trial, the UK's Recovery trial, and a Cochrane review of other evidence on hydroxychloroquine conclusively showed that hydroxychloroquine did not reduce deaths among hospitalized COVID-19 patients. Based on this evidence, WHO dropped the hydroxychloroquine arm of the Solidarity Trial in June of 2020. More information can be found here."},{"id":223,"category":"Malaria and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-malaria-and-covid-19","question":"How many malaria-affected countries have reported cases of COVID-19?","response":"Malaria-endemic countries in all WHO have regions have reported cases of COVID-19. In the WHO African Region, which carries more than 90% of the global malaria burden, there have been more than 1 million confirmed cases of COVID-19 since the beginning of the pandemic. The latest situation reports on the COVID-19 pandemic are available on the WHO website."},{"id":224,"category":"Malaria and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-malaria-and-covid-19","question":"Should core malaria vector control interventions be maintained in view of the rapid global spread of COVID-19?","response":"As of March 2020, there have been reports of the suspension of insecticide-treated net (ITN) and indoor residual spraying (IRS) campaigns in several African countries due to concerns around exposure to COVID-19. Suspending such campaigns will leave many vulnerable populations at greater risk of malaria, particularly young children and pregnant women. WHO strongly encourages countries not to suspend the planning for – or implementation of – vector control activities, including ITN and IRS campaigns, while ensuring these services are delivered using best practices to protect health workers and communities from COVID-19 infection. Modifications of planned distribution strategies may be needed to minimize exposure to the coronavirus. WHO commends the leaders of Benin, Chad, the Central African Republic, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, Mali, Niger, Sierra Leone and Uganda for committing to move forward with ITN campaigns during the pandemic. Other countries are adapting their net distribution strategies to ensure households receive the nets as quickly and safely as possible.Together with partners, WHO has developed guidance to ensure that those suffering from malaria can safely receive the care they need in COVID-19 settings. Tailoring malaria interventions in the COVID-19 responseincludes guidance on the prevention of infection through vector control and chemoprevention, testing, treatment of cases, clinical services, supply chain and laboratory activities. The document is consistent with broader WHO guidance on how to maintain essential health services during the pandemic."},{"id":225,"category":"Malaria and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-malaria-and-covid-19","question":"Should WHO-recommended preventive therapies be maintained in sub-Saharan Africa?","response":"Yes, delivery of intermittent preventive treatment in pregnancy (IPTp), seasonal malaria chemoprevention (SMC), and intermittent preventive treatment in infants (IPTi) should be maintained provided that best practices for protecting health workers – and other front-line workers – from COVID-19 are followed. Ensuring access to these and other core malaria prevention tools saves lives and is an important strategy for reducing the strain on health systems in the context of the COVID-19 response.Tailoring malaria interventions in the COVID-19 response, developed by WHO and partners, includes guidance on how to deliver preventive therapies for pregnant women and young children in ways that protect health workers and communities against potential COVID-19 transmission."},{"id":226,"category":"Malaria and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-malaria-and-covid-19","question":"Are there any changes to WHO guidance with respect to malaria diagnosis and treatment?","response":"WHO guidance remains the same. Countries should not scale back efforts to detect and treat malaria; doing so would seriously undermine the health and well-being of millions of people infected with a potentially life-threatening disease.As signs and symptoms of malaria and COVID-19 can overlap (such as a fever), public health messages will need to be adapted in malaria-endemic settings so that people who have a fever are encouraged to seek immediate treatment rather than stay at home; without prompt treatment, a mild case of malaria can rapidly progress to severe illness and death."},{"id":227,"category":"Malaria and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-malaria-and-covid-19","question":"What additional special measures may be needed in the context of COVID-19?","response":"In addition to routine approaches to malaria control, there may be a case for special measures in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic – such as a temporary return to presumptive malaria treatment, or the use of mass drug administration – which have proved useful in some previous emergencies. Presumptive malaria treatment refers to treatment of a suspected malaria case without the benefit of diagnostic confirmation (e.g. through a rapid diagnostic test). This approach is typically reserved for extreme circumstances, such as disease in settings where prompt diagnosis is no longer possible.Mass drug administration (MDA) is a WHO-recommended approach for rapidly reducing malaria mortality and morbidity during epidemics and in complex emergency settings. Through MDA, all individuals in a targeted population are given antimalarial medicines – often at repeated intervals – regardless of whether or not they show symptoms of the disease. Such special measures should only be adopted after careful consideration of 2 key aims: lowering malaria-related mortality and keeping health workers and communities safe. WHO is exploring concrete proposals for when and how to activate such measures; guidance will be published in due course."},{"id":228,"category":"Malaria and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-malaria-and-covid-19","question":"What are the key considerations for countries that are working to eliminate malaria or prevent re-establishment of transmission?","response":"All of the considerations described above apply to malaria-eliminating countries and those preventing re-establishment of the disease: efforts must be sustained to prevent, detect and treat malaria cases while preventing the spread of COVID-19 and ensuring the safety of those who deliver the services. Countries that are nearing malaria elimination must protect their important gains and avoid malaria resurgences. Countries that have eliminated malaria must remain vigilant for any imported cases of malaria that may be occurring to prevent reintroduction of the disease."},{"id":229,"category":"Malaria and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-malaria-and-covid-19","question":"Why is WHO particularly concerned about the spread of COVID-19 in malaria-affected areas?","response":"Experience from previous disease outbreaks has shown the disruptive effect on health service delivery and the consequences for diseases such as malaria. The 2014-2016 Ebola outbreak in Guinea, Liberia and Sierra Leone, for example, undermined malaria control efforts and led to a massive increase in malaria-related illness and death in the 3 countries.A modelling analysis from WHO and partners, published on 23 April, found that the number of malaria deaths in sub-Saharan Africa could double this year alone if there are severe disruptions in access to insecticide-treated nets and antimalarial medicines due to COVID-19. These projections reinforce the critical importance of sustaining efforts to prevent, detect and treat malaria during the pandemic.In all regions, protective measures should be utilized to minimize the risk of COVID-19 transmission between patients, communities and health providers. WHO and partners have developed guidance on how to safely maintain malaria prevention and treatment services in COVID-19 settings."},{"id":230,"category":"Malaria and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-malaria-and-covid-19","question":"Have there been disruptions in the global supply of key malaria-related commodities as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"Yes. Since the early days of the pandemic, there have been reports of disruptions in the supply chains of essential malaria commodities – such as long-lasting insecticidal nets, rapid diagnostic tests and antimalarial medicines – resulting from lockdowns and from a suspension of the importation and exportation of goods in response to COVID-19. WHO and partners are working together to ensure the availability of key malaria control tools, particularly in countries with a high burden of the disease, and that efforts to limit the spread of COVID-19 do not compromise access to malaria prevention, diagnosis and treatment services."},{"id":231,"category":"Malaria and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-malaria-and-covid-19","question":"What is WHO’s position on the use of chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine in the context of the COVID-19 response?","response":"WHO is actively following the ongoing clinical trials that are being conducted in response to COVID-19, including the more than 80 studies looking at the use of chloroquine and its derivative, hydroxychloroquine, for treatment and/or prevention. To date, 3 large randomized controlled trials, including the WHO Solidarity trial, have failed to show that the use of hydroxychloroquine among hospitalized patients infected with COVID-19 can prevent death or disease progression. Additionally, 3 trials of patients with mild or moderate disease failed to show a significant benefit in prevention of respiratory failure through the use of hydroxychloroquine. Thus, there is now growing evidence that hydroxychloroquine is not an effective treatment for COVID-19. This evidence will inform the next update of WHO guidance on therapeutics. Studies on the use of chloroquine or hydroxychloroquine to prevent individuals, particularly those at high risk such as health care workers, from contracting COVID-19 are ongoing. Currently, there is insufficient evidence to assess the protective efficacy of either of these medicines for the prevention of COVID-19 infection or disease. WHO cautions physicians against administering these unproven treatments to patients with COVID-19 outside the context of a clinical trial. Individuals are also advised against self-medicating with these drugs.For public health emergencies, WHO has a systematic and transparent process for research and development (R&D), including for clinical trials of drugs. The WHO “R&D Blueprint” for COVID-19, initiated on 7 January 2020, aims to fast-track the availability of effective tests, vaccines and medicines that can be used to save lives and avert large-scale crises."},{"id":232,"category":"Malaria and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-malaria-and-covid-19","question":"What is WHO’s position on the use of Artemisia plant material for the prevention or treatment of malaria and/or COVID-19?","response":"The most widely used antimalarial treatments, artemisinin-based combination therapies (ACTs), are produced using the pure artemisinin compound extracted from the plant Artemisia annua. There have been reports that products or extracts (e.g. herbal teas or tablets) made from Artemisia plant material may have a preventive or curative effect on COVID-19. However, available in vitro data suggests that purified artemisinin compounds or A. annua plant product or extracts do not have an appreciable effect against COVID-19 at concentrations that could be safely achieved in humans. As such, current evidence does not support the use of artemisinins or A. annua products or extracts as an antiviral for COVID-19. WHO urges extreme caution over reports touting the efficacy of such products. As explained in a WHO position statement, there is no scientific evidence base to support the use of non-pharmaceutical forms of Artemisia for the prevention or treatment of malaria. There is also no evidence to suggest that COVID-19 can be prevented or treated with products made from Artemisia-based plant material."},{"id":233,"category":"Malaria and COVID-19","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-malaria-and-covid-19","question":"What is WHO doing to support malaria-affected countries in the context of COVID-19?","response":"The WHO Global Malaria Programme is leading a cross-partner effort to mitigate the negative impact of the coronavirus in malaria-affected countries and, where possible, contribute towards a successful COVID-19 response. The work is being carried out in close collaboration with colleagues based at WHO headquarters, regional offices and country level.In March 2020, before the pandemic had secured a strong footing in Africa, WHO sounded an urgent call for maintaining core malaria prevention and treatment services while protecting health workers and communities against COVID-19 transmission. The findings of a modelling analysis from WHO and partners, published in April, reinforced the WHO call for continuity of malaria services during then pandemic.In collaboration with partners, WHO developed technical guidance for countries on how to safely maintain malaria prevention and treatment in COVID-19 settings. Tailoring malaria interventions in the COVID-19 response is consistent with broader WHO guidance on how to maintain essential health services during the pandemic."},{"id":234,"category":"Masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-masks","question":"Why should people wear masks?","response":"Masks are a key measure to suppress transmission and save lives. Masks should be used as part of a comprehensive ‘Do it all!’ approach including physical distancing, avoiding crowded, closed and close-contact settings, good ventilation, cleaning hands, covering sneezes and coughs, and more. Depending on the type, masks can be used for either protection of healthy persons or to prevent onward transmission."},{"id":235,"category":"Masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-masks","question":"Who should wear what kind of mask?","response":"Medical masks are recommended for:Health workers in clinical settings. See our guidance for more information on the\r\n        use of personal protective equipment by health care workers.Anyone who is feeling unwell, including people with mild symptoms, such as muscle aches, slight cough, sore throat or fatigue.Anyone awaiting COVID-19 test results or who has tested positive.People caring for someone who is a suspected or confirmed case of COVID-19 outside of health facilities.Medical masks are also recommended for the following groups, because they are at a higher risk of becoming seriously ill with COVID-19 and dying:People aged 60 or over.People of any age with underlying health conditions, including chronic respiratory disease, cardiovascular disease, cancer, obesity, immunocompromised patients and diabetes mellitus.Non-medical, fabric masks can be used by the general public under the age of 60 and who do not have underlying health conditions. Find out more about masks, including videos on how to use, on our public advice page."},{"id":236,"category":"Masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-masks","question":"When should masks be worn by the general public?","response":"In areas where the virus is circulating, masks should be worn when you’re in crowded settings, where you can’t be at least 1 metre from others, and in rooms with poor or unknown ventilation. It’s not always easy to determine the quality of ventilation, which depends on the rate of air change, recirculation and outdoor fresh air. So if you have any doubts, it’s safer to simply wear a mask. You should always clean your hands before and after using a mask, and before touching it while wearing it. While wearing a mask, you should still keep physical distance from others as much as possible. Wearing a mask does not mean you can have close contact with people. For indoor public settings such as busy shopping centres, religious buildings, restaurants, schools and public transport, you should wear a mask if you cannot maintain physical distance from others. If a visitor comes to your home who is not a member of the household, wear a mask if you cannot maintain a physical distance or the ventilation is poor. When outside, wear a mask if you cannot maintain physical distance from others. Some examples are busy markets, crowded streets and bus stops."},{"id":237,"category":"Masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-masks","question":"Should I wear a mask while exercising?","response":"Even when you’re in an area of COVID-19 transmission, masks should not be worn during vigorous physical activity because of the risk of reducing your breathing capacity. No matter how intensely you exercise, keep at least 1 metre away from others, and if you’re indoors, make sure there is adequate ventilation."},{"id":238,"category":"Masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-masks","question":"How do I choose what fabric mask to buy, or ideal fit and fabrics if I make my own?","response":"Check for filtration, breathability and fit when choosing a fabric mask. It should be held in place comfortably with little adjustment using elastic bands or ties. There are different mask shapes such as flat-fold or duckbill – find the one that fits closely over your nose, cheeks and chin. When the edges of the mask are not close to the face and shift, such as when speaking, air penetrates through the edges of the mask rather than being filtered through the fabric. Masks with vents or exhalation valves are not advised because they allow unfiltered breath to escape the mask.Fabric masks should be made of three layers of fabric:Inner layer of absorbent material, such as cotton.Middle layer of non-woven non-absorbent material, such as polypropylene.Outer layer of non-absorbent material, such as polyester or polyester blend.If purchasing a fabric mask from a store, check to make sure it meets national performance standards. Watch the video on WHO’s recommended fabric mask materials and composition for more information."},{"id":239,"category":"Masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-masks","question":"How should I wear and clean a fabric mask?","response":"How to put on and wear a fabric mask:Before touching the mask, clean your hands with an alcohol-based hand rub or soap and water.Inspect the mask for tears or holes, do not use a mask that is damaged.Adjust the mask to cover your mouth, nose, and chin, leaving no gaps on the sides.Place the straps behind your head or ears. Do not cross the straps because this can cause gaps on the side of your face.Avoid touching the mask while wearing it. If you touch it, clean your hands.Change your mask if it gets dirty or wet.How to take off and store a fabric mask:Clean your hands before taking off the mask.Take off the mask by removing it from the ear loops, without touching the front of the mask.If your fabric mask is not dirty or wet and you plan to reuse it, put it in a clean plastic, resealable bag. If you need to use it again, hold the mask at the elastic loops when removing it from the bag. Clean your mask once a day.Clean your hands after removing the mask.How to clean a fabric mask:Wash fabric masks in soap or detergent and preferably hot water (at least 60 degrees Centigrade/140 degrees Fahrenheit) at least once a day.If it is not possible to wash the mask in hot water, then wash it in soap/detergent and room temperature water, followed by  boiling the mask for 1 minute.General tips:Make sure to clean your hands before touching your mask.Make sure you have your own mask and do not share it with others.Resist the temptation to pull down your mask to your chin or take if off when speaking to other people.Do not store your mask around your arm or wrist or pull it down to rest around your chin or neck. Instead, store it in a clean plastic bag.Watch our ‘How to wear a fabric mask’ video for a demonstration."},{"id":240,"category":"Masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-masks","question":"How should I put on, wear and take off a medical mask?","response":"How to put on and take off a medical mask:Before touching the mask, clean your hands with an alcohol-based hand rub or soap and water.  Inspect the mask for tears or holes; do not use a mask that has previously been worn or is damaged. Verify which side is the top – this is usually where the metal strip is. Then, identify the inside of the mask, which is usually the white side. Place the mask on your face covering your nose, mouth and chin, making sure that there are no gaps between your face and the mask. Place the straps behind your head or ears. Do not cross the straps because this can cause gaps on the side of the mask.Pinch the metal strip so it moulds to the shape of your nose.Remember, do not touch the front of the mask while using it to avoid contamination; if you accidentally touch it, clean your hands.  How to take off a medical mask:Before touching the mask, clean your hands with an alcohol-based hand rub or soap and water.Remove the straps from behind the head or ears, without touching the front of the mask. As you remove the mask, lean forward and pull the mask away from your face.   Medical masks are for single use only; discard the mask immediately, preferably into a closed bin. Clean your hands after touching the mask.Be aware of the condition of the mask; replace it if it gets soiled or damp."},{"id":241,"category":"Masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-masks","question":"What is the difference between medical masks and respirators, like N95s?","response":"Medical masks (also known as surgical masks) are:composed of 3 layers of synthetic nonwoven materialsconfigured to have filtration layers sandwiched in the middleavailable in different thicknesseshave various levels of fluid-resistance and filtrationRespirators (also known as filtering facepiece respirators – FFP) are available at different performance levels such as FFP2, FFP3, N95, N99.Medical masks and respirator masks are similar in their protection value. However, respirators are specific for certain procedures and instances because they have a tightly fitted component to them. Respirator masks are designed to protect healthcare workers who provide care to COVID-19 patients in settings and areas where aerosol generating procedures are undertaken. Healthcare workers should be fit tested before using a respirator to ensure that they are wearing the correct size. Wearing a loose-fitting respirator will not offer the same protection to the wearer and may allow small particles to get inside the mask through the sides."},{"id":242,"category":"Masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-masks","question":"Does WHO recommend the use of masks with exhalation valves to prevent transmission of COVID-19?","response":"No, WHO does not advise using masks or respirators with exhalation valves. These masks are intended for industrial workers to prevent dust and particles from being breathed in as the valve closes on inhale. However, the valve opens on exhale, making it\r\n    easier to breathe but also allowing any virus to pass through the valve opening. This makes the mask ineffective at preventing the spread of COVID-19 or any other respiratory virus."},{"id":243,"category":"Masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-masks","question":"Does WHO recommend the use of gloves in the community to prevent transmission of COVID-19?","response":"No, WHO does not advise using gloves by people in the community. Instead, WHO encourages the installation of public hand hygiene stations at the entrance and exit of public places, such as supermarkets or public/private buildings. This helps reduce germs brought in by people’s hands. By widely improving hand hygiene practices, countries can help prevent the spread of the COVID-19 virus and other infections."},{"id":244,"category":"Masks","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-masks","question":"When should health workers wear masks in the context of COVID-19?","response":"Health workers are the most likely to be exposed to COVID-19 because they are in close contact with patients with suspected, probable or confirmed COVID-19.In areas of community or cluster transmission, health workers, caregivers and visitors should wear a mask at all times when in the health facility, even if physical distancing can be maintained. Masks should be worn throughout their shifts, apart from when eating, drinking or needing to change the mask for specific reasons:Health workers and caregivers include: doctors, nurses, midwives, medical attendants, cleaners, community health workers, and any others working in clinical areas.Health workers must remember to combine hand hygiene with any time they touch their mask or face, before and after putting on and removing their masks, as well as before they touch them to readjust them. In areas with sporadic spread of COVID-19, health workers in clinical areas should wear medical masks throughout their shift apart from when eating, drinking or needing to change the mask for specific reasons. Health workers should continue to physically distance and avoid unnecessary close contact with colleagues and others in the facility when not providing patient care. Respirator masks are recommended for use where aerosol generating procedures are in place for a suspect/confirmed COVID-19 patient. In these settings, WHO recommends the use of airborne and contact precautions.As health workers have been  infected with COVID-19 outside of health facilities, it is critical that health workers, as all people, follow the guidance to protect themselves from infection when outside of a health facility.Further resources:Healthcare workers can complete our OpenWHO course on how to put on and remove personal protective equipment.Read our guidance on ‘Infection prevention and control during health care when coronavirus disease (‎COVID-19)‎ is suspected or confirmed’.WHO first issued interim guidance on recommended practices for health workers caring for suspected or confirmed COVID-19 patients in January 2020, which included following droplet/contact precautions: surgical gown, gloves, medical mask, and eye protection."},{"id":245,"category":"Mass gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-mass-gatherings","question":"How large does a meeting or event need to be in order to be a “mass gathering”?","response":"High profile international sporting events such as the Olympics or World Cups as well as international religious events such as the Hajj count as mass gatherings. However, lower profile conferences and events can also meet WHO’s definition of a mass gathering. An event counts as a “mass gatherings” if the number of people it brings together is so large that it has the potential to strain the planning and response resources of the health system in the community where it takes place. You need to consider the location and duration of the event as well as the number of participants. For example, if the event takes place over several days in a small island state where the capacity of the health system is quite limited then even an event with just a few thousand participants could place a big strain on the health system and then be considered a “mass gathering” event. Conversely, if the event is held in a big city in a country with a large, well-resourced health system and lasts just a few hours, the event may not constitute a “mass gathering” event."},{"id":246,"category":"Mass gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-mass-gatherings","question":"Does WHO recommend that all international mass gatherings be cancelled because of COVID-19?","response":"No. As each international mass gathering is different, the factors to consider when determining if the event should be cancelled may also differ. Any decision to change a planned international gathering should be based on a careful assessment of the risks and how they can be managed, and the level of event planning. The assessment should involve all stakeholders in the event, and in particular the health authorities in the country or community where the event is due to take place. These authorities and stakeholders are in the best position to assess the level of stress the event might place on the local health system and emergency services – and whether this level of stress is acceptable in the current situation. It is WHO’s view that all countries with community transmission should seriously consider postponing or reducing mass gatherings that bring people together and have the potential to amplify disease and support the recommended best practice of physical distancing. Any decision will be supported through the use of WHO tools, in particular the Risk Assessment for Mass Gatherings during COVID-19. If movement restrictions and further national measures have been established in the country, the WHO RA does not apply. However, when the process of re-opening/conducting mass gatherings is being considered post movement restrictions, it will be key to ensure any decisions are based on a risk assessment, such as the WHO Mass gatherings COVID-19 risk assessment."},{"id":247,"category":"Mass gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-mass-gatherings","question":"What factors should organizers and health authorities look at when assessing whether the risks are acceptable or not?","response":"For countries not currently known to be experiencing community transmission of COVID-19, the priority consideration will be whether the planned mass gathering event substantially increases the risk of the virus entering the country and becoming established, as well as the risk for participants to importing infection back to their home country and further increasing global spread. In making this assessment, the organizers and their national or local health authorities should recognize that the risk of imported cases of COVID-19 is naturally linked to international travel. They should also recognize that it is neither realistic or desirable to aim for zero risk. When organizers and health authorities are determining whether to hold a mass gathering, they should determine what is an acceptable risk and what additional measures should be implemented to mitigate the risks.For countries where COVID-19 has already started to spread in the community, key consideration will be: aiming at containing or at least slowing down the spread of the virus in the local community/country.preventing participants from other countries being infected with COVID-19  In each case the risk should be considered in the context of the known features of COVID-19, its severity, its transmissibility and the effectiveness of measures to prevent or reduce transmission. The strain already placed on the local health system in responding to COVID-19 outbreak(s), and the additional strain the mass gathering might place on the system also need to be taken into account.You can find more advice on what to look at in the WHO document Key planning recommendations for Mass Gatherings in the context of the current COVID-19 outbreak of 14 February 2020. See: https://www.who.int/publications-detail/key-planning-recommendations-for-mass-gatherings-in-the-context-of-the-current-covid-19-outbreak"},{"id":248,"category":"Mass gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-mass-gatherings","question":"What if my organization does not have the expertise to assess the risks COVID-19 poses for our planned mass gathering?","response":"The national and local public health authorities in the country where you plan to hold the mass gathering will most likely know how to conduct a health risk assessment. If there is a WHO Country Office there they may also be able to provide some expert support. So too might the WHO Regional Office in your part of the world. You can find the names and contact details of the WHO Regional Offices at https://www.who.int/about/who-we-are/regional-offices"},{"id":249,"category":"Mass gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-mass-gatherings","question":"If we go ahead with an international mass gathering, what can we do to reduce the risk of participants catching COVID-19?","response":"Promote hand washing, respiratory hygiene and social distancing at the event. Make sure you have emergency contact details for all participants, including where they are staying during the event. You should make it clear to them that this information will be shared with the local public health authorities to enable rapid contact tracing if a participant at the event becomes ill with COVID-19. The event organisers need to have an agreed preparedness plan in case one or more participants become ill with COVID-19 symptoms. This should include rapid isolation of the ill person and their safe transfer to a local health facility. You should consider whether the number of participants at the event could be reduced, making available participation by video or teleconference and possibly screening participants for COVID-19 symptoms (cough, fever, malaise) at points of entry to the venue. You can find advice on how individual participants can protect themselves and their loved ones from COVID-19 at: https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public"},{"id":250,"category":"Mass gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-mass-gatherings","question":"Where can I find more advice on assessing and managing health risks around international mass gatherings?","response":"WHO has produced guidance and also a training course on how to plan for a mass gathering. The guidance and the course both look at how to conduct a risk assessment, plan for and manage health risks in partnership with the local authorities: https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance/points-of-entry-and-mass-gatherings  You can find advice to give individual participants on how to protect themselves and their loved ones from COVID-19 at: https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public"},{"id":251,"category":"Mass gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-mass-gatherings","question":"What should be the criteria for excluding an athlete or other accredited participant from competing?","response":"Agreed health criteria are needed for the exclusion of athletes from competing and for allowing them to return to competition wherever appropriate. These should be consistent with public health guidelines for the general population, with risk profiles based on recent travel to high-risk community transmission zones, recent contact with individuals diagnosed with or suspected of having COVID-19, current symptomatology, etc. Athletes who are feeling unwell should not participate in events.If testing of athletes has been agreed with the local public health service there is a need to consider test availability, time taken for receipt of test results and host-country health services capacity. Criteria for exclusion of officials/judges from competition and for allowing them to return to competition where appropriate should follow guidance and criteria for the workplace.Requirements for the attendance of all athletes and other accredited participants should be put in place:–   health check: travel declaration and temperature screening–   contact tracing protocols ready (with all details of those present) –   allowing extra spacing (physical distancing)–   following all hygiene precautions.  Isolation procedures for athletes and other accredited participants (e.g. field-of-play staff, medical teams, officials who have close contact with the athletes) who feel unwell or become symptomatic should be clear and documented and rehearsed prior to holding the event, especially for higher risk sports, e.g. contact sports."},{"id":252,"category":"Mass gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-mass-gatherings","question":"Should event organizers arrange screening at venues beyond national government requirements for point of entry (PoE)?","response":"Temperature screening alone, at exit or entry, is not an effective way to stop international spread, since infected individuals may be in incubation period, may not express apparent symptoms early on in the course of the disease, or may dissimulate fever through the use of antipyretics; in addition, such measures require substantial investments for what may bear little benefits. It is more effective to provide prevention recommendation messages to travellers and to collect health declarations at arrival, with travellers’ contact details, to allow for a proper risk assessment and a possible contact tracing of incoming travellers. Event organizers should also consider the capacity to undertake this and the management of suspected cases. However, sporting organizations may have criteria for participation that are stricter than government requirements for Ports of Entry into the country that are based on event risk assessment, including organizers' healthcare capacity.Any additional screening questionnaires for participation in events need to be aligned with public health agencies in the jurisdiction. There is a need to consider how to manage different groups – athletes, officials and spectators, and the large numbers of individuals likely to arrive at a sporting event from many oversea countries – and to follow both host country and WHO travel advice and to assess whether there is difficulty in obtaining accurate information about the travel history of those individuals."},{"id":253,"category":"Mass gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-mass-gatherings","question":"Should event organizers provide COVID-19 testing?","response":"No, testing should be conducted in accordance with local health providers and national guidance.  Anyone unwell or symptomatic should not be allowed to participate in the event. Establish close collaboration with local public health authorities well before the event, to facilitate testing for athletes, officials or spectators who meet pre-agreed suspect cases definitions. Consider host-country health service capacity to manage any COVID-19 activity, and other public health issues happening at the event over and above its own national pandemic response."},{"id":254,"category":"Mass gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-mass-gatherings","question":"Are there additional safeguards event organizers can implement or recommend to athletes/officials/visitors in the context of COVID-19?","response":"Follow standard preventative advice to the general public, including physical distancing, in the athletes’ village.Also promote:signage, digital messaging to all participants and their entourages about COVID-19 and how to prevent infectionregular disinfection and cleaning of surfaces, in venues and in personal spaces non-sharing of equipment and cleaning of equipment after each user.Organizers are recommended to develop a checklist (include hand gels stations, hygiene facilities, etc.). See the event mitigation recommendations checklist for event organizers above."},{"id":255,"category":"Mass gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-mass-gatherings","question":"What are the risks arising from public transport to the venue(s)?","response":"The extra risk from participants and spectators travelling on public transport in a major city may not be significant compared to the ongoing risk to the local population using the transport all the time if physical distancing is not possible on public transport."},{"id":256,"category":"Pregnancy and childbirth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-pregnancy-and-childbirth","question":"Are pregnant women at higher risk from COVID-19?","response":"Pregnant women or recently pregnant women who are  older, overweight, and have pre-existing medical conditions such as hypertension and diabetes seem to have an increased  risk of developing severe COVID-19. When pregnant women develop severe disease, they also seem to more often require care in intensive care units than non-pregnant women of reproductive age.Due to changes in their bodies and immune systems, we know that pregnant women can be badly affected by some respiratory infections. It is therefore important that they take precautions to protect themselves against COVID-19, and report possible symptoms (including fever, cough or difficulty in breathing) to their healthcare provider.WHO will continue to review and update its information and advice as more evidence becomes available."},{"id":257,"category":"Pregnancy and childbirth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-pregnancy-and-childbirth","question":"I’m pregnant. How can I protect myself against COVID-19?","response":"Pregnant women should take the same precautions to avoid COVID-19 infection as other people. You can help protect yourself by:Washing your hands frequently with an alcohol-based hand rub or soap and water.Keeping space between yourself and others and avoiding crowded spaces. Wear a non-medical, fabric  mask where it is not possible to keep sufficient physical distance between yourself and others.Avoiding touching your eyes, nose and mouth.Practicing respiratory hygiene. This means covering your mouth and nose with your bent elbow or tissue when you cough or sneeze. Then dispose of the used tissue immediately.If you have fever, cough or difficulty breathing, seek medical care early. Call before going to a health facility, and follow the directions of your local health authority.Pregnant women and women who have recently delivered should attend their routine care appointments, according to local policies and following adapted measures to reduce possible transmission of the virus."},{"id":258,"category":"Pregnancy and childbirth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-pregnancy-and-childbirth","question":"Should pregnant women be tested for COVID-19?","response":"Testing protocols and eligibility during pregnancy vary depending on where you live.However, WHO recommendations are that pregnant women with symptoms of COVID-19 should be prioritized for testing. If they have COVID-19, they may need specialized care."},{"id":259,"category":"Pregnancy and childbirth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-pregnancy-and-childbirth","question":"Can COVID-19 be passed from a woman to her unborn or newborn baby?","response":"We still do not know if a pregnant woman with COVID-19 can pass the virus to her fetus or baby during pregnancy or delivery. To date, the active virus has not been found in samples of fluid around the baby in the womb or breastmilk."},{"id":260,"category":"Pregnancy and childbirth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-pregnancy-and-childbirth","question":"What care should be available during pregnancy and childbirth?","response":"All pregnant women and their newborns, including those with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 infections, have the right to high quality care before, during and after childbirth, including mental health care.A safe and positive childbirth experience includes:Being treated with respect and dignity;Having a companion of choice present during delivery;Clear communication by maternity staff;Appropriate pain relief strategies:Mobility in labour where possible, and birth position of choice.If COVID-19 is suspected or confirmed, health workers should take all appropriate precautions to reduce risks of infection to themselves and others, including hand hygiene, and appropriate use of protective clothing like gloves, gown and medical mask."},{"id":261,"category":"Pregnancy and childbirth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-pregnancy-and-childbirth","question":"Do pregnant women with suspected or confirmed COVID-19 need to give birth by caesarean section?","response":"No. WHO advice is that caesarean sections should only be performed when medically justified.The mode of birth should be individualized and based on a woman’s preferences alongside obstetric indications."},{"id":262,"category":"Pregnancy and childbirth","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-pregnancy-and-childbirth","question":"Can I touch and hold my newborn baby if I have COVID-19?","response":"Yes. Close contact and early, exclusive breastfeeding helps a baby to thrive. You should be supported toBreastfeed safely, with good respiratory hygiene; Hold your newborn skin-to-skin, andShare a room with your babyYou should wash your hands before and after touching your baby, and keep all surfaces clean. Mothers with symptoms of COVID-19 are advised to wear a medical mask, during any contact with the baby."},{"id":263,"category":"Risks and safety for older people","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-risks-and-safety-for-older-people","question":"What is COVID-19?","response":"COVID-19 is a disease caused by a new coronavirus, which has not been previously identified in humans. In most cases, COVID-19 causes mild symptoms including dry cough, tiredness and fever, though fever may not be a symptom for some older people. Other mild symptoms include aches and pains, nasal congestion, runny nose, sore throat or diarrhoea. Some people become infected but don’t develop any symptoms and don't feel unwell. Most people recover from the disease without needing special treatment. Around 1 out of every 6 people who get COVID-19 becomes seriously ill and has difficulty breathing."},{"id":264,"category":"Risks and safety for older people","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-risks-and-safety-for-older-people","question":"How is COVID-19 transmitted?","response":"People can catch COVID-19 from others who have the virus. The disease can spread from person to person through small droplets from the nose or mouth, which are spread when a person with COVID-19 coughs or exhales. These droplets land on objects and surfaces around the person. Other people then catch COVID-19 by touching these objects or surfaces, and then touching their eyes, nose or mouth. People can also catch COVID-19 if they breathe in droplets from a person with COVID-19 who coughs out or exhales droplets."},{"id":265,"category":"Risks and safety for older people","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-risks-and-safety-for-older-people","question":"Who is at risk of developing severe disease?","response":"Older people, and people of all ages with pre-existing medical conditions (such as diabetes, high blood pressure, heart disease, lung disease, or cancer) appear to develop serious illness more often than others."},{"id":266,"category":"Risks and safety for older people","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-risks-and-safety-for-older-people","question":"Is there a vaccine, drug or treatment for COVID-19?","response":"While some western, traditional or home remedies may provide comfort and alleviate symptoms of mild COVID-19, there are no medicines that have been shown to prevent or cure the disease. WHO does not recommend self-medication with any medicines, including antibiotics, as a prevention or cure for COVID-19. However, there are several ongoing clinical trials of both western and traditional medicines. WHO is coordinating efforts to develop vaccines and medicines to prevent and treat COVID-19 and will continue to provide updated information as soon as research results become available."},{"id":267,"category":"Risks and safety for older people","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-risks-and-safety-for-older-people","question":"What can I do to prevent infection?","response":"To prevent infection, there are a five things that you can do.\n \n1. Wash your hands frequently and thoroughly with soap and water and dry them thoroughly. \nYou can also use alcohol-based hand rub if your hands are not visibly dirty and if this product is available. Cleaning your hands frequently will remove the virus if it is on your hands. You can learn how to wash your hands in this video (or this visual). If an alcohol-based hand rub or soap is not available, then using chlorinated water (0.05%) for handwashing is an option, but it is not ideal because frequent use may irritate your skin.\n \n 2. Cover your mouth and nose with a flexed elbow or tissue when coughing and sneezing. \nAnd remember to throw away the used tissue immediately in a bin with a lid and to wash your hands. This way you protect others from any virus released through coughs and sneezes.\n \n3. Avoid touching your eyes, nose and mouth. \nHands touch many surfaces which can be contaminated with the virus. If you touch your eyes, nose or mouth with unclean hands, you can transfer the virus from the surface to yourself.\n \n4. Keep physical distance from others. \nIf your national or local authorities have put in place confinement measures, it is important to respect them. Taking exercise outside is good for your physical and mental health, but should only be undertaken if regulations for your area allow it. When you do go out, avoid crowded spaces and maintain at least 1 metre distance (3 feet or arms-length) from others. Avoid unnecessary visits to your house. If visits are necessary (e.g. caregiver to support with activities of daily living), ask your visitor to regularly check for symptoms to ensure that they are symptom free when visiting you. Ask them to also follow these five key actions, including washing their hands when they first enter your home. \n \n5. Clean and disinfect frequently touched surfaces every day. \nThis includes tables, doorknobs, light switches, countertops, handles, desks, phones, keyboards, toilets, taps, and sinks. If surfaces are dirty, use detergent or soap and water prior to disinfection. Learn more by clicking here."},{"id":268,"category":"Risks and safety for older people","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-risks-and-safety-for-older-people","question":"What can older people do to prepare for COVID-19 in their community?","response":"There is a lot that you can do to prepare for COVID-19 in your community. Inform yourself of the special measures taken in your community as well as the services and the sources of reliable information that are availableduring the health emergency  (e.g. home deliveries, psychosocial support, health ministry website, alternative access to your pension). Create a list of the basic supplies that you will need for at least two weeks and try to get these delivered where possible (e.g. non-perishable food items, household products, batteries for assistive\n            devices you may use, and prescription medicines). Alternatively, ask family members, caregivers, neighbours or community leaders to help with ordering and/or delivery of groceries or prescription medicines. Make sure that your mobile phone\n            credit is topped up and identify a safe place to charge your phone regularly so that you can keep in contact with family and friends and reach emergency services if needed.   Make a list of emergency numbers (e.g. COVID-19 local helpline, nearby hospital and health emergencies numbers, hotline for victims of abuse, psychosocial support hotline) and support contacts (e.g. family members\n            and friends, main caregiver, community care worker, associations of older persons). If you live alone, you may wish to share this list and ask your neighbours, family or caregiver to be in touch regularly, for example, by phone or video chat. Discuss with your health-care worker how your health needs can be addressed during COVID-19. This may involve postponing non-urgent appointments, talking to your doctor or health-care worker by phone or video chat instead\n            of in person and/or revising your vaccination schedule. If you rely on the support provided by a caregiver, identify with him or her another person that you trust to support your daily living and care needs in case your caregiver is unable to continue to provide\n            care. Together, you can note down all the personal care and assistance that you require and how it should be provided and share it with this trusted person so that they can be ready to provide care in case of need.  If you are the primary caregiver of another person who is care dependent (e.g. grandchild, older spouse, child with a disability), identify a person that you and the person that you care for trust to take on your caregiving responsibilities in case you fall sick.\n Local authorities or volunteer organizations that provide support in these situations in your community might be able to help. If multiple people live in your home, if possible prepare a separate room or space in your home so that anyone showing symptoms compatible with COVID-19 can be isolated from others. If you do not have space for self-isolation,\n            contact your community leaders or local health authorities to see if there is community space that could help you or other household members self-isolate. Think about what matters most to you regarding care and support, including medical treatment, in case something happens to you and you are unable to make your own decisions. If you want to develop an advanced care plan to record\n            your treatment and care wishes, you can talk about it with your health-care worker or someone that you trust. You can write down your wishes and  share them with people you trust."},{"id":269,"category":"Risks and safety for older people","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-risks-and-safety-for-older-people","question":"How can I keep healthy on a daily basis during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"You can follow these 10 steps to keep healthy during the COVID-19 pandemic.Keep to your regular routines as much as possible and maintain a daily schedule for yourself including sleeping, meals and activities.  Stay socially connected. Speak to loved ones and people you trust every day or as much as possible, using the telephone, video-calls or messaging, through writing letters, etc. Use this time to share your feelings and to do common\n        hobbies together.\n         \nBe physically active every day. Reduce long periods of sitting and set up a daily routine that includes at least 30 minutes of exercise. Make sure to do activities that are safe and appropriate for your level of physical fitness as\n        indicated by your health-care worker. You can use household chores as a way to keep physically active, follow an on-line class (e.g. Tai Chi, yoga) or choose your favourite music and dance to that. \n Drink water and eat healthy and well-balanced meals. This will keep you hydrated, help strengthen your immune system and lower the risk of chronic illnesses and infectious diseases.  For nutrition advice click here.\n  Avoid smoking and drinking alcohol. Smokers are likely to be more vulnerable to COVID-19 because smoking can affect lung capacity and because the act of smoking increases the possibility of transmission of virus from hand\n        to mouth. Drinking alcohol not only disturbs your sleep but may also increase your risk of falls, weaken your immune system, and interact with any prescription medicines that you are taking. Limit the amount of alcohol you drink or don’t\n        drink alcohol at all.\n         Take breaks from news coverage about COVID-19 as prolonged exposure can cause feelings of anxiety and despair. Seek updates at specific times of the day from a reliable source like the \n        WHO website (click here) or national or local channels in order to help you distinguish facts from rumours or scams.  Engage in hobbies and activities that you enjoy or learn something new. Cognitive exercise such as reading a book or doing crosswords/Sudoku will keep your mind active and distract you from worrying. You can also use this time to\n        keep a well-being diary (click here for an example.)\n If you have ongoing health conditions, take your prescribed medicines and follow the advice of your health-care worker regarding any health visits or phone consultations.\n         If you have an emergency medical condition that is not related to COVID-19, contact health emergencies immediately and ask what you should do next. Follow the instructions of the health-care worker. \n If stress, worry, fear or sadness get in the way of your daily activities for several days in a row, seek psychosocial support from available services in your community.  If you are subject to abuse or violence from\n        others, tell someone you trust and report this to the relevant authorities. You can also seek support from dedicated helplines that may be available in your country."},{"id":270,"category":"Risks and safety for older people","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-risks-and-safety-for-older-people","question":"What should I do if I have symptoms of COVID-19?","response":"If you present symptoms related to COVID-19, seek medical advice. Call by phone first if possible and give information about pre-existing health conditions and medicines that you are taking. Follow the instructions of the health-care worker and monitor your symptoms regularly.  If you have difficulty breathing, contact health emergencies immediately as this may be due to a respiratory infection. Call by phone first if possible to learn what to do next. If you live with others, make sure that you isolate yourself as soon as you suspect infectionby using the space that you identified in advance. You and other members of the household should also wear a medical mask as much as possible if these are available. You can learn how to wear a mask here. If you live with others and home care for COVID-19 is advised by your health-care worker, other household members should follow available guidance on home care for patients with COVID-19 presenting with mild symptoms and management of their contacts (guidance here). See related flyers for people who are ill, for household members and for caregivers.  If you live alone and home care for COVID-10 is advised by your health-care worker, ask your family, friends, neighbours, health-care worker or a local volunteer organisation to check in on you regularly and to provide support as needed following existing guidance for caregivers (guidance here)."},{"id":271,"category":"Risks and safety for older people","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-risks-and-safety-for-older-people","question":"I have recently lost someone I care about. What advice do you have to help me cope?","response":"Losing someone close to you is always hard, whatever the cause. During these extraordinary circumstances, when your usual routine may be disrupted and when funerals may not be permitted, it may be even harder. Following this advice may help. Do not criticise yourself for how you feel. When you lose a family member or friend to COVID-19, you may experience a range of emotions.  You may also have difficulty sleeping or low levels of energy. All these feelings are normal\n        and there is no right or wrong way to feel grief. Allow yourself time to process your emotions in response to your loss. You may think that the sadness and pain that you feel will never go away, but in most cases, these feelings lessen over time. Talk regularly with people that you trust about your feelings. Keep to your routines as much as you feel able and try to focus on activities that bring you joy. Seek advice and comfort from people that you trust (e.g. religious/faith leaders, mental health workers or other trusted members of your community) while maintaining physical distance (e.g. attending virtual mass).    Think of alternative ways to say goodbye to the person who passed away such as writing a letter or dedicating a drawing to your loved one. These are small actions that can help you cope with grief and loss, particularly in situations where funeral services are not permitted"},{"id":272,"category":"Risks and safety for older people","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-risks-and-safety-for-older-people","question":"What precautions are necessary when visiting someone in a health and/or long-term care facility?","response":"If you have been in contact with someone suspected or confirmed with COVID-19, or are feeling unwell, do not visit any health or long-term care facility.Follow the facility guidelines on any visit requirements, including screening and wearing a mask.Clean your hands before entering and try to keep at least a 1 metre distance from others.If you are 60 or over, or have a chronic condition like heart disease, take extra precautions by wearing a medical mask during your visit."},{"id":273,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"Are children at lower risk of COVID-19 than adults?","response":"So far, data suggests that children under the age of 18 years represent about 8.5% of reported cases, with relatively few deaths compared to other age groups and usually mild disease. However, cases of critical illness have been reported. As with adults, pre-existing medical conditions have been suggested as a risk factor for severe disease and intensive care admission in children.Further studies are underway to assess the risk of infection in children and to better understand transmission in this age group."},{"id":274,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"What is the role of children in transmission?","response":"The role of children in transmission is not yet fully understood. To date, few outbreaks involving children or schools have been reported. However, the small number of outbreaks reported among teaching or associated staff to date suggests that spread\n    of COVID-19 within educational settings may be limited.As children generally have milder illness and fewer symptoms, cases may sometimes go unnoticed. Importantly, early data from studies suggest that infection rates among teenagers may be higher than in younger children.Considering that many countries are starting to slowly lift restrictions on activities, the longer-term effects of keeping schools open on community transmission are yet to be evaluated. Some modelling studies suggest that school re-opening might have\n    a small effect on wider transmission in the community, but this is not well understood. Further studies are underway on the role of children in transmission in and outside of educational settings. WHO is collaborating with scientists around the world\n    to develop protocols that countries can use to study COVID-19 transmission in educational institutions. Click here to access this information."},{"id":275,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"Should children with underlying health conditions (asthma, diabetes, obesity) return to school?","response":"Whether a child should go to school depends on their health condition, the current transmission of COVID-19 within their community, and the protective measures the school and community have in place to reduce the risk of COVID-19 transmission. While current evidence suggests that the risk of severe disease for children is lower overall than for adults, special precautions can be taken to minimize the risk of infection among children, and the benefits of returning to school should also be considered.Current evidence suggests that people with underlying conditions such as chronic respiratory illness including asthma (moderate-to-severe), obesity, diabetes or cancer, are at higher risk of developing severe disease and death than people without other health conditions. This also appears to be the case for children, but more information is still needed."},{"id":276,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"Should teachers and other staff with underlying health conditions return to school?","response":"Adults 60 years and older and people with underlying health conditions are at higher risk for severe disease and death. The decision to return to a teaching environment depends on the individual and should include consideration of local disease trends, as well as the measures being put in place in schools to prevent further spread."},{"id":277,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"What is the incubation period for children?","response":"The incubation period for children is the same as in adults. The time between exposure to COVID-19 and when symptoms start is commonly around 5 to 6 days, and ranges from 1 to 14 days."},{"id":278,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"What should be considered when deciding whether to re-open schools or keep them open?","response":"Deciding to close, partially close or reopen schools should be guided by a risk-based approach, to maximize the educational, well-being and health benefit for students, teachers, staff, and the wider community, and help prevent a new outbreak of COVID-19 in the community.Several elements should be assessed in deciding to re-open schools or keep them open:The epidemiology of COVID-19 at the local level: This may vary from one place to another within a countryBenefits and risks: what are the likely benefits and risks to children and staff of open schools? Including consideration of:Transmission intensity in the area where the school operates: No cases, sporadic transmission; clusters transmission or community transmissionOverall impact of school closures on education, general health and wellbeing; and on vulnerable and marginalized populations (e.g. girls, displaced or disabled)Effectiveness of remote learning strategiesDetection and response: Are the local health authorities able to act quickly?The capacity of schools/educational institutions to operate safelyCollaboration and coordination: Is the school collaborating with local public health authorities?The range of other public health measures being implemented outside school"},{"id":279,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"What benefits would school re-opening provide?","response":"School closures have clear negative impacts on child health, education and development, family income and the overall economy.The decision to reopen schools should include consideration of the following benefits:Allowing students to complete their studies and continue to the next levelEssential services, access to nutrition, child welfare, such as preventing violence against childrenSocial and psychological well-beingAccess to reliable information on how to keep themselves and others safeReducing the risk of non-return to schoolBenefit to society, such as allowing parents to work"},{"id":280,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"What are the prevention and control measures to be prepared and put in place in schools?","response":"There are several actions and requirements that should be reviewed and put in place to prevent the introduction and spread of COVID-19 in schools and into the community; and to ensure the safety of children and school staff while at school. Special provisions should be considered for early childhood development, higher learning institutions, residential schools or specialized institutions.WHO recommends the following:Community-level measures: Carry out early detection, testing, contact tracing and quarantine of contacts; investigate clusters; ensure physical distancing, hand and hygiene practices and age-appropriate mask use; shield vulnerable groups. Community-led initiatives such as addressing misleading rumors also play an important role in reducing the risk of infection.Policy, practice and infrastructure: Ensure the necessary resources, policies and infrastructure, are in place that protect the health and safety of all school personnel, including people at higher risk.Behavioral aspects: Consider the age and capacity of students to understand and respect measures put in place. Younger children may find it more difficult to adhere to physical distancing or the appropriate use of masks.Safety and security: School closure or re-opening may affect the safety and security of students and the most vulnerable children may require special attention, such as during pick-up and drop-off.Hygiene and daily practices at the school and classroom level: Physical distancing of at least 1 metre between individuals including spacing of desks, frequent hand and respiratory hygiene, age-appropriate mask use, ventilation and environmental cleaning measures should be in place to limit exposure. Schools should educate staff and students on COVID-19 prevention measures, develop a schedule for daily cleaning and disinfection of the school environment, facilities and frequently touches surfaces, and ensure availability of hand hygiene facilities and national/local guidance on the use of masks.Screening and care of sick students, teachers and other school staff: Schools should enforce the policy of “staying home if unwell”, waive the requirement for a doctor’s note, create a checklist for parents/students/staff to decide whether to go to school (taking into consideration the local situation), ensure students who have been in contact with a COVID-19 case stay home for 14 days, and consider options for screening on arrival.Protection of individuals at high-risk: Schools should identify students and teachers at high-risk with pre-existing medical conditions to come up with strategies to keep them safe; maintain physical distancing and se of medical masks as well as frequent hand hygiene and respiratory etiquette.Communication with parents and students: Schools should keep students and parents informed about the measures being implemented to ensure their collaboration and support.Additional school-related measures such as immunization checks and catch-up vaccination programmes: Ensure continuity or expansion of essential services, including school feeding and mental health and psycho-social support.Physical distancing outside classrooms: Maintain a distance of at least 1 metre for both students (all age groups) and staff, where feasible.Physical distancing inside classrooms:In areas with community transmission of COVID-19, maintain a distance of at least 1 metre between all individuals of all age groups, for any schools remaining open. This includes increasing desk spacing and staging recesses, breaks and lunchbreaks; limiting the mixing of classes and of age groups; considering smaller classes or alternating attendance schedules, and ensuring good ventilation in classrooms.In areas with cluster-transmission of COVID-19, a risk-based approach should be taken when deciding whether to keep a distance of at least 1 metre between students. Staff should always keep at least 1 metre apart from each other and from students and should wear a mask in situations where 1-metre distance is not practical.In areas with sporadic cases/no cases of COVID-19, children under the age of 12 should not be required to keep physical distance at all times. Where feasible, children aged 12 and over should keep at least 1 metre apart from each other.  Staff should always keep at least 1 metre from each other and from students and should wear a mask in situations where 1-metre distance is not practical.  Remote learning: Where children cannot attend classes in person, support should be given to ensure students have continued access to educational materials and technologies (internet, texting radio, radio, or television), (e.g. delivering assignments or broadcasting lessons). Shutting down educational facilities   should only be considered when no alternatives are available."},{"id":281,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"Checklist for parents/caregivers and community members","response":"Monitor your child’s health and keep them home from school if they are ill.Teach and model good hygiene practices for your children:Wash your hands with soap and safe water frequently. If soap and water are not readily available, use an alcohol-based hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol. Always wash hands with soap and water, if hands are visibly dirty.Ensure that safe drinking water is available and toilets or latrines are clean and available at home.Ensure waste is safely collected, stored and disposed of.Cough and sneeze into a tissue or your elbow and avoid touching your face, eyes, mouth and nose.Encourage your children to ask questions and express their feelings with you and their teachers. Remember that your child may have different reactions to stress; be patient and understanding. Prevent stigma by using facts and reminding students to be considerate of one another.Coordinate with the school to receive information and ask how you can support school safety efforts (though parent-teacher committees, etc),."},{"id":282,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"Checklist for students and children","response":"In a situation like this it is normal to feel sad, worried, confused, scared or angry. Know that you are not alone and talk to someone you trust, like your parent or teacher so that you can help keep yourself and your school safe and healthy.Ask questions, educate yourself and get information from reliable sources.Protect yourself and others:Wash your hands frequently, always with soap and water for at least 20 seconds.Remember to not touch your face, eyes, nose and mouth.Do not share cups, eating utensils, food or drinks with others.Be a leader in keeping yourself, your school, family and community healthy.  Share what you learn about preventing disease with your family and friends, especially with younger children Model good practices such as sneezing or coughing into your elbow and washing your hands, especially for younger family members.Don’t stigmatize your peers or tease anyone about being sick; remember that the virus doesn’t follow geographical boundaries, ethnicities, age or ability or gender. Tell your parents, another family member, or a caregiver if you feel sick, and ask to stay home."},{"id":283,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"What are the risks during transportation to and from schools?","response":"The following adaptations to transport to and from school should be implemented to limit unnecessary exposure of school or staff members.Promote and put in place respiratory and hand hygiene, physical distancing measures and use of masks in transportation such as school buses, in accordance with local policy.Provide tips for how to safely commute to and from school, including for public transportation.Organize only one child per seat and ensure physical distancing of at least 1 metre between passengers in school buses, if possible. This may require more school buses per school.If possible and safe, keep the windows of the buses, vans, and other vehicles open."},{"id":284,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"Does WHO recommend staff and children to wear masks at school? And if yes, what type of masks?","response":"In countries or areas where there is intense community transmission of COVID-19 and in settings where physical distancing cannot be achieved, the following criteria for use of masks in schools are recommended:1. Children aged 5 years and under should not be required to wear masks.2. For children between six and 11 years of age, a risk-based approach should be applied to the decision to use a mask, considering:intensity of transmission in the area where the child is and evidence on the risk of infection and transmission in this age group.beliefs, customs and behaviours.the child’s capacity to comply with the correct use of masks and availability of adult supervision.potential impact of mask wearing on learning and development.additional considerations such as sport activities or for children with disabilities or underlying diseases.3. Children and adolescents 12 years or older should follow the national mask guidelines for adults.4. Teacher and support staff may be required to wear masks when they cannot guarantee at least a 1-metre distance from others or there is widespread transmission in the area.Types of mask:Fabric masks are recommended to prevent onward transmission in the general population in public areas, particularly where distancing is not possible, and in areas of community transmission. This could include the school grounds in some situations.\n    Masks may help to protect others, because wearers may be infected before symptoms of illness appear. The policy on wearing a mask or face covering should be in line with national or local guidelines. Where\n    used, masks should be worn, cared for and disposed of properly. The use of masks by children and adolescents in schools should only be considered as one part of a strategy to limit the spread of COVID-19."},{"id":285,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"Are there any specific recommendations on school ventilation and air conditioning use?","response":"Yes, ensure adequate ventilation and increase total airflow supply to occupied spaces, if possible. Clean, natural ventilation (i.e., opening windows) should be used inside buildings where possible, without re-circulating the air. If heating, ventilation and air conditioning systems are used they should be regularly inspected, maintained and cleaned. Rigorous standards for installation, maintenance and filtration are essential to make sure they are effective and safe. Consider running the systems at maximum outside airflow for two hours before and after times when the building is occupied, according to the manufacturer’s recommendations."},{"id":286,"category":"Schools","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-schools","question":"What should be monitored after re-opening of school?","response":"The following should be monitored:effectiveness of symptoms-reporting, monitoring, rapid testing and tracing of suspected casesthe effects of policies and measures on educational objectives and learning outcomesthe effects of policies and measures on health and well-being of children, siblings, staff, parents and other family membersthe trend in school dropouts after lifting the restrictionsthe number of cases in children and staff in the school, and frequency of school-based outbreaks in the local administrative area and the country.Assessment of impact of remote teaching on learning outcomes.Based on what is learned from this monitoring, further modifications should be made to continue to provide children and staff with the safest environment possible."},{"id":287,"category":"Self-care interventions for sexual and reproductive health and rights (SRHR)","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-self-care-interventions-for-sexual-and-reproductive-health-and-rights","question":"What is self care?","response":"WHO’s definition of self care is the ability of individuals, families and communities to promote health, prevent disease, maintain health, and to cope with illness and disability with or without the support of a health worker."},{"id":288,"category":"Self-care interventions for sexual and reproductive health and rights (SRHR)","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-self-care-interventions-for-sexual-and-reproductive-health-and-rights","question":"What are self-care interventions?","response":"Self-care interventions recommended by WHO are evidence-based and can include information about a sexual or reproductive health issue as well as ways in which individuals can obtain drugs, devices, diagnostics and/or digital products fully or partially separate from formal health services that can be used with or without the direct supervision of a health worker. For example, self-injectable contraception, HPV self-sampling kits or HIV self-tests."},{"id":289,"category":"Self-care interventions for sexual and reproductive health and rights (SRHR)","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-self-care-interventions-for-sexual-and-reproductive-health-and-rights","question":"Why are self-care interventions important during a pandemic like COVID-19?","response":"With the major disruptions to the normal functioning of national health systems caused by the need to respond to people who have or are affected by the virus, evidence-based, high-quality self-care interventions can provide an important alternative to the usual health facility- or health worker-based services. Self-care is a valuable part of a well-functioning health system and can be particularly useful when physical distancing measures make it more difficult for people to access their normal health care services and medications.\n\nMore information can be found here:"},{"id":290,"category":"Self-care interventions for sexual and reproductive health and rights (SRHR)","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-self-care-interventions-for-sexual-and-reproductive-health-and-rights","question":"Do I need to see a health worker for self care actions?","response":"Self-care interventions provide individuals, families and communities with a way to manage their own health at home. Some self-care actions, such as washing your hands and practicing good respiratory hygiene measures that protect you from COVID-19, do not need you to meet with a health worker. Other self-care interventions, such as obtaining a prescription for hormonal contraception and abortion medications or counselling during pregnancy, will need interaction with a health worker. Such support can be provided in different ways during this pandemic and will depend on the healthcare arrangements in place where you live; for example, some medicines are available over-the-counter without a prescription in a pharmacy, or counseling and important information during pregnancy and when caring for a newborn can be provided over the phone or online."},{"id":291,"category":"Self-care interventions for sexual and reproductive health and rights (SRHR)","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-self-care-interventions-for-sexual-and-reproductive-health-and-rights","question":"What self care actions can I take to protect my sexual and reproductive health?","response":"In 2019, WHO issued a new guideline that brought together 32 existing or new recommendations on a range of sexual and reproductive health self-care interventions. The guideline has recommendations on pregnancy and newborn care, contraception, abortion, sexually transmitted infections including HIV and HPV, and for sexual health more broadly. The full list of recommendations can be found here:"},{"id":292,"category":"Self-care interventions for sexual and reproductive health and rights (SRHR)","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-self-care-interventions-for-sexual-and-reproductive-health-and-rights","question":"How can I get healthcare support during the COVID-19 pandemic for a self-care intervention?","response":"There are a number of ways in which support can be provided:\nDigital technologies and platforms, such as helplines through the phone or online or websites of organizations with recognized expertise may be available for consultation or follow up. Such information sources could enable you to then proceed with obtaining and self-administering an injectable contraceptive or self-testing for HIV, for example.\n\nIt may also be possible to get over the counter medical devices, medicines, information and diagnostics through pharmacies or drug stores. Menstrual hygiene products, pregnancy tests, condoms and emergency contraception pills are usually available over-the-counter and depending on where you live, contraceptive pills and drugs that protect you from getting HIV if you think you have been exposed to risk.\n\nYou may also be able to receive communications in a variety of ways that can help keep you healthy. Examples include notifications and reminders about taking medicines sent by SMS or email."},{"id":293,"category":"Self-care interventions for sexual and reproductive health and rights (SRHR)","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-self-care-interventions-for-sexual-and-reproductive-health-and-rights","question":"Is self care safe?","response":"For all of the recommendations on self-care interventions on sexual and reproductive health issued by WHO, the evidence to date suggests that self care is safe, with the right level of support by the health service as needed.\n\nSelf-care can also benefit health workers, by allowing them to serve a greater number of patients and deploying their clinical skills where greatest need exists. During a pandemic such as COVID-19, adopting self-care as part of the healthcare system can also reduce the exposure of health workers to infection as self-care will reduce the number of in-person contacts with a health worker."},{"id":294,"category":"Self-care interventions for sexual and reproductive health and rights (SRHR)","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-self-care-interventions-for-sexual-and-reproductive-health-and-rights","question":"Who is self care for?","response":"Self care can be practiced by everyone and evidence-based self-care interventions have the potential to benefit even the most vulnerable populations. For individuals who may need to access information, counselling or a health services before, during or after accessing a self-care intervention, links with existing health services remains important. Examples of providing access to referrals and health facilities for non-COVID-19 related SRH conditions may include ensuring antenatal care visits, delivery and postpartum care; retesting and HIV treatment if an individual’s HIV self-test is positive along with other STI diagnostic and treatment as required. In addition, crisis centers, shelters, legal aid, and protection services for individuals subject to violence."},{"id":295,"category":"Self-care interventions for sexual and reproductive health and rights (SRHR)","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-self-care-interventions-for-sexual-and-reproductive-health-and-rights","question":"Where can I get more information?","response":"Further information about self-care can be found on the WHO website:4\nMore information about COVID-19 and sexual and reproductive health\nMore information on COVID-19"},{"id":296,"category":"Serology, antibodies and immunity","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-serology","question":"What is serology?","response":"‘Serology’ is the study of antibodies in blood serum.  \n‘Antibodies’ are part of the body’s immune response to infection. Antibodies that work against SARS-CoV-2 – the virus that causes COVID-19 – are usually detectable in the first few weeks after infection. The presence of antibodies indicates that a person was infected with SARS-CoV-2, irrespective of whether the individual had severe or mild disease, or no symptoms.\n‘Seroprevalence studies’ are conducted to measure the extent of infection, as measured by antibody levels, in a population under study. With any new virus, including SARS-CoV-2, initial seroprevalence in the population is assumed to be low or non-existent due to the fact that the virus has not circulated before."},{"id":297,"category":"Serology, antibodies and immunity","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-serology","question":"What is the difference between molecular testing and serologic testing?","response":"‘Molecular testing’, including polymerase-chain reaction (PCR) testing, detects genetic material of the virus and so can detect if a person is currently infected with SARS-CoV-2.\n‘Serologic testing’ detects antibodies against a virus, measuring the amount of antibodies produced following infection, thereby detecting if a person has previously been infected by SARS-CoV-2. Serologic tests should not be used to diagnose acute SARS-CoV-2 infection, as antibodies develop a few weeks after infection."},{"id":298,"category":"Serology, antibodies and immunity","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-serology","question":"What is the purpose of serologic testing?","response":"When a new disease, like COVID-19 emerges, initial surveillance and testing strategies focus initially on patients with severe disease and the use of molecular testing to measure acute infections, as these are the individuals who seek and require health care. This can often miss the fraction of mild or asymptomatic infections that do not require medical attention, and as such, the full extent of infection is not known early in an outbreak.\nSerologic testing helps retrospectively determine the size of an outbreak or extent of infection in a population under study. Seroprevalence studies give a more complete picture of how much of a population has been infected with SARS-CoV-2 and will capture unrecognized cases not identified through routine or active surveillance."},{"id":299,"category":"Serology, antibodies and immunity","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-serology","question":"Does the presence of antibodies mean that a person is immune?","response":"There are many studies underway to better understand the antibody response following infection to SARS-CoV-2.  Several studies to date show that most people who have been infected with SARS-CoV-2 develop antibodies specific to this virus. However, the levels of these antibodies can vary between those who have severe disease (higher levels of antibodies) and those with milder disease or asymptomatic infection (lower levels of antibodies). Many studies are underway to better understand the levels of antibodies that are needed for protection, and how long these antibodies last."},{"id":300,"category":"Serology, antibodies and immunity","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-serology","question":"Can people who have had SARS-CoV-2 infection be re-infected?","response":"To date, there are some reports of individuals who have been reinfected with SARS-CoV-2.  There are likely to be more examples of reinfection reported and scientists are working to understand the role of the immune response in the first and second infection. WHO is working with scientists to understand each occurrence of reinfection and the antibody response during the first and subsequent infections."},{"id":301,"category":"Serology, antibodies and immunity","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-serology","question":"What are the results of seroprevalence studies published to date?","response":"There are now more than 200 peer-reviewed publications,  pre-prints,  manuscripts and government reports of SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence studies. These studies vary in study design, populations under study, serologic tests used, timing of sample collection, and quality. Overall, the population-based seroprevalence reported across available studies remains low, at below 10%.\nSome studies conducted in areas of known high virus transmission and studies of health care workers in areas of known high transmission have reported seroprevalence estimates over 20%.\nAvailable study results indicate that, globally, most people remain susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection."},{"id":302,"category":"Serology, antibodies and immunity","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-serology","question":"What is herd immunity?","response":"'Herd immunity', also known as 'population immunity', is the indirect protection from an infectious disease that happens when a population is immune either through vaccination or immunity developed through previous infection. WHO supports achieving 'herd immunity' through vaccination, not by allowing a disease to spread through any segment of the population, as this would result in unnecessary cases and deaths.Herd immunity against COVID-19 should be achieved by protecting people through vaccination, not by exposing them to the pathogen that causes the disease. Read the Director-General’s 12 October media briefing speech for more detail. Vaccines train our immune systems to create proteins that fight disease, known as ‘antibodies’, just as would happen when we are exposed to a disease but – crucially – vaccines work without making us sick. Vaccinated people are protected from getting the disease in question and passing on the pathogen, breaking any chains of transmission. Visit our webpage on COVID-19 and vaccines for more detail. To safely achieve herd immunity against COVID-19, a substantial proportion of a population would need to be vaccinated, lowering the overall amount of virus able to spread in the whole population. One of the aims with working towards herd immunity is to keep vulnerable groups who cannot get vaccinated (e.g. due to health conditions like allergic reactions to the vaccine) safe and protected from the disease. Read our Q&A on vaccines and immunization for more information.The percentage of people who need to be immune in order to achieve herd immunity varies with each disease. For example, herd immunity against measles requires about 95% of a population to be vaccinated. The remaining 5% will be protected by the fact that measles will not spread among those who are vaccinated. For polio, the threshold is about 80%. The proportion of the population that must be vaccinated against COVID-19 to begin inducing herd immunity is not known. This is an important area of research and will likely vary according to the community, the vaccine, the populations prioritized for vaccination, and other factors.  Achieving herd immunity with safe and effective vaccines makes diseases rarer and saves lives. Find out more about the science behind herd immunity by watching or reading this interview with WHO’s Chief Scientist, Dr Soumya Swaminathan."},{"id":303,"category":"Similarities and differences with influenza","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-similarities-and-differences-with-influenza","question":"How are COVID-19 and influenza viruses similar?","response":"Firstly, COVID-19 and influenza viruses have a similar disease presentation. That is, they both cause respiratory disease, which presents as a wide range of illness from asymptomatic or mild through to severe disease and death.  Secondly, both viruses are transmitted by contact, droplets and fomites. As a result, the same public health measures, such as hand hygiene and good respiratory etiquette (coughing into your elbow or into a tissue and immediately disposing of the tissue), are important actions all can take to prevent infection."},{"id":304,"category":"Similarities and differences with influenza","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-similarities-and-differences-with-influenza","question":"How are COVID-19 and influenza viruses different?","response":"The speed of transmission is an important point of difference between the two viruses. Influenza has a shorter median incubation period (the time from infection to appearance of symptoms) and a shorter serial interval (the time between successive cases) than COVID-19 virus. The serial interval for COVID-19 virus is estimated to be 5-6 days, while for influenza virus, the serial interval is 3 days. This means that influenza can spread faster than COVID-19.   Further, transmission in the first 3-5 days of illness, or potentially pre-symptomatic transmission –transmission of the virus before the appearance of symptoms – is a major driver of transmission for influenza. In contrast, while we are learning that there are people who can shed COVID-19 virus 24-48 hours prior to symptom onset, at present, this does not appear to be a major driver of transmission.   The reproductive number – the number of secondary infections generated from one infected individual – is understood to be between 2 and 2.5 for COVID-19 virus, higher than for influenza. However, estimates for both COVID-19 and influenza viruses are very context and time-specific, making direct comparisons more difficult.   Children are important drivers of influenza virus transmission in the community. For COVID-19 virus, initial data indicates that children are less affected than adults and that clinical attack rates in the 0-19 age group are low. Further preliminary data from household transmission studies in China suggest that children are infected from adults, rather than vice versa.  While the range of symptoms for the two viruses is similar, the fraction with severe disease appears to be different. For COVID-19, data to date suggest that 80% of infections are mild or asymptomatic, 15% are severe infection, requiring oxygen and 5% are critical infections, requiring ventilation. These fractions of severe and critical infection would be higher than what is observed for influenza infection. Those most at risk for severe influenza infection are children, pregnant women, elderly, those with underlying chronic medical conditions and those who are immunosuppressed. For COVID-19, our current understanding is that older age and underlying conditions increase the risk for severe infection.  Mortality for COVID-19 appears higher than for influenza, especially seasonal influenza. While the true mortality of COVID-19 will take some time to fully understand, the data we have so far indicate that the crude mortality ratio (the number of reported deaths divided by the reported cases) is between 3-4%, the infection mortality rate (the number of reported deaths divided by the number of infections) will be lower. For seasonal influenza, mortality is usually well below 0.1%. However, mortality is to a large extent determined by access to and quality of health care."},{"id":305,"category":"Similarities and differences with influenza","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-similarities-and-differences-with-influenza","question":"What medical interventions are available for COVID-19 and influenza viruses?","response":"While there are a number of therapeutics currently in clinical trials in China and more than 20 vaccines in development for COVID-19, there are currently no licensed vaccines or therapeutics for COVID-19.  In contrast, antivirals and vaccines available for influenza. While the influenza vaccine is not effective against COVID-19 virus, it is highly recommended to get vaccinated each year to prevent influenza infection."},{"id":306,"category":"Small public gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-small-public-gatherings","question":"I am ATTENDING a small gathering or an event such as a wedding, a party or sports tournament. What precautions should I take to protect myself and others from getting infected with COVID-19?","response":"Always check local regulations before attending an event.Stay at home if you are feeling unwell.Always comply with the following 3 basic preventive measures:Maintain at least 1 metre distance from others, and wear a mask if you cannot guarantee this distance.Cover a sneeze or cough with a tissue or bent elbow, and immediately dispose of tissue in a closed-lid bin. Avoid touching eyes, nose and mouth.Wash your hands frequently with soap and water, or with a hand sanitizer."},{"id":307,"category":"Small public gatherings","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-small-public-gatherings","question":"I am ORGANIZING a small gathering or an event such as a wedding, a party or sports tournament. What precautions should I take to prevent the spread of COVID-19 among guests?","response":"Always check local guidelines before planning your event.Brief guests about precautions before the event starts; during the event, remind guests of these precautions and ensure they are followed.Choose outdoor venues over indoor spaces – if indoors, ensure the area is well-ventilated.Minimize crowding by staggering arrivals and departures, numbering entries, designating seats/places and marking the floor to ensure physical distancing between people of at least one meter.Provide all necessary supplies – hand hygiene stations, hand sanitizer or soap and water, tissues, closed-lid bins, distance markers, masks."},{"id":308,"category":"Solidarity Trial and hydroxychloroquine","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hydroxychloroquine","question":"Why was the use of hydroxychloroquine stopped in the Solidarity Trial?","response":"On 17 June 2020, WHO announced that the hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) arm of the Solidarity Trial to find an effective COVID-19 treatment was being stopped. The trial's Executive Group and principal investigators made the decision based on evidence from the Solidarity trial, UK's Recovery trial and a Cochrane review of other evidence on hydroxychloroquine.Data from Solidarity (including the French Discovery trial data) and the recently announced results from the UK's Recovery trial both showed that hydroxychloroquine does not result in the reduction of mortality of hospitalised COVID-19 patients, when compared with standard of care."},{"id":309,"category":"Solidarity Trial and hydroxychloroquine","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hydroxychloroquine","question":"What will happen to the people who were already enrolled in the hydroxychloroquine arm of the trial?","response":"Investigators will not randomize further patients to hydroxychloroquine in the Solidarity trial. Patients who have already started hydroxychloroquine but who have not yet finished their course in the trial may complete their course or stop at the discretion of the supervising physician. The use of hydroxychloroquine and chloroquine are accepted as generally safe for use in patients with autoimmune diseases or malaria."},{"id":310,"category":"Solidarity Trial and hydroxychloroquine","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hydroxychloroquine","question":"What is WHO’s view of the use of hydroxychloroquine in pre or post-exposure prophylaxis?","response":"The decision to stop hydroxychloroquine’s use in the Solidarity trial does not apply to the use or evaluation of hydroxychloroquine in pre or post-exposure prophylaxis in patients exposed to COVID-19."},{"id":311,"category":"Solidarity Trial and hydroxychloroquine","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-hydroxychloroquine","question":"What is the Solidarity Trial?","response":"The Solidarity Trial is an international clinical trial to help find an effective treatment for COVID-19, launched by WHO and partners. It is hoped that one or more of the treatments under trial will result in improving clinical outcomes in COVID-19 patients and save lives. Other trials are on-going around the world in addition to the Solidarity Trial. The treatment options are: Remdesivir; Lopinavir/Ritonavir; and Lopinavir/Ritonavir with Interferon beta-1a. The treatment options were originally selected based on evidence from laboratory, animal and clinical studies. Hydroxychloroquine was originally included in the trial but this arm was stopped, as of 17 June 2020, as evidence showed it did not result in the reduction of mortality of hospitalised COVID-19 patients, when compared with standard of care.Over 100 countries have expressed an interest in participating in the trial and WHO is actively supporting more than 60 of them, including with the following:ethical and regulatory approvals of the WHO core protocol;identification of hospitals participating in the trial;training of hospital clinicians on the web-based randomization and data system;shipping the trial drugs as requested by each participating country.As of 3 June 2020, more than 3500 patients have been recruited in 35 countries, with over 400 hospitals actively recruiting patients. Interim trial analyses are monitored by a Global Data and Safety Monitoring Committee, which is an independent group of experts."},{"id":312,"category":"Staying active","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-staying-active","question":"What is physical activity?","response":"&lt;!--\n /* Font Definitions */\n@font-face\n\t{font-family:\"Cambria Math\";\n\tpanose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;\n\tmso-font-charset:1;\n\tmso-generic-font-family:roman;\n\tmso-font-format:other;\n\tmso-font-pitch:variable;\n\tmso-font-signature:0 0 0 0 0 0;}\n@font-face\n\t{font-family:Calibri;\n\tpanose-1:2 15 5 2 2 2 4 3 2 4;\n\tmso-font-charset:0;\n\tmso-generic-font-family:auto;\n\tmso-font-pitch:variable;\n\tmso-font-signature:-536870145 1073786111 1 0 415 0;}\n@font-face\n\t{font-family:\"Arial Unicode MS\";\n\tpanose-1:2 11 6 4 2 2 2 2 2 4;\n\tmso-font-charset:0;\n\tmso-generic-font-family:auto;\n\tmso-font-pitch:variable;\n\tmso-font-signature:-134238209 -371195905 63 0 4129279 0;}\n /* Style Definitions */\np.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal\n\t{mso-style-unhide:no;\n\tmso-style-parent:\"\";\n\tmargin:0cm;\n\tmargin-bottom:.0001pt;\n\tmso-pagination:widow-orphan;\n\tfont-size:12.0pt;\n\tfont-family:\"Times New Roman\";\n\tmso-fareast-font-family:\"Arial Unicode MS\";\n\tborder:none;\n\tmso-fareast-language:EN-US;}\np.Body, li.Body, div.Body\n\t{mso-style-name:Body;\n\tmso-style-unhide:no;\n\tmso-style-parent:\"\";\n\tmargin:0cm;\n\tmargin-bottom:.0001pt;\n\tmso-pagination:widow-orphan;\n\tfont-size:12.0pt;\n\tfont-family:\"Times New Roman\";\n\tmso-fareast-font-family:\"Arial Unicode MS\";\n\tmso-bidi-font-family:\"Arial Unicode MS\";\n\tcolor:black;\n\tborder:none;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-type:none;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-dpiwidth:0pt;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-linecap:flat;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-join:bevel;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-pctmiterlimit:0%;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-dash:solid;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-align:center;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-compound:simple;\n\tmso-ansi-language:FR;\n\tmso-fareast-language:EN-US;\n\ttext-underline:black;}\n.MsoChpDefault\n\t{mso-style-type:export-only;\n\tmso-default-props:yes;\n\tfont-size:10.0pt;\n\tmso-ansi-font-size:10.0pt;\n\tmso-bidi-font-size:10.0pt;\n\tmso-fareast-font-family:\"Arial Unicode MS\";\n\tborder:none;\n\tmso-ansi-language:EN-US;\n\tmso-fareast-language:EN-US;}\n.MsoPapDefault\n\t{mso-style-type:export-only;}\n@page WordSection1\n\t{size:612.0pt 792.0pt;\n\tmargin:70.85pt 70.85pt 70.85pt 70.85pt;\n\tmso-header-margin:36.0pt;\n\tmso-footer-margin:36.0pt;\n\tmso-paper-source:0;}\ndiv.WordSection1\n\t{page:WordSection1;}\n--&gt;\n\n\n\nPhysical activity includes all forms of active\nrecreation, sports participation, cycling and walking, as well as activities\nyou do at work and around the home and garden. It doesn’t have to be exercise\nor sport – play, dance, gardening, and even house cleaning and carrying heavy\nshopping is all part of being physically active.During the COVID-19 pandemic, when so many of us are\nvery restricted in our movements, it is even more important for people of all\nages and abilities to be as active as possible. Even a short break from\nsitting, by doing 3-5 minutes of physical movement, such as walking or\nstretching, will help ease muscle strain, relieve mental tension and improve\nblood circulation and muscle activity. Regular physical activity can also help\nto give the day a routine and be a way of staying in contact with family and\nfriends."},{"id":313,"category":"Staying active","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-staying-active","question":"Why do we need it?","response":"&lt;!--\n /* Font Definitions */\n@font-face\n\t{font-family:\"Cambria Math\";\n\tpanose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;\n\tmso-font-charset:1;\n\tmso-generic-font-family:roman;\n\tmso-font-format:other;\n\tmso-font-pitch:variable;\n\tmso-font-signature:0 0 0 0 0 0;}\n@font-face\n\t{font-family:Calibri;\n\tpanose-1:2 15 5 2 2 2 4 3 2 4;\n\tmso-font-charset:0;\n\tmso-generic-font-family:auto;\n\tmso-font-pitch:variable;\n\tmso-font-signature:-536870145 1073786111 1 0 415 0;}\n@font-face\n\t{font-family:\"Arial Unicode MS\";\n\tpanose-1:2 11 6 4 2 2 2 2 2 4;\n\tmso-font-charset:0;\n\tmso-generic-font-family:auto;\n\tmso-font-pitch:variable;\n\tmso-font-signature:-134238209 -371195905 63 0 4129279 0;}\n /* Style Definitions */\np.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal\n\t{mso-style-unhide:no;\n\tmso-style-parent:\"\";\n\tmargin:0cm;\n\tmargin-bottom:.0001pt;\n\tmso-pagination:widow-orphan;\n\tfont-size:12.0pt;\n\tfont-family:\"Times New Roman\";\n\tmso-fareast-font-family:\"Arial Unicode MS\";\n\tborder:none;\n\tmso-fareast-language:EN-US;}\np.Body, li.Body, div.Body\n\t{mso-style-name:Body;\n\tmso-style-unhide:no;\n\tmso-style-parent:\"\";\n\tmargin:0cm;\n\tmargin-bottom:.0001pt;\n\tmso-pagination:widow-orphan;\n\tfont-size:12.0pt;\n\tfont-family:\"Times New Roman\";\n\tmso-fareast-font-family:\"Arial Unicode MS\";\n\tmso-bidi-font-family:\"Arial Unicode MS\";\n\tcolor:black;\n\tborder:none;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-type:none;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-dpiwidth:0pt;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-linecap:flat;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-join:bevel;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-pctmiterlimit:0%;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-dash:solid;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-align:center;\n\tmso-style-textoutline-outlinestyle-compound:simple;\n\tmso-ansi-language:FR;\n\tmso-fareast-language:EN-US;\n\ttext-underline:black;}\n.MsoChpDefault\n\t{mso-style-type:export-only;\n\tmso-default-props:yes;\n\tfont-size:10.0pt;\n\tmso-ansi-font-size:10.0pt;\n\tmso-bidi-font-size:10.0pt;\n\tmso-fareast-font-family:\"Arial Unicode MS\";\n\tborder:none;\n\tmso-ansi-language:EN-US;\n\tmso-fareast-language:EN-US;}\n.MsoPapDefault\n\t{mso-style-type:export-only;}\n@page WordSection1\n\t{size:612.0pt 792.0pt;\n\tmargin:70.85pt 70.85pt 70.85pt 70.85pt;\n\tmso-header-margin:36.0pt;\n\tmso-footer-margin:36.0pt;\n\tmso-paper-source:0;}\ndiv.WordSection1\n\t{page:WordSection1;}\n--&gt;\n\n\n\nRegular physical activity benefits both the body and\nmind. It can reduce high blood pressure, help manage weight and reduce the risk\nof heart disease, stroke, type 2 diabetes, and various cancers. It also\nimproves bone and muscle strength and increases balance, flexibility and\nfitness. For older people, activities that improve balance help to prevent\nfalls and injuries. For children, regular physical activity helps support\nhealthy growth and development and reduce the risk of disease in later life,\nand through regular activity, children can develop fundamental movement skills\nand build social relationships.Regular physical activity also improves mental health\nand can reduce the risk of depression, cognitive decline and delay the onset of\ndementia - and improve overall feelings of wellbeing."},{"id":314,"category":"Staying active","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-staying-active","question":"How much physical activity is recommended?","response":"WHO has detailed recommendations on the amount of physical activity people of all ages should do to benefit their health and wellbeing. (available here for children under age of 5 and here for youth, adults and olders) Here are the minimum levels we recommend:Infants under the age of 1 year need to be physically active several times a day.\n    Children under 5 years of age should spend at least 180 minutes a day in physical activities, with 3-4 year-olds being moderately or vigorously active for an hour a day.\n    Children and adolescents aged 5-17yearsall children and adolescents should do at least 60 minutes a day of moderate to vigorous-intensity physical activity, including activities that strengthen muscle and bone, at least 3 days per week.Adults aged 18 years and overshould do a total of at least 150 minutes of moderate-intensity physical activity throughout the week, or at least 75 minutes of vigorous-intensity physical activity throughout the week, including muscle-strengthening activities 2 or more days per\n        week.\n    older adults with poor mobility should do physical activity to enhance balance and prevent falls on 3 or more days per week.\n      But any physical activity is better than none.  Start with small amounts and gradually increase duration, frequency and intensity over time. Being active during the COVID-19 pandemic is challenging for us all.  Because the opportunities to be physically active seem to be more restricted, it is even more important to plan in every day the ways to be active and to reduce the time spent\n    sitting for long periods. Put simply, it is a critical time to ensure we all move more and sit less."},{"id":315,"category":"Staying active","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-staying-active","question":"So how do I stay safe while exercising in COVID-19?","response":"Do not exercise if you have a fever, cough and difficulty breathing. Stay home and rest, seek medical attention and call in advance. Follow the directions of your local health authority.If you are able to go for a walk or bicycle ride always practice physical distancing and wash your hands with water and soap before you leave, when you get to where you are going, and as soon as you get home.  If water and soap are not immediately available, use alcohol-based hand rub. If you go to a park or public open space to walk, run or exercise always practice physical distancing and wash your hands with water and soap, before you leave, when you get to where you are going, and as soon as you get home.  If water and soap are not immediately available, use alcohol-based hand rub. Follow the directions of your local health authority in regards to any restrictions on the number of people with you and/or restrictions on the use of public outdoor play or exercise equipment. If you are not regularly active start slowly and with low intensity activities, like walking and low impact exercises. Start with shorter amounts, like 5-10 minutes, and gradually build up to 30 minutes or more continuously over a few weeks. It is better and safer to be active for short periods more frequently than to try and be active for long periods when you are not used to it. Choose the right activity so that you reduce the risk of injury and that you enjoy the activity. Choose the right intensity according to your health status and fitness level. You should be able to breath comfortably and hold a conversation while you do light- and moderate-intensity physical activity."},{"id":316,"category":"Staying active","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-staying-active","question":"How do I stay active in and around the home?","response":"Try and reduce long periods of time spent sitting, whether for work, studying, watching TV, reading, or using social media or playing games using screens. Reduce sitting for long periods by taking short 3-5 minute breaks every 20-30 minutes.\n    Simply stand up and stretch or even better, take a walk around the house, up and down the stairs, or into the garden. By just moving around and stretching you can improve your health and wellbeing. For more ideas and illustrations of healthy stretches\n    see here.Set up a regular routine to be active every day, by planning a physical activity or exercise break either by yourself, by joining an online class, or by setting up a time to be active online with your friends or colleagues. Making a specific\n    time to be active helps ensure you get your daily physical activity. Put the time in your diary, and it will help remind you. Stick with it, as this will help you build a regular routine, and help you adjust to new ways of working, study and family\n    life under COVID-19 restrictionsBe active with your family and friends, connecting with others can help you and your family in the home and elsewhere spend time together and be active. Planning time to be active with your children with\n    active games at home, walks in the parks, or cycling can be a way the whole family can relax, be together and be active and healthy whilst at home.   Set yourself and your family Be Active goals, by choosing a specific type of activity, time of day and/or number of minutes you will do every day. Get each family member to choose their own goal which sets a bit of a challenge but is\n    realistic with help from family or friends and motivation. Record your progress on a weekly activity chart and, if you think it would help, reward yourself with something you value.http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/health-emergencies/coronavirus-covid-19/novel-coronavirus-2019-ncov-technical-guidance/stay-physically-active-during-self-quarantine/_recache?fbclid=IwAR2RQYVYBnmpDCMjBwqmoz0hZxzmit_9yKzXu6ZhjGNywRTEzWOUQefU8V0More physical activity ideas to help you stay activeFor Infants under 1 year of ageSpend regular time doing floor-based play with your baby in a prone position (‘tummy time’) and spread this throughout the day while baby is awake.For Children under 5 years of ageActive play in and around the home – invent games which involve being active and can develop skills in throwing, catching, kicking, as well as developing posture and balance.Active play and games where children get out of breath, such as running around, skipping and jumping.For Children and adolescents aged 5-17 yearsActive games and active play with family.Join in online active games or activity classes, also look for online physical education classes as well as exercise routines suitable for adolescents.Set up playground games indoors such as Jump rope and hop-scotch – make up new games and challenges that involve being active. Learn a new skill – for example try an learn to juggle. Encourage doing some muscle strength training activities such as lifting weights or use improvised weight such as bottles full of water or sand.For Adults Climb up the stairs as much as you can, think of it as an opportunity to be active. Use household chores as a way to be more physical activity. Join in an online exercise class or make up your own routine to music you enjoy that uses the major muscle groups and raises you heart rate. Do some muscle strengthening activities such as lifting weights or improvise using full bottles of water or simply use your own body weight and do sets of press ups, sit ups and squats. Make time for fun, such as dancing to music.Where to get more help and informationFor more ideas use internet search platforms and check out social media for suggestions and access to free resources suitable for children of all ages and adults of all fitness and abilities."},{"id":317,"category":"Staying at hotels and accommodation establishments","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-staying-at-hotels-and-accommodation-establishments","question":"What precautions should everyone take in a hotel or other accommodation establishment?","response":"Everyone should follow basic precautions: Wash all parts of your hands frequently (at least 20 seconds if using an alcohol-based hand rub, and at least 40 seconds with soap and water), including after exchanging objects such as money or credit cards. Look for hand sanitizer stations and use them before going into dining halls, restaurants or bars.Cover a cough or sneeze with a bent elbow or tissue, and throw away the tissue in a closed bin.Maintain at least a 1 metre distance from staff and other guests. This includes avoiding hugging, kissing, or shaking hands. If you can’t guarantee the distance, wear a mask. Be sure to check local and national guidelines on the use of masks."},{"id":318,"category":"Staying at hotels and accommodation establishments","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-staying-at-hotels-and-accommodation-establishments","question":"Are pools and water areas safe to use?","response":"Gym, beach, swimming pool, spa, sauna and steam bath facilities can be used safely with certain restrictions, as determined by national guidelines.  In particular, look for the following measures:a maximum number of people allowed to ensure adequate physical distancing fabric mask policies required by local or national regulations hand washing stations, especially in the toilet and change room areassingle use towels only  a bin for guests to place their towel after use for launderingindividual use drinking watertissues and waste containers with lidshigh touch areas such as door handles disinfected regularly throughout the day"},{"id":319,"category":"Staying at hotels and accommodation establishments","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-staying-at-hotels-and-accommodation-establishments","question":"Are there precautions to take while eating in a restaurant?","response":"There is no evidence that the virus that causes COVID-19 is transmitted by food, including fresh fruits and vegetables. The virus can be killed while cooking food at temperatures of at least 70°C.Food buffets are not recommended because of the risk of close physical contact with others, shared serving implements and multiple people touching the surfaces on the buffet. Indoor dining spaces should have a maximum of 4 people in 10 square metres. The distance from the back of one chair to the back of another chair should be at least 1 metre apart for both indoor and outdoor dining, and guests that face each other should also be at this distance.Guests should be reminded when entering and leaving the area to clean their hands. When the physical distance of at least 1 metre cannot be guaranteed, masks are recommended to be worn by staff and guests. More on masks, including who should wear what kind and when, is available here."},{"id":320,"category":"Staying at hotels and accommodation establishments","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-staying-at-hotels-and-accommodation-establishments","question":"Is it safe to use fans or air conditioning in an accommodation?","response":"Ventilation is an important factor in preventing the virus that causes COVID-19 from spreading. Recirculated air from split air conditioning units, fan coils or any system that runs with a recirculation mode should be avoided where possible, unless in a single occupancy room with no one else present. If recirculation is unavoidable, increase outdoor air exchange by opening windows, if possible and safe to do so, and minimize air blowing from one person directly at another. Floor or ceiling fans can provide ventilation when the people occupying the room are from the same household, but are not recommended when travelers from different households are together."},{"id":321,"category":"Staying at hotels and accommodation establishments","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-staying-at-hotels-and-accommodation-establishments","question":"Can you get the virus from people who were in the room previous to you?","response":"Hotels and other accommodations should have procedures for cleaning, disinfecting and ventilating the room properly between every guest’s stay. These processes allow the accommodations to be used immediately afterward. If these procedures are followed, there is no need to leave the room empty between guests."},{"id":322,"category":"Staying at hotels and accommodation establishments","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-staying-at-hotels-and-accommodation-establishments","question":"What should travelers do if they get sick while at an accommodation facility?","response":"If a guest develops symptoms of COVID-19, such as fever, dry cough or tiredness, they should notify the facility manager and seek medical advice by contacting local health authorities. The guest should isolate from others, including fellow travelers. If the guest cannot be isolated or staff need to enter the room, the ill person should put on a medical mask, and people nearby should also wear a mask.  If the medical mask cannot be tolerated by the ill person, then he or she should cough or sneeze into a bent elbow or use tissues to cover the mouth, and discard the tissue immediately into a closed waste bag."},{"id":323,"category":"Tobacco","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tobacco","question":"As a smoker, is my risk of getting the COVID-19 virus higher than that of a non-smoker?","response":"At the time of preparing this Q&A, there are no peer-reviewed studies that have evaluated the risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection associated with smoking. However, tobacco smokers (cigarettes, waterpipes, bidis, cigars, heated tobacco products) may be more vulnerable to contracting COVID-19, as the act of smoking involves contact of fingers (and possibly contaminated cigarettes) with the lips, which increases the possibility of transmission of viruses from hand to mouth. Smoking waterpipes, also known as shisha or hookah, often involves the sharing of mouth pieces and hoses, which could facilitate the transmission of the COVID-19 virus in communal and social settings."},{"id":324,"category":"Tobacco","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tobacco","question":"As a smoker, am I likely to get more severe symptoms if infected?","response":"Smoking any kind of tobacco reduces lung capacity and increases the risk of many respiratory infections and can increase the severity of respiratory diseases. COVID-19 is an infectious disease that primarily attacks the lungs. Smoking impairs lung function making it harder for the body to fight off coronaviruses and other respiratory diseases.  Available research suggests that smokers are at higher risk of developing severe COVID-19 outcomes and death."},{"id":325,"category":"Tobacco","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tobacco","question":"As a vaper, am I more likely to be infected or to have more severe symptoms if infected?","response":"There is no evidence about the relationship between e-cigarette use and COVID-19. However, existing evidence indicates that electronic nicotine delivery systems (ENDS) and electronic non-nicotine delivery systems (ENNDS), more commonly referred to as e-cigarettes, are harmful and increase the risk of heart disease and lung disorders.  Given that the COVID-19 virus affects the respiratory tract, the hand-to-mouth action of e-cigarette use  may increase the risk of infection."},{"id":326,"category":"Tobacco","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tobacco","question":"What about using smokeless tobacco, like chewing tobacco?","response":"Using smokeless tobacco often involves some hand to mouth contact.  Another risk associated with using smokeless tobacco products, like chewing tobacco, is that the virus can be spread when the user spits out the excess saliva produced during the chewing process."},{"id":327,"category":"Tobacco","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tobacco","question":"What does WHO recommend for tobacco users?","response":"Given the risks to health that tobacco use causes, WHO recommends quitting tobacco use.  Quitting will help your lungs and heart to work better from the moment you stop.  Within 20 minutes of quitting, elevated heart rate and blood pressure drop. After 12 hours, the carbon monoxide level in the bloodstream drops to normal. Within 2-12 weeks, circulation improves and lung function increases. After 1-9 months, coughing and shortness of breath decrease. Quitting will help to protect your loved ones, especially children, from exposure to second-hand smoke. WHO recommends the use of proven interventions such as toll-free quit lines, mobile text-messaging cessation programmes, and nicotine replacement therapies (NRTs), among others, for quitting tobacco use."},{"id":328,"category":"Tobacco","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tobacco","question":"What can I do to protect people from the risks associated with smoking, smokeless tobacco use and vaping?","response":"If you smoke, use e cigarettes or use smokeless tobacco, now is a good time to quit completely.Do not share devices like waterpipes and e-cigarettes.Spread the word about the risks of smoking, using e-cigarettes  and using smokeless tobacco.Protect others from the harms of second-hand smoke.Know the importance of washing your hands, physical distancing, and not sharing any smoking or  e -cigarette products.Do not spit in public places"},{"id":329,"category":"Tobacco","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tobacco","question":"Does nicotine use affect my chances in the context of COVID-19?","response":"There is currently insufficient information to confirm any link between tobacco or nicotine in the prevention or treatment of COVID-19. WHO urges researchers, scientists and the media to be cautious about amplifying unproven claims that tobacco or nicotine could reduce the risk of COVID-19. WHO is constantly evaluating new research, including that which examines the link between tobacco use, nicotine use, and COVID-19."},{"id":330,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"What precautions should I take during travel?","response":"During travel, everyone should clean hands frequently, cough or sneeze into a bent elbow or tissue, and try to maintain a physical distance of at least one metre from others. Travelers should follow the recommendations of the travel authorities regarding policies in the airport and of the airline for the flight."},{"id":331,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"Who should not travel?","response":"People with confirmed diagnoses of COVID-19 cases should be in isolation and not traveling. Anyone who has had contact with someone else confirmed with COVID-19 cases should be in quarantine and not travel. People aged 60 and over, and those with serious chronic illnesses or underlying health conditions should try to postpone travel, or take special precautions and wear a medical face mask continuously throughout the travel. Check the destination country for policies on what kind of tourism travel is allowed."},{"id":332,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"What is meant by “essential travel”?","response":"Essential travel is travel for emergencies and humanitarian actions (including emergency medical flights and medical evacuation). It includes essential personnel (including emergency responders and providers of public health technical support, critical personnel in transport sector such as seafarers and diplomatic officers) and repatriation to a home country."},{"id":333,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"If I feel well but am in the high-risk category, should I travel?","response":"People age 60 and over, and those with serious chronic diseases of underlying health conditions, should postpone or delay travel internationally to and from areas with community transmission, where there are many cases of COVID-19.  This is because people in the high-risk group more frequently get very sick after getting the disease, with some dying of it. If you have to travel in these circumstances, you should wear a medical  mask for more protection against the virus. However, masks do not mean you are fully protected. You should also clean your hands frequently, cough or sneeze into a bent elbow or tissue, and maintain a distance of at least 1 metre from others wherever possible."},{"id":334,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"How can ventilation reduce the risk of contracting COVID-19 in airplanes?","response":"Some airplanes have cabin air filtration systems equipped with HEPA filters which can remove viruses and germs quickly, minimizing the duration of the exposure to any potential infectious materials produced by a cough or sneeze. The cabin air system is designed to operate most efficiently by delivering approximately 50 percent outside air and 50 percent filtered, recirculated air. The air supply is essentially sterile and particle-free.  However, adequate ventilation is just one of the preventive measures to reduce the risk of COVID-19 transmission.  Other important measures include maintaining physical distance of at least 1 meter whenever possible, frequent hand hygiene and wearing a mask. Passengers should check with the airline company and the national or local guidelines about when and where to wear a mask while flying."},{"id":335,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"The travel company is asking me to wear a mask while traveling. Which kind of mask should I use?","response":"You should follow the advice of your travel company. If the type of mask is not specified then people 60 years and over, and those who have underlying health conditions, should wear a medical mask while traveling. This provides greater protection from others who may have the virus.People who feel healthy and have no symptoms can wear a fabric mask to prevent any virus they may have from spreading to others. Remember that wearing a mask does not provide full protection. You should always combine this with frequent hand cleaning, covering a cough or sneeze with a bent elbow or tissue, and maintaining at least a 1 metre distance from others wherever possible.Find out how to choose and wear a mask here."},{"id":336,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"Should I get an immunity certificate before travelling?","response":"The use of “immunity certificates” for international travel in the context of COVID-19 is not currently supported by scientific evidence and therefore not recommended by WHO.\n More evidence is needed to understand the effectiveness of rapid SARS-CoV-2 antibody tests. For more information, please refer to WHO scientific brief “Immunity passports”\n in the context of COVID-19, which will be updated as new evidence becomes available. Beyond\n    the scientific considerations, there are ethical, legal and human rights aspects related to privacy of personal data, medical confidentiality, potential risk of falsification or engagement in risky behaviour, stigma and discrimination."},{"id":337,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"Could I be screened when I exit or arrive at my destination?","response":"Whether screening is conducted depends on the country policies and its risk benefit analysis. Exit and entry screening includes measures like temperature checking and checking for signs and symptoms (fever above 38°C, cough).  You may be asked to complete a form informing health authorities about your possible exposure to cases within the last two weeks (contact with patients among health care workers, visits to hospitals, sharing accommodation with a person sick with COVID-19, etc.). Symptomatic travellers and identified contacts will be asked to have a medical examination and be tested for COVID- 19. You should not be charged for these protective measures, including any required isolation and quarantine."},{"id":338,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"Should I use a digital contact tracing app while traveling?","response":"Digital apps are now available in some countries to identify and inform travellers who may have been in contact with a person confirmed to have COVID-19 or had a positive test for COVID-19. They are effective only if a large proportion of the general population uses the app.  International travellers may have issues of compatibility and data sharing when crossing borders. Those considering an app are advised to review the legal and ethical aspects related to individual privacy and personal data protection."},{"id":339,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"Should I get a test before departure or upon arrival?","response":"Laboratory PCR testing (molecular testing for SARS-CoV-2) immediately prior to departure or on arrival may provide information about the status of travellers. However, laboratory results should be interpreted with caution, since a small proportion of false negative and false positive results may occur. If conducted, testing should be accompanied by a comprehensive COVID-19 follow up, for example, by advising departing travellers who have been tested to report any symptoms to local public health authorities. If the testing is conducted on arrival, all travellers should be provided with an emergency phone number in case symptoms develop. A relevant case management protocol should be followed in case of a positive test."},{"id":340,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"What happens if I have symptoms when arriving at my destination?","response":"If you have any symptoms or have had contact with people who have COVID-19, you may be asked to get an exam and be tested for COVID-19. Even if you don’t test positive, you should be provided with an emergency phone number to call in case symptoms develop later.  You should not be charged by the country for:examinations to determine your health statusrequired vaccinations or protective equipment on arrival (if these were not published at least 10 days earlier)appropriate isolation or quarantine facilitiesrequired certificates at the point of entry that document measures applied any baggage accompanying you"},{"id":341,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"What should I do after arriving at my destination?","response":"Travellers should self-monitor for any symptoms for 14 days after arrival. Report any symptoms and your travel history to local health facilities and follow national protocols. If you are confirmed to have COVID-19, you will be placed in isolation in a health facility or in self-isolation at home, depending on the country’s policies, and asked to provide a list of your contacts in the last 14 days. Your contacts will be placed under quarantine."},{"id":342,"category":"Travel advice for the general public","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-travel-advice-for-the-general-public","question":"What should I do if I get sick while traveling?","response":"If you become ill during your travel, inform your travel attendant (plane, ship, train, etc.). You may be moved to a seat farther away from others. Ask for information on how to be seen by a health care provider and seek care immediately. Wear a mask continuously while you travel, frequently clean your hands with hand sanitizer, cover a cough or sneeze with a bent elbow or tissue, and maintain at least a 1 metre distance from others wherever possible. You should stop travelling as soon as feasible.If you are told you must quarantine or self-isolate yourself in a specific place, you should be provided with free, appropriate facilities and care, and not be asked to stay longer than 14 days."},{"id":343,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"Are people with tuberculosis likely to be at increased risk of COVID-19 infection, illness and death?","response":"While experience on COVID-19 infection in tuberculosis (TB) patients remains limited, it is anticipated that people ill with both TB and COVID-19 may have poorer treatment outcomes, especially if TB treatment is interrupted. Older age, diabetes and chronic      obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) are linked with more severe COVID-19 and are      also risk factors for poor outcomes in TB.TB patients should take precautions as advised by health authorities to be protected from COVID-19 and continue their TB treatment as prescribed.People ill with COVID-19 and TB show similar symptoms such as cough, fever and\ndifficulty breathing. Both diseases attack primarily the lungs and although both\nbiological agents transmit mainly via close contact, the incubation period from\nexposure to disease in TB is longer, often with a slow onset."},{"id":344,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"Do COVID-19 and tuberculosis spread in the same way?","response":"While both tuberculosis (TB) and COVID-19 spread by close contact between people the exact mode of transmission differs, explaining some differences in infection control measures to mitigate the two conditions.  TB bacilli remain suspended in the air in droplet nuclei for several hours after a TB patient coughs, sneezes, shouts, or sings, and people who inhale them can get infected. The size of these droplet nuclei is a key factor determining their infectiousness. Their concentration decreases with ventilation and exposure to direct sunlight.  COVID-19 transmission has primarily been attributed to the direct breathing of droplets expelled by someone with COVID-19 (people may be infectious before clinical features become apparent). Droplets produced by coughing, sneezing, exhaling and speaking may land on objects and surfaces, and contacts can get infected with COVID-19 by touching them and then touching their eyes, nose or mouth . Handwashing, in addition to respiratory precautions, are thus important in the control of COVID-19."},{"id":345,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"What is the potential impact of COVID-19 pandemic on essential tuberculosis services?","response":"Modelling work suggests that if the COVID-19 pandemic led to a global reduction of 25% in expected TB detection for 3 months – a realistic possibility given the levels of disruption in TB services being observed in multiple countries – then we could expect a 13% increase in TB deaths, bringing us back to the levels of TB mortality that we had 5 years ago. This may even be a conservative estimate as it does not factor in other possible impacts of the pandemic on TB transmission, treatment interruptions and poorer outcomes in people with TB and COVID-19 infection (Predicted impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on global tuberculosis deaths in 2020, P. Glaziou). Between 2020 and 2025 an additional 1.4 million TB deaths could be registered as a direct consequence of the COVID-19 pandemic (Stop TB Partnership analysis).All measures should be taken to ensure continuity of services for people who need preventive and curative treatment for tuberculosis (TB)."},{"id":346,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"What should health authorities do to provide sustainability of essential tuberculosis services during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"People-centred delivery of tuberculosis (TB) prevention, diagnosis, treatment and care services should be ensured in tandem with the COVID-19 response.Prevention: Measures must be implemented to limit transmission of TB and COVID-19 in congregate settings and health care facilities. Administrative, environmental and personal protection measures apply to both (e.g. basic infection prevention and control, cough etiquette, patient triage). Provision of TB preventive treatment should be maintained as much as possible.Diagnosis: Tests for TB and COVID-9 are different and both should be made available for individuals with respiratory symptoms, which may be similar for the two diseases. Treatment and care: People-centred outpatient and community-based care should be strongly preferred over hospital treatment for TB patients (unless serious conditions require hospitalization) to reduce opportunities for transmission. Anti-TB treatment, in line with the latest WHO guidelines, must be provided for all TB patients, including those in quarantine and those with confirmed COVID-19 disease. Adequate stocks of TB medicines should be provided to all patients to reduce trips to collect medicines.Use of digital health technologies for patients and programmes should be intensified. In line with WHO recommendations, technologies like electronic medication monitors and video-supported therapy can help patients complete their TB treatment."},{"id":347,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"How can health authorities ensure supplies of tuberculosis medicines and diagnostics?","response":"Appropriate planning and monitoring are essential to ensure that procurement and supply of tuberculosis (TB) medicines and diagnostics are not interrupted. WHO is monitoring medicine supply at the global level, while The Global Fund, the Stop TB Partnership Global Drug Facility (GDF), USAID, Unitaid and other donors play an essential role in supporting countries to secure adequate and sustainable supplies of TB medicines, drugs and diagnostics. Countries are advised to place their orders for 2020 delivery as soon as possible given anticipated delays in transport and delivery mechanisms."},{"id":348,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"What services can be leveraged across both diseases?","response":"The response to COVID-19 can benefit from the capacity building efforts developed for tuberculosis (TB) over many years of investment by national authorities and donors. These include infection prevention and control, contact tracing, household and community-based care, and surveillance and monitoring systems.Although modes of transmission of the two diseases are slightly different, administrative, environmental and personal protection measures apply to both (e.g. basic infection prevention and control, cough etiquette, patient triage). TB laboratory networks have been established in countries with the support of WHO and international partners. These networks as well as specimen transportation mechanisms could also be used for COVID-19 diagnosis and surveillance.Respiratory physicians, pulmonology staff of all grades, TB specialists and health workers at the primary health care level may be points of reference for patients with pulmonary complications of COVID-19. They should familiarize themselves with the most current WHO recommendations for the supportive treatment and containment of COVID-19. TB programme staff with their experience and capacity, including in active case finding and contact tracing, are well placed to support the COVID-19 response.Various digital technologies used in TB programmes can      support the COVID-19 response, including adherence support, electronic      medical records and eLearning."},{"id":349,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"What measures should be in place to protect staff working in tuberculosis laboratories and healthcare facilities, and community health workers, from COVID-19 infection?","response":"Health care facilities, including those that diagnose and care for tuberculosis (TB) and lung diseases, are bound to receive patients with COVID-19, many of whom may be undiagnosed. Additional measures may be needed to avoid that staff in these centres are exposed to\n    COVID-19 infection.The Information Note includes additional, temporary measures that should be considered. These include alternative arrangements to reduce visits for TB follow-up, precautions for sputum collection, transportation and testing. The note also includes a description of ethical obligations in this setting.Existing WHO recommendations for infection prevention and control for TB and for COVID-19 should be strictly implemented, including personal protection equipment. Lessons learnt over many years of TB infection prevention and control, contact tracing, investigation\n    and management can benefit efforts to stop the spread of COVID-19."},{"id":350,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"How can we protect people seeking tuberculosis care during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"In a context of widespread restriction of movement of the population in response to the pandemic and isolation of COVID-19 patients, communication with the healthcare services should be maintained so that people with tuberculosis (TB), especially those most vulnerable, get essential services. This includes management of adverse drug reactions and co-morbidities, nutritional and mental health support, and restocking of the supplies of medicines. Enough TB medicines will need to be dispensed to the patient or caregiver to last until the next visit. This will limit interruption or unnecessary visits to the clinic. Mechanisms to deliver medicines at home and even to collect specimens for follow-up testing may become expedient. Home-based TB treatment is bound to become more common. Alternative arrangements to reduce clinic visits may involve limiting appointments to specific times to avoid exposure to other clinic attendees; using digital technologies to maintain treatment support. Community health workers become more critical as treatment is more decentralized.More TB patients will probably start their treatment at home and therefore limiting the risk of household transmission of TB during the first few weeks is important. Vulnerable populations who have poor access to healthcare should not get further marginalized during the pandemic."},{"id":351,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"Can tuberculosis and COVID-19 be tested on the same type of specimen?","response":"The diagnostic methods for tuberculosis (TB) and COVID-19 are quite distinct and commonly require different specimens.  Sputum, as well as many other biological specimens, can be used to diagnose TB using culture or molecular techniques.Tests for COVID-19 are done most commonly by nasopharyngeal or oropharyngeal swab or wash in ambulatory patients, but sputum or endotracheal aspirate or bronchoalveolar lavage may be used in patients with severe respiratory disease.  Molecular testing is the currently recommended method for the identification of infectious COVID-19 and just as for TB, serological assays are not recommended for the routine diagnosis of COVID-19.The pipeline for COVID-19 diagnostics has flourished impressively within a few months. Amongst these is the Xpert® Xpress SARS-CoV-2 cartridge for use on GeneXpert machines, which are machines used in TB diagnosis. WHO is currently evaluating this cartridge as well as other tests. Additional resources to roll out COVID-19 testing should be mobilized rather than relying only on existing resources that are used for TB, to ensure that the diagnostic coverage for TB is maintained as necessary."},{"id":352,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"Should all people being evaluated for tuberculosis also be tested for COVID-19 and vice-versa?","response":"Testing of the same patient for both tuberculosis (TB) and COVID-19 would generally be indicated for three main reasons, subject to the specific setting in each country:clinical features that are common to both diseases; or simultaneous exposure to both diseases; orpresence of a risk factor As the pandemic advances, more people of all ages, including TB patients, will be exposed to COVID-19. The Information Note contains further considerations for simultaneous testing for the two diseases."},{"id":353,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"Is tuberculosis treatment different in people who have both TB and COVID-19?","response":"In most cases tuberculosis (TB) treatment is not different in people with or without COVID-19 infection. Experience on joint management of both COVID-19 infection and TB remains limited. However, suspension of TB treatment in COVID-19 patients should be exceptional. TB preventive treatment, treatment for drug-susceptible or drug-resistant TB disease should continue uninterrupted to safeguard the patient’s health, reduce transmission and prevent the development of drug-resistance. While treatment trials are ongoing, no medication is currently recommended for COVID-19 and therefore no cautions on drug-drug interactions are indicated at present. TB patients on treatment should nonetheless be asked if they are taking any medicines, including traditional cures, that may interact with their medication.Effective treatments to prevent TB and to treat active TB have been scaled up and are in use worldwide. The risk of death in TB patients approaches 50% if left untreated and may be higher in the elderly or in the presence of comorbidity. It is critical that TB services are not disrupted during the COVID-19 response.  Gathering evidence as this pandemic unfolds will be very important, while upholding the norms of professional conduct and patient confidentiality when handling clinical details."},{"id":354,"category":"Tuberculosis","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-tuberculosis","question":"Does the BCG vaccine protect people from COVID-19?","response":"There is no evidence at this point that the Bacille Calmette-Guérin vaccine (BCG) protects people against infection with COVID-19 virus. Clinical trials addressing this question are underway, and WHO will evaluate the evidence when it is available. In the absence of evidence, WHO does not recommend BCG vaccination for the prevention of COVID-19. WHO continues to recommend reserving BCG for neonatal vaccination in settings with a high risk of tuberculosis.More information"},{"id":355,"category":"Vaccine access and allocation","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccine-access-and-allocation","question":"As safe and effective vaccines for COVID-19 are approved, who should be the first to receive them?","response":"WHO believes that everyone, everywhere who could benefit from safe and effective COVID-19 vaccines should have access as quickly as possible, starting with those at highest risk of serious disease or death. WHO’s Strategic Advisory Group of Experts on Immunization (SAGE) has released two key documents to help guide the allocation and prioritization of populations to receive COVID-19 vaccines:The Values Framework for the allocation and prioritization of COVID-19 vaccination, which offers high-level guidance globally on the values and ethical considerations regarding allocation of COVID-19 vaccines between countries, and offers guidance nationally on the prioritization of groups for vaccination within countries while supply is limited.  The Roadmap for Prioritizing Population Groups for Vaccines against COVID-19, which recommends public health strategies and target priority groups for different levels of vaccine availability and epidemiologic settings.  Examples of target priority groups include frontline health and care workers at high risk of infection, older adults, and those people at high risk of death because of underlying conditions like heart disease and diabetes. In addition, WHO led the development of a Fair Allocation Framework that aims to ensure that successful COVID-19 vaccines and treatments are shared equitably across all countries. This framework a key part of the Access to COVID-19 Tools (ACT) Accelerator, a global collaboration to accelerate development, production, and equitable access to COVID-19 tests, treatments, and vaccines. The framework advises that as safe and effective COVID-19 vaccines are authorized for use, all countries should receive doses in proportion to their population size to immunize the highest-priority groups. In the second phase, vaccines would continue to be deployed to all countries so that additional populations can be covered according to national priorities."},{"id":356,"category":"Vaccine access and allocation","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccine-access-and-allocation","question":"What is WHO doing to ensure that COVID-19 vaccines will be allocated fairly?","response":"WHO is one of the leaders of a global alliance known as COVAX, the vaccine pillar of the ACT-Accelerator collaboration, which is working to accelerate the development and manufacturing of COVID-19 vaccines and ensure that there is fair and equitable access to these vaccines for all countries.COVAX will allocate vaccines across countries according to a framework developed by a group that includes ethicists, scientists, and other health experts and vetted by WHO’s Member States. Under this framework, COVID-19 vaccines will be rolled out in two phases. In the first phase, they will be allocated according to population size to all participating countries at the same time, so as to protect those people at greatest risk of infection and of severe disease.WHO’s Strategic Advisory Group of Experts (SAGE) has provided recommendations about which populations should be prioritized first. These include frontline health and care workers at high risk of infection, older adults, and those people at high risk of death because of underlying conditions like heart disease and diabetes. In the second phase of the roll-out, as more doses are produced, vaccines can go to groups less at risk of being infected or of suffering badly.COVAX aims to provide at least 2 billion vaccine doses by the end of 2021. The Facility has achieved that goal and additionally has the possibility to increase those doses by another 1 billion as right of first refusal for several candidates in clinical trials supported by CEPI. Although these doses are not enough for everyone in all countries, it may be enough to end the acute stage of the crisis and put the world on the road to ending the pandemic."},{"id":357,"category":"Vaccine access and allocation","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccine-access-and-allocation","question":"How is WHO helping countries prepare for COVID-19 vaccines?","response":"Along with accelerating COVID-19 vaccine research and helping scale up manufacturing capacity, WHO is working in close partnership with countries, regional colleagues, and other partners to develop needed policies, strengthen regulatory capacity, training courses, and guide countries in all the needed preparations for a programme to deliver COVID-19 vaccines. WHO, UNICEF, and partners are supporting countries in preparing for COVID-19 vaccine introduction. The Country Readiness and Delivery workstream – which is part of the ACT Accelerator – has developed a toolbox with guidance, tools, and trainings.For example, WHO’s Strategic Advisory Group of Experts (SAGE) has issued interim policy recommendations for the rollout of the first COVID-19 vaccine approved for emergency use, the Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 vaccine. These recommendations can guide and support country decision-making bodies, such as the National Immunization Technical Advisory Groups, on the optimal use of existing COVID-19 vaccines. SAGE is expected to review other vaccines in the coming months.WHO has also developed detailed technical guidance and adaptable planning tools and templates to help countries plan for COVID-19 vaccines considering the many aspects of readiness that need to be put in place. These areas include planning and implementation, data and monitoring, supply and logistics, and acceptance and demand. To support initial preparations, a vaccine introduction readiness assessment tool (VIRAT) has been developed and disseminated. It provides countries with an integrated roadmap of milestones and a framework for self-monitoring progress in preparing for vaccine introduction. This will help ensure that COVID-19 vaccines reach those in need as soon as they are available.WHO advises every country to develop a National Deployment and Vaccination Plan (NDVP) for COVID-19 vaccines.  Having one plan in each country, that comprehensively describes all elements of the country’s approach to COVID-19 vaccine rollout will be crucial for a coordinated effort. Guidance on developing that plan is available from WHO, including all elements that a country needs to consider."},{"id":358,"category":"Vaccine research and development","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccine-research-and-development","question":"How is the research and development process being accelerated without compromising safety?","response":"WHO and its partners are committed to accelerating the development of COVID-19 vaccines while maintaining the highest standards on safety.In the past, vaccines have been developed through a series of steps that can take many years. Now, given the urgent need for COVID-19 vaccines, unprecedented financial investments and scientific collaborations are changing how vaccines are developed. This means that some of the steps in the research and development process have been happening in parallel, while still maintaining strict clinical and safety standards. For example, some clinical trials are evaluating multiple vaccines at the same time. However, this does not make the studies any less rigorous.More information about COVID-19 vaccine development is available here."},{"id":359,"category":"Vaccine research and development","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccine-research-and-development","question":"What are human challenge studies? What is WHO’s view on these studies?","response":"In a regular vaccine study, one group of volunteers at risk for a disease is given an experimental vaccine, and another group is not; researchers monitor both groups over time and compare outcomes to see if the vaccine is safe and effective.In a human challenge vaccine study, healthy volunteers are given an experimental vaccine, and then deliberately exposed to the organism causing the disease to see if the vaccine works. Some scientists believe that this approach could accelerate COVID-19 vaccine development, in part because it would require far fewer volunteers than a typical study. However, there are important ethical considerations that must be addressed – particularly for a new disease like COVID-19, which we do not yet fully understand and are still learning how to treat; it may be difficult for the medical community and potential volunteers to properly estimate the potential risks of participating in a COVID-19 human challenge study. For more information, see this WHO publication on the ethics of COVID-19 human challenge studies."},{"id":360,"category":"Vaccine research and development","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccine-research-and-development","question":"Who should participate in clinical trials for COVID-19 vaccines?","response":"Small (phase I) safety studies of COVID-19 vaccines should enroll healthy adult volunteers. Larger (phase II and III) studies should include volunteers that reflect the populations for whom the vaccines are intended. This means enrolling people from diverse geographic areas, racial and ethnic backgrounds, genders, and ages, as well as those with underlying health conditions that put them at higher risk for COVID-19. Including these groups in clinical trials is the only way to make sure that a vaccine will be safe and effective for everyone who needs it."},{"id":361,"category":"Vaccine research and development","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccine-research-and-development","question":"How do I volunteer for a COVID-19 vaccine trial?","response":"Opportunities to volunteer for a COVID-19 vaccine trial vary from country to country. If you are interested in volunteering, check with local health officials or research institutions."},{"id":362,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Is there a vaccine for COVID-19?","response":"Yes there are now several vaccines that are in use. The first mass vaccination programme started in early December 2020 and the number of vaccination doses administered is updated on a daily basis here. At least 13 different vaccines (across 4 platforms) have been administered.The Pfizer/BioNtech Comirnaty vaccine was listed for WHO Emergency Use Listing (EUL) on 31 December 2020. The SII/Covishield and AstraZeneca/AZD1222 vaccines (developed by AstraZeneca/Oxford and manufactured by the State Institute of India and SK Bio respectively) were given EUL on 16 February. The Janssen/Ad26.COV 2.S developed by Johnson & Johnson, was listed for EUL on 12 March 2021. The Moderna COVID-19 vaccine (mRNA 1273) was listed for EUL on 30 April 2021 and the Sinopharm COVID-19 vaccine was listed for EUL on 7 May 2021. The Sinopharm vaccine is produced by Beijing Bio-Institute of Biological Products Co Ltd, subsidiary of China National Biotec Group (CNBG). The Sinovac-CoronaVac was listed for EUL on 1 June 2021.For further information, see here.WHO is on track to EUL other vaccine products through June. The products and progress in regulatory review by WHO is provided by WHO and updated regularly. The document is provided here.Once vaccines are demonstrated to be safe and efficacious, they must be authorized by national regulators, manufactured to exacting standards, and distributed. WHO is working with partners around the world to help coordinate key steps in this process, including to facilitate equitable access to safe and effective COVID-19 vaccines for the billions of people who will need them. More information about COVID-19 vaccine development is available  here."},{"id":363,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"When will COVID-19 vaccines be ready for distribution?","response":"The first COVID-19 vaccines have already begun to be introduced in countries. Before COVID-19 vaccines can be delivered:The vaccines must be proven safe and effective in large (phase III) clinical trials.  Some COVID-19 vaccine candidates have completed their phase III trials, and many other potential vaccines are being developed.Independent reviews of the efficacy and safety evidence is required for each vaccine candidate, including regulatory review and approval in the country where the vaccine is manufactured, before WHO considers a vaccine candidate for prequalification.\r\n        Part of this process also involves the Global Advisory Committee on Vaccine Safety.In addition to review of the data for regulatory purposes, the evidence must also be reviewed for the purpose of policy recommendations on how the vaccines should be used.An external panel of experts convened\r\n by WHO, called the Strategic Advisory Group of Experts on Immunization (SAGE), analyzes the results from clinical trials, along with evidence on the disease, age groups affected, risk factors for disease, programmatic use, and other information.\r\n        SAGE then recommends whether and how the vaccines should be used.Officials in individual countries decide whether to approve the vaccines for national use and develop policies for how to use the vaccines in their country based on the WHO recommendations.The vaccines must be manufactured in large quantities, which is a major and unprecedented challenge – all the while continuing to produce all the other important life-saving vaccines already in use.As a final step, all approved vaccines will require distribution through a complex logistical process, with rigorous stock management and temperature control.WHO is working with partners around the world to accelerate every step of this process, while also ensuring the highest safety standards are met. More information is available here."},{"id":364,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Will COVID-19 vaccines provide long-term protection?","response":"Because COVID vaccines have only been developed in the past months, it’s too early to know the duration of protection of COVID-19 vaccines. Research is ongoing to answer this question. However, it’s encouraging that available data suggest that most people who recover from COVID-19 develop an immune response that provides at least some period of protection against reinfection – although we’re still learning how strong this protection is, and how long it lasts."},{"id":365,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"How quickly could COVID-19 vaccines stop the pandemic?","response":"The impact of COVID-19 vaccines on the pandemic will depend on several factors. These include the effectiveness of the vaccines; how quickly they are approved, manufactured, and delivered; the possible development of other variants and how many people get vaccinated\nWhilst trials have shown several COVID-19 vaccines to have high levels of efficacy, like all other vaccines, COVID-19 vaccines will not be 100% effective. WHO is working to help ensure that approved vaccines are as effective as possible, so they can have the greatest impact on the pandemic."},{"id":366,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"What types of COVID-19 vaccines are being developed? How would they work?","response":"Scientists around the world are developing many potential vaccines for COVID-19. These vaccines are all designed to teach the body’s immune system to safely recognize and block the virus that causes COVID-19.Several different types of potential vaccines for COVID-19 are in development, including:Inactivated or weakened virus vaccines, which use a form of the virus that has been inactivated or weakened so it doesn’t cause disease, but still generates an immune response.Protein-based vaccines, which use harmless fragments of proteins or protein shells that mimic the COVID-19 virus to safely generate an immune response.Viral vector vaccines, which use a safe virus that cannot cause disease but serves as a platform to produce coronavirus proteins to generate an immune response.RNA and DNA vaccines, a cutting-edge approach that uses genetically engineered RNA or DNA to generate a protein that itself safely prompts an immune response.For more information about all COVID-19 vaccines in development, see this WHO publication, which is being updated regularly."},{"id":367,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Will other vaccines help protect me from COVID-19?","response":"Currently, there is no evidence that any other vaccines, apart from those specifically designed for the SARS-Cov-2 virus,  will protect against COVID-19.However, scientists are studying whether some existing vaccines – such as the Bacille Calmette-Guérin (BCG) vaccine, which is used to prevent tuberculosis – are also effective for COVID-19. WHO will evaluate evidence from these studies when available."},{"id":368,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"What are the benefits of getting vaccinated?","response":"The COVID-19 vaccines produce protection against the disease, as a result of developing an immune response to the SARS-Cov-2 virus.  Developing immunity through vaccination means there is a reduced risk of developing the  illness and its consequences.\r\n    This immunity helps you fight the virus if exposed. Getting vaccinated may also protect people around you, because if you are protected from getting infected and from disease, you are less likely to infect someone else. This is particularly important\r\n    to protect people at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19, such as healthcare providers, older or elderly adults, and people with other medical conditions."},{"id":369,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Who should get the COVID-19 vaccines?","response":"The COVID-19 vaccines are safe for most people 18 years and older, including those with pre-existing conditions of any kind, including auto-immune disorders. These conditions include: hypertension, diabetes, asthma, pulmonary, liver and kidney disease, as well as chronic infections that are stable and controlled. If supplies are limited in your area, discuss your situation with your care provider if you:Have a compromised immune systemAre pregnant or nursing your babyHave a history of severe allergies, particularly to a vaccine (or any of the ingredients in the vaccine)Are severely frail"},{"id":370,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Can we stop taking precautions after being vaccinated?","response":"Vaccination protects you from getting seriously ill and dying\r\nfrom COVID-19. For the first fourteen days after getting a vaccination, you do\r\nnot have significant levels of protection, then it increases gradually. For a\r\nsingle dose vaccine, immunity will generally occur two weeks after vaccination.\r\nFor two-dose vaccines, both doses are needed to achieve the highest level of\r\nimmunity possible. While a COVID-19 vaccine will protect you from serious illness\r\nand death, we are still learning about the extent to which it keeps you from\r\nbeing infected and passing the virus on to others (transmission). The data that\r\nis emerging from countries is showing that the vaccines that are currently in\r\nuse are protecting against severe disease and hospitalization. However, no\r\nvaccine is 100% effective and breakthrough infections are regrettable, but to\r\nbe expected. The current evidence shows that vaccines provide some protection\r\nfrom infection and transmission, but that protection is less than that for\r\nserious illness and death. We are still learning also about the variants of\r\nconcern and whether the vaccines are as protective against these strains as the\r\nnon-variant virus.  For these reasons,\r\nand while many of those in the community may not yet be vaccinated, maintaining\r\nother prevention measures is important especially in communities where SARS\r\nCoV-2 circulation is significant. To help keep you and others safe, and while efforts\r\ncontinue to reduce viral transmission and ramp up vaccine coverage, you should continue\r\nto maintain at least a 1-metre distance from others, cover a cough or sneeze in\r\nyour elbow, clean your hands frequently and wear a mask, particularly in\r\nenclosed, crowded or poorly ventilated spaces. Always follow guidance from\r\nlocal authorities based on the situation and risk where you live."},{"id":371,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Can I have the second dose with a different vaccine than the first dose?","response":"Clinical trials in some countries are looking at whether you can have a first dose from one vaccine and a second dose from a different vaccine. There isn't enough data yet to recommend this type of combination."},{"id":372,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Can the COVID-19 vaccine cause a positive test result for the disease, such as for a PCR or antigen test?","response":"No, the COVID-19 vaccine will not cause a positive test result for a COVID-19 PCR or antigen laboratory test. This is because the tests check for active disease and not whether an individual is immune or not. However, because the COVID-19 vaccine prompts an immune response, it may be possible to test positive in an antibody (serology) test that measures COVID-19 immunity in an individual."},{"id":373,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Should I be vaccinated if I have had COVID-19?","response":"Even if you have already had COVID-19, you should be vaccinated when it is offered to you. The protection that someone gains from having COVID-19 will vary from person to person, and we also don’t know how long natural immunity might last."},{"id":374,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Is the vaccine safe for children?","response":"Vaccines are usually tested in adults first, and only then\r\nassessed in children to because they are still developing and growing. COVID-19\r\nhas also been a more serious and dangerous disease among older populations. Now\r\nthat the vaccines have been determined to be safe for adults, they are being\r\nstudied in children. Recently, Pfizer released safety data about the use of their COVID-19\r\nvaccine in adolescents. The phase 3 trial in participants aged 12 to 15 years\r\ndemonstrated a robust antibody response and 100% efficacy in preventing\r\nCOVID-19 disease. Following this announcement, the European Medicines Agency, Health Canada\r\nand the US Food and Drug Administration authorised the use of the Pfizer\r\nvaccine for use in 12-15 year olds and other countries are expected to follow.WHO will review these and any other data and provide\r\nrecommendations. Vaccinations for children are likely to be discussed in\r\nfuture by WHO’s Strategic Advisory Group of Experts (SAGE). This has\r\nbeen done for Pfizer and SAGE is updating its prioritization roadmap based on\r\nall of the evidence currently available. While the supply of vaccines is\r\nlimited, priorities will remain on those most at risk of serious illness who\r\nuntil now have not been vaccinated in many countries around the world: the\r\nelderly, those with chronic health conditions and health workers. Children are at low risk of serious disease and vaccinating them\r\nis primarily about reducing transmission which is also contributed to by the\r\nnonpharmaceutical interventions that include physically distancing from others,\r\ncleaning hands frequently, sneezing and coughing  into their elbow, wearing a mask if age\r\nappropriate and avoiding crowded, poorly ventilated spaces."},{"id":375,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Do the vaccines protect against variants?","response":"More studies are needed to assess the effectiveness of the\r\ncurrent COVID vaccines against the variants. A growing body of data suggests\r\nthat most vaccines stimulate enough immunity to retain substantial efficacy\r\nagainst most variants, especially for severe disease, hospitalization, and\r\ndeath. The impact of the variants on efficacy against mild disease and against\r\ninfection without disease is more impacted than for the more severe outcomes. The reason vaccines substantially retain protection against\r\ndisease is likely related to the broad immune response they induce, which means\r\nthat virus changes or mutations are unlikely to make vaccines completely\r\nineffective. If any of these vaccines become less effective against one or more\r\nvariants, it will likely be possible to change the composition of the vaccines\r\nto protect against these variants, however this will take time and additional\r\ndata to fully evaluate. Data continues to be collected and analysed on new\r\nvariants of the COVID-19 virus. WHO will update its guidance when more\r\ndetails are known about the impact of specific variants on specific\r\nvaccines.  WHO’s SAGE is reviewing this\r\nevidence on a regular basis. While we are learning more, we need to do everything possible to\r\nstop the spread of the virus in order to prevent mutations that may reduce the performance\r\nof existing vaccines. This means staying at least 1 metre away from others,\r\ncovering a cough or sneezing in your elbow, frequently cleaning your hands,\r\nwearing a mask and avoiding crowded, poorly ventilated rooms or opening a\r\nwindow."},{"id":376,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Does the vaccine cause different side effects in men and women? Does age have an impact?","response":"The effect of the COVID-19 vaccine varies from person to person,\r\nlike it does for most vaccines. As more people get vaccinated, we may be able\r\nto determine patterns. This information continues to be collected and will be\r\nshared, but for now, we cannot anticipate who may have side effects."},{"id":377,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Does having side effects mean that the vaccine is working? What does having no side effects mean?","response":"The vaccine stimulates your immune system to protect you from\r\nthe virus. This process can sometimes cause side effects like fever, chills or\r\nheadache, but not everyone experiences this. The presence or magnitude of the\r\nreaction you may have vaccination does not predict or reflect your immune\r\nresponse to the vaccine. You do not have to have side effects in order to be\r\nprotected."},{"id":378,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines","question":"Should we eat or drink differently the day or two after getting vaccinated?","response":"The\r\neffectiveness of the vaccine is not dependent on any food or drink before or\r\nafter taking the vaccine."},{"id":379,"category":"Vaccines and people living with HIV","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-and-people-living-with-hiv","question":"How does WHO support to access COVID-19 vaccines?","response":"There are currently more than 70 COVID-19 vaccine candidates in various stages of clinical trials. Several have already been approved by national regulatory bodies and are being provided in countries.  WHO is compiling the COVID-19 vaccine landscape and tracker database with detailed information on vaccine candidates in both clinical and pre-clinical development1. WHO also has an ongoing prequalification process for these vaccines; information on all COVID-19 vaccines submitted for WHO prequalification, and guidance on their use, is provided and regularly updated2. WHO is working in collaboration with scientists, global health organizations and manufacturers, through the Access to COVID-19 Tools (ACT) Accelerator3, to speed up the pandemic response. COVID-19 vaccines will only be distributed by the COVAX Facility if they have WHO emergency use listing (EUL), prequalification (PQ) or stringent regulatory authorization (SRA). Both UNICEF and PAHO Revolving Fund will also require such authorizations. For vaccines which are found to be safe and effective, the COVID-19 Vaccines Global Access (COVAX) Facility4 led by WHO, GAVI and CEPI, aims to facilitate the equitable access and distribution of these vaccines to protect people in all countries. People at greatest risk of progression to severe disease will be prioritized. Authorized COVID-19 vaccines significantly reduce the risk of severe disease and death. However, it is not currently known to what extent people who have received a COVID-19 vaccine can pass the virus on to others after vaccination. Therefore, once vaccinated, all people should continue to take preventive measures against COVID-19, such as physical distancing, wearing a mask, keeping rooms well ventilated, avoiding crowds, cleaning hands, and coughing into a bent elbow or tissue5.1 https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/draft-landscape-of-covid-19-candidate-vaccines2 https://extranet.who.int/pqweb/sites/default/files/documents/Status_COVID_VAX_20Jan2021_v2.pdf3 https://www.who.int/initiatives/act-accelerator4 https://www.gavi.org/covax-facility5 https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public/when-and-how-to-use-masks"},{"id":380,"category":"Vaccines and people living with HIV","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-and-people-living-with-hiv","question":"Are COVID-19 vaccines safe for people living with HIV?","response":"Many of the most advanced vaccines have included a small number of people living with HIV. Despite limited data, available information suggests COVID-19 vaccines for which WHO has issued recommendations, are safe for people living with HIV. The vaccines often include genetic material from SARS-CoV-2, but do not contain the whole virus, so the virus cannot replicate. As they are not live vaccines, they are not expected to be less safe in people who are immunocompromised.  No pharmacological interactions have been reported between COVID-19 vaccines and antiretroviral drugs; people living with HIV should continue to take antiretroviral therapy after vaccination, which maintains health and prevents onward HIV transmission. At this time, no antiretroviral drug has been shown to be effective against SARS-CoV-2 infection. People living with HIV should not switch or add antiretroviral drugs to their regimens for the purpose of preventing or treating COVID-19."},{"id":381,"category":"Vaccines and people living with HIV","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-and-people-living-with-hiv","question":"Do COVID-19 vaccines provide protection for people living with HIV?","response":"It is theoretically possible that people living with HIV with low CD4 cell counts might have a weaker immune response to a vaccine. However, in practice this has not been documented for other vaccines and there is no evidence to support a less robust immune response to COVID-19 vaccines among people with low CD4 cell counts. WHO is reviewing new evidence as it emerges and will provide an update when needed.  It is important to advocate for the inclusion of people living with HIV, including those with more advanced disease, in vaccine trials to provide information to confirm efficacy."},{"id":382,"category":"Vaccines and people living with HIV","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-and-people-living-with-hiv","question":"Should people living with HIV get vaccines early in the roll out?","response":"WHO recommends that countries consider the WHO SAGE Roadmap For Prioritizing Uses Of COVID-19 Vaccines In The Context Of Limited Supply.1 Most countries have made clear plans to support arrangements for those who will receive the vaccine in order of priority based on their age, health, occupation and other factors such people in living in care or residential homes. Some countries are prioritising vaccination for people living with HIV or who are immunocompromised (as indicated by having a CD4 cell count <200/mm2)3,4. Many people living with HIV have one or more comorbidities that may put them at increased risk for a more severe COVID-19. Furthermore, recent literature suggests that people living with HIV appear to be at increased risk for severe outcomes and death due to COVID-19 compared with people without HIV. People living with HIV with certain co-morbidities (such as asthma, COPD, diabetes, heart disease, kidney disease, liver disease, Parkinson’s disease, multiple sclerosis, motor neurone disease, severe obesity) will be prioritized for early vaccination in most settings. People living with HIV should not be excluded from COVID-19 vaccine access plans regardless of their immune status and countries ought to consider including people with HIV in a priority group for COVID-19 vaccination according with their epidemiological context.1 WHO SAGE Roadmap For Prioritizing Uses Of COVID-19 Vaccines In The Context Of Limited Supply. https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/who-sage-roadmap-for-prioritizing-uses-of-covid-19-vaccines-in-the-context-of-limited-supply2 https://www.who.int/initiatives/act-accelerator3 SARS-CoV-2 vaccine advice for adults living with HIV: British HIV Association (BHIVA) & Terrence Higgins Trust (THT) guidance. https://www.bhiva.org/SARS-CoV-2-vaccine-advice-for-adults-living-with-HIV-plain-english-version-update.4 Interim Guidance for COVID-19 and Persons with HIV. https://clinicalinfo.hiv.gov/sites/default/files/guidelines/documents/HIV_COVID_19_GL__2021.pdf."},{"id":383,"category":"Vaccines and people living with HIV","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-and-people-living-with-hiv","question":"What can people living with HIV do today to support their health?","response":"While the world works towards ensuring fair and equitable access to safe and effective COVID-19 vaccines, it is important to continue the essential public health actions to prevent SARS-CoV-2 transmission and to reduce COVID-19 mortality. Alongside the response to the COVID-19 pandemic, it is critical to maintain access to essential health services. This includes supporting people living with HIV to be able to continue anti-retroviral therapy (ART) and adapting services to make this easier and more efficient during the COVID-19 response. Continuing to provide HIV testing with linkage to ART initiation are priorities.  For people living with HIV, starting and remaining on ART to reduce health risks and complications during COVID-19 are essential services, together with prevention, diagnosis and treatment of co-morbidities and co-infections.  Although there may be an increase in the risk of developing severe disease from COVID-19 among people living with HIV, making sure that people have access to effective ART and other health care they need will help to minimise this risk. Close monitoring is warranted for all people living with HIV and SARS-CoV-2 infection, especially those with advanced HIV or with comorbidities.For further information on COVID-19 vaccines and all WHO guidance related to COVID-19 see https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance"},{"id":384,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"How do we know that COVID-19 vaccines are safe?","response":"There are strict protections in place to help ensure the safety of all COVID-19 vaccines. Before receiving validation from WHO and national regulatory agencies, COVID-19 vaccines must undergo rigorous testing in clinical trials to prove that they meet internationally agreed benchmarks for safety and efficacy.Unprecedented scientific collaborations have allowed COVID-19 vaccine research, development, and authorizations to be completed in record time – to meet the urgent need for these vaccines while maintaining high safety standards. As with all vaccines, WHO and regulatory authorities will continuously monitor the use of COVID-19 vaccines to identify and respond to any safety issues that might arise, and through that process to assure they remain safe for use around the world."},{"id":385,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"What are the side effects of COVID-19 vaccines?","response":"Like any vaccine, COVID-19 vaccines can cause mild, short term side effects, such as a low-grade fever or pain or redness at the injection site. Most reactions to vaccines are mild and go away within a few days on their own. More serious or long-lasting side effects to vaccines are possible but extremely rare. Vaccines are continually monitored for as long as they are in use, to detect rare adverse events and implement approaches to limit their occurrence. Reported side effects to COVID-19 vaccines have mostly been mild to moderate and short-lasting. They include: fever, fatigue, headache, muscle pain, chills, diarrhoea, and pain at the injection site. The chances of any of these side effects following vaccination differ according to the specific COVID-19 vaccine.In most cases, these can be managed with rest, plenty of non-alcoholic liquids, and paracetamol/acetaminophen for the typical side effects. Contact your care provider if the tenderness (pain) where you got the injection increases after 24 hours, or the side effects do not go away within a couple days. If you have difficulty breathing, chest pain, confusion, loss of speech or mobility, call a healthcare provider immediately."},{"id":386,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"What is the link between COVID-19 vaccines and allergic reactions?","response":"Severe allergic reactions have occurred rarely to some of the COVID vaccines. A severe allergic reaction – such as anaphylaxis – is a potential but rare side effect with any vaccine. In persons with a known risk, such as previous experience of an allergic reaction to a previous dose of the vaccine or any of the known components in the vaccine, precautions may need to be taken.WHO recommends that healthcare providers assess the risk for severe allergic reactions prior to giving a COVID-19 vaccine by inquiring about previous reactions or known allergies to any components in the vaccine.  All immunization providers should be trained to recognize severe allergic reactions and take steps to treat such reactions if they occur. COVID-19 vaccine use is being closely monitored by national authorities and international bodies, including WHO, to detect serious side effects, including any unexpected reactions. This is helping us better understand and manage the specific risks of allergic reactions or other serious side effects to COVID-19 vaccines that may not have been detected during clinical trials, ensuring safe vaccination for all."},{"id":387,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"Should I take a blood thinner a few days before taking the vaccine, given reports of blood clotting caused by the vaccination?","response":"No, you should not take a blood thinner unless your healthcare provider has prescribed that medication to treat an existing health condition. Covid-19 vaccines are safe for people taking blood thinners but you should let the person giving you the vaccine know about any medication you are taking BEFORE you are given the vaccine."},{"id":388,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"What happens if an adverse event is reported?","response":"As with any vaccine, it is essential to closely monitor the safety and effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccines that are used in immunization programmes. If a health problem is reported following vaccination, a thorough investigation should take place by the public health programme in the country.It is rare to find that health problems occurring following receipt of a vaccine are actually caused by the vaccine itself. Health problems following vaccination are most often found to be coincidental and entirely unrelated to vaccination. Sometimes they are related to how the vaccine has been stored, transported, or administered. Errors related to the delivery of the vaccine can be prevented by better training health workers and strengthening supply chains.In the very rare cases where a adverse reaction is suspected to be related to the vaccine itself, the vaccine may be suspended from use while the situation is assessed. Further investigations will take place to determine what exactly caused the event, and corrective measures will be put in place. WHO works with vaccine manufacturers, health officials, researchers, and other partners to monitor any safety concerns and potential side effects on an ongoing basis."},{"id":389,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"Under what circumstances should a COVID-19 vaccine be recalled?","response":"Vaccine recalls or withdrawals due to safety issues are rare. Recalls are usually initiated voluntarily by a vaccine manufacturer before any adverse events are reported. For example, ongoing monitoring of vaccine production may show that an irregularity has caused a batch of vaccines to lose their strength. In this case, people who have received a vaccine from that batch may need to be vaccinated again to ensure they are protected."},{"id":390,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"How will WHO inform the public about suspected or confirmed adverse events related to COVID-19 vaccines?","response":"Suspected safety events officially reported to WHO go through a series of rapid verification steps involving an independent panel of experts. WHO shares the results of these evaluations on its website.WHO also coordinates with local, regional, and national health officials to investigate vaccine safety concerns and advise on next steps. Information is also made available through the Vaccine Safety Net, a publicly available network of digital international resources on vaccine safety that have been approved by WHO."},{"id":391,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"Is it possible that someone vaccinated against COVID-19 will still get infected?","response":"While COVID-19 vaccines have high levels of efficacy, especially against hospitalization and severe disease, no vaccine is 100% protective. As a result, there will be some small percentage of vaccinated people who fall ill with COVID-19 in spite of being vaccinated.In addition to a vaccine's specific characteristics, several factors such as a person's age, their underlying health conditions, previous COVID-19 disease, current exposure to SARS-CoV-2, or the circulation of virus variants may have an impact on a vaccine’s effectiveness. We do not yet know how long immunity from different COVID-19 vaccines will last. That is one reason why, even as COVID-19 vaccines are being rolled out, we must continue using all public health measures that work to decrease exposure risk, such as physical distancing, masks, and handwashing.For the first 14 days after getting vaccinated, you do not have significant levels of protection as the protection increases gradually. For a single dose vaccine, protection is generally considered to occur by two weeks after vaccination. For two-dose vaccines, both doses are needed to achieve the highest level of immunity possible. While a COVID-19 vaccine is most effective against serious illness and death, we are still learning about their ability to protect you from getting infected and passing the virus on to others. To help keep yourself and others safe, and while vaccination rolling out in your community, continue to maintain at least a one metre distance from others, cover a cough or sneeze in your elbow, clean your hands frequently and wear a mask, particularly in enclosed, crowded or poorly ventilated spaces. Always follow guidance from local authorities based on the situation and risk where you live."},{"id":392,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"Who should be excluded from receiving COVID-19 vaccines?","response":"Medical professionals can best advise individuals on whether or not you should receive a COVID-19 vaccine. There are very few conditions that would exclude someone from being vaccinated. Based on available evidence, people with a history of severe allergic reactions to any ingredients of the COVID-19 vaccine should generally be excluded from COVID-19 vaccination in order to avoid possible adverse effects.If you are currently sick or experiencing symptoms of COVID-19, you can get vaccinated once your primary symptoms have resolved.In addition to the general recommendations above, each vaccine may have specific considerations for specific populations and health conditions."},{"id":393,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"Is it safe for pregnant women, those planning to become pregnant, and breastfeeding mothers to receive COVID-19 vaccines?","response":"In the interim, WHO recommends that for pregnant women the use of the COVID-19 vaccine be considered on the basis of a benefit vs risk assessment. To help pregnant women make this assessment, they should be provided with information about the risks of COVID-19 in pregnancy, the likely benefits of vaccination in the local epidemiological context, and the current limitations of safety data in pregnant women. WHO does not recommend pregnancy testing prior to vaccination. WHO does not recommend delaying pregnancy or terminating pregnancy because of vaccination.Vaccination with any of the vaccine products that have been assessed by the WHO Strategic Advisory Group of Experts on Immunization can be offered to breastfeeding women. WHO does not recommend discontinuation of breastfeeding after vaccination. More evidence will continue to be sought in order to further inform WHO’s policy recommendations on this subject."},{"id":394,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"Should women who are on their periods take the COVID-19 vaccine?","response":"Women can receive a vaccine at any point in their menstrual cycle."},{"id":395,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"Are mRNA vaccines safe? If they’re based on new technology, how can we be sure?","response":"The COVID-19 mRNA vaccine technology has been rigorously assessed for safety, and clinical trials have shown that mRNA vaccines produce an immune response that has high efficacy against disease. mRNA vaccine technology has been studied for several decades, including in the contexts of Zika, rabies, and influenza vaccines. mRNA vaccines are not live virus vaccines and do not interfere with human DNA."},{"id":396,"category":"Vaccines safety","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines-safety","question":"How will WHO ensure vaccine safety monitoring and response when COVID-19 vaccines are used?","response":"Vaccine safety monitoring is ensured at the national, regional, and global level. As is standard practice in all national immunization programmes, WHO supports the set up of safety monitoring systems for COVID-19 vaccines in every country. After a COVID-19 vaccine is introduced in a country, WHO works with vaccine manufacturers, health officials and other partners to monitor for any safety concerns on an ongoing basis. Specific safety concerns that may arise are evaluated by WHO and an independent group of experts (the Global Advisory Committee on Vaccine Safety, or GACVS) in conjunction with the relevant national authorities."},{"id":397,"category":"Ventilation and air conditioning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ventilation-and-air-conditioning","question":"What is ventilation and how can it prevent COVID-19 from spreading?","response":"Ventilation involves introducing clean air into a space while removing stale air, in order to maintain or improve air quality. Ventilation can be achieved naturally (e.g. by opening a window) or by installing a mechanical system. The spread of COVID-19 occurs most often when an infected person is in close or direct contact with another person. The risk of the spread of the virus is higher in crowded and poorly ventilated spaces where people spend long periods of time together in close proximity. Improving indoor ventilation can reduce the risk of the virus spreading indoors. Ventilation is not a standalone measure and it should be implemented as part of a comprehensive package of measures, such as physical distancing, wearing a mask, frequent hand cleaning, and coughing or sneezing into a bent elbow. Each of these is important to protect you against COVID-19 infection. Find out more about how to stay safe on our  public advice page."},{"id":398,"category":"Ventilation and air conditioning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ventilation-and-air-conditioning","question":"How do I naturally ventilate a room?","response":"When you are inside with other people, open windows or doors whenever possible. For instance, try to get a cross breeze so that air coming in from one window moves across the room and exits from another window."},{"id":399,"category":"Ventilation and air conditioning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ventilation-and-air-conditioning","question":"Can I use air conditioning or other ventilation systems?","response":"Heating, ventilation and air-conditioning (HVAC) systems are used to maintain indoor air temperature and humidity at healthy and comfortable levels. A well-maintained and operated system can reduce the spread of COVID-19 in indoor spaces by increasing\r\n    the rate of air change, reducing air recirculation and increasing the amount of outdoor air coming in. Settings that recirculate the air should not be used. HVAC systems should always be regularly inspected, maintained, and cleaned."},{"id":400,"category":"Ventilation and air conditioning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ventilation-and-air-conditioning","question":"How can I improve heating and air conditioning systems at home?","response":"Non-ducted heating and air conditioning units that recirculate air, such as fan-coil or split units, should be assessed, maintained and cleaned according to manufacturer recommendations. Assess the unit’s filter and consider replacing the existing filter with MERV14/F8 or the highest compatible filter with the filter rack, in collaboration with an HVAC professional. The units and filters should be periodically cleaned and maintained according to manufacturer recommendations.More information is available here."},{"id":401,"category":"Ventilation and air conditioning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ventilation-and-air-conditioning","question":"Can fans be used safely inside?","response":"Air blowing from an infected person directly at another person in a closed space increases the risk of the virus spreading from one person to another. If COVID-19 is circulating in your community and the use of a table or pedestal fan is unavoidable, it is important to regularly bring in air from outside by opening windows or doors, while minimizing how much air blows from one person (or group of\r\n        people) to another person (or group of people).The use of ceiling fans can improve the circulation of air from outside and avoid pockets of stagnant air forming indoors. However, it is critical to bring in air from outside when using ceiling fans, such as by opening windows."},{"id":402,"category":"Ventilation and air conditioning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ventilation-and-air-conditioning","question":"How can I improve ventilation at home if someone is sick and isolating there?","response":"If someone is sick and being cared for at home, here are some precautions to take:The ill person should stay in a separate room. If this is not possible, then keep at least a 1-metre distance from them. The sick person and anyone else in the same room should wear a medical mask.Provide good ventilation in the room of the ill person and shared spaces, and open windows if possible and safe to do so. Use cross ventilation to increase natural air movement by opening windows or doors on both sides of the room. If possible, block air from moving from the sick person’s room to the rest of the house. If available, choose a room with a private toilet with an air extractor or exhaust fan, which should run at a high speed.As a supplement, you can use a stand-alone air cleaner with a MERV14/F8 filter. These devices may improve air quality but are not a replacement for ventilation.Also see  WHO’s Q&A on homecare ."},{"id":403,"category":"Ventilation and air conditioning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ventilation-and-air-conditioning","question":"How can ventilation reduce the risk of contracting COVID-19 in airplanes?","response":"Most airplanes have cabin air filtration systems equipped with HEPA filters which can remove viruses and germs quickly, minimizing how long people are exposed to any potential infectious virus or bacteria expelled by a cough or sneeze. Cabin air systems\r\n    are designed to operate most efficiently by delivering approximately 50 percent outside air and 50 percent filtered, recirculated air. The air supply is essentially sterile and particle-free. However, adequate ventilation is just one of the preventive\r\n    measures to reduce the risk of COVID-19 transmission.  Other important measures include maintaining physical distance of at least 1 metre whenever possible, wearing a mask, frequent hand hygiene and wearing a mask."},{"id":404,"category":"Ventilation and air conditioning","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-ventilation-and-air-conditioning","question":"What is WHO doing to address ventilation in the context of COVID-19?","response":"Since January 2020, WHO has provided recommendation on ventilation in COVID-19 guidance. Early in the pandemic, WHO established the WHO Environment and Engineering Control Expert Advisory Panel (ECAP) for COVID-19 to review available scientific evidence and practices and update recommendations on environment and engineering controls. This multidisciplinary network brings together technical experts from various fields, such as infection control specialists, engineers, architects, aerobiologists and environmental experts. In June 2020, WHO contributed to guidance on ventilation and air-conditioning systems in the context of COVID-19, available here. WHO works closely with the World Meteorological Organization Joint Office for Climate and Health and the United States National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) through the Global Heat Health Information Network to develop and update this guidance.In February 2021, WHO published a  roadmap to improve ventilation."},{"id":405,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"Home is not a safe place for me. What can I do?","response":"If you are experiencing violence, it may be helpful to reach out to family, friends and neighbors, to seek support from a hotline or, if safe, from online service for survivors of violence. Find out if local services (e.g. shelters, counselling) are open and reach out to them if available. Make a safety plan in case the violence against you or your children escalates. This includes: Identifying a neighbour, friend, relative, colleague, or shelter to go to in case you need to leave the house immediately for safety. Have a plan for how you will exit the house safely and how you will reach there (e.g. transport).  Keep a few essential items (e.g. identification documents, phone, money, medicines, and clothes) available, and a list of telephone numbers in case of an emergency.  If possible, develop a code with a trusted neighbour so they can come to your aid in case of an emergency."},{"id":406,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"I need medical attention because of violence. Who can help me and where should I go?","response":"If you need urgent medical attention, call for an ambulance or contact your country’s emergency health services. If you need any other support, contact a specialized service if available or a health provider."},{"id":407,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"I am safe, but I am suffering from mental / sexual / social / long-term physical health problems because of violence. Is there anyone who can help me during COVID-19?","response":"As much as possible, reduce sources of stress: Maintain contact with and seek support from family and friends via phone, email, text, etc. Try to maintain daily routines and make time for physical activity and sleep. Use relaxation exercises (e.g. slow breathing, meditation, progressive muscle relaxation, grounding exercises – see WHO Clinical handbook p.70) to relieve stressful thoughts and feelings. Engage in activities that in the past have helped with managing adversity. Seek information about COVID- 19 from reliable sources and reduce the time spent consuming news (for example, 1-2 times per day, rather than every hour). Seek care from a trained health provider for symptoms and conditions including injuries that need medical attention. Due to restrictions on movement, and pressure on health systems, it may be difficult to access healthcare in person at this time. In this case, find out what is available in your locality and seek alternatives, including information and support offered by phone or online.  If you are currently receiving healthcare and support for violence-related issues this could continue during COVID-19 – this could even be by phone or online if feasible and appropriate for your health needs."},{"id":408,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"I am worried about someone I know. How can I help?","response":"If you know of, or are concerned about, someone in an abusive relationship there are some things you can do: Keep regularly in touch with the person to check that they are safe, ensuring that it is safe for them to be in touch with you. Assume that a perpetrator of violence can see, hear and or monitor communications, so find out how best to communicate with the person that you are concerned about.  Send them an SMS or message via email or social media, in a way that is safe for them. Be discrete in connecting with them when the abuser is present in the home so that they are not placed at risk of additional harm. Check each time, as this may change. Find out what services for survivors of violence against women (e.g. shelters, hotlines, counselling services, women’s organizations) are functioning during the COVID-19 pandemic and make this information available through your networks and social media. Only provide this information directly if you can do so discretely without the abuser finding out.  If someone you know needs urgent help for whatever reason, be prepared to call emergency health services, the police, health centre, or hotline."},{"id":409,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"I want to report an incidence of violence during COVID-19. What should I do?","response":"If you want to report an incidence of violence, you should follow your country’s guidance on how to report violence and contact the service where you are most likely to get a survivor-centred response.  Some countries are making exceptions to movement restrictions for reporting of violence specifically. Remember that reporting may put you at risk, so ensure you have a safety plan in place. You may find making a report mentally or emotionally difficult. Seek the support of friends, relations, neighbours or colleagues, or local support services for survivors of violence."},{"id":410,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"I have harmed or am worried about harming or hurting my partner (and children) with my words or actions. How can I stop?","response":"If you feel yourself getting angry or very annoyed, step away into another room if you can, or outside for a deep breath.  Count to ten and breathe in and out until you feel calmer. Count down from 10, or do anything else that may help you stay calm. Talk to a trusted friend, relative, or religious leader and if necessary seek help from local health services or specialized services if available.  Recognize that everyone in your family is experiencing stress during this time. Demonstrate kindness and patience in your words and actions.  Eliminate or reduce your alcohol consumption as much as possible. The current measures to address the COVID-19 pandemic, such as restrictions on movement, as well as financial instability caused by the crisis, are likely to add to your stress.  This is normal, and you can control how you react.  Take measures to ensure you manage your stress in a way that is respectful and safe to you and your family. Try to be kind to yourself, your partner, children and anyone else in the family."},{"id":411,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"I am a health worker. How can I help women survivors of violence during COVID-19?","response":"As a health worker, there are things you can do to help mitigate the impacts of violence on women and children at any time, including during the COVID-19 pandemic.   Whilst your time and resources may be stretched during this health emergency, you have a duty of care to women who may seek help from you – often to address physical and mental hurt caused by violence.   You may need to adjust how you deliver services, if face-to-face care is not possible. Depending on your resources consider mobile phone, WhatsApp or other communication channels to deliver support, always ensuring you can do this in a way that is safe for the survivor. Communicate openly with women about any changes in service delivery.   If a woman with suspected or confirmed COVID-19 seeks your care because of violence, your response should be the same as for any other survivor. You should however ensure that you are protected from infection, by maintaining distance where possible, wearing protective clothing, practicing respiratory hygiene, and washing hands and surfaces with soap and water regularly and after touching, to avoid infection. In any circumstances, including during the COVID-19 pandemic, health workers should provide first-line support, using the LIVES approach to help women survivors of violence:  Listen closely, with empathy and no judgement Inquire about women’s needs and concerns Validate women’s experiences. Show you believe and understand. Enhance their safety. Support women to connect with additional services."},{"id":412,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"I run a health facility. What can I do to support women survivors of violence during COVID-19?","response":"Identify information on local services for survivors, including on hotlines, shelters, rape crisis centers, and counselling.  Find out opening hours, contact details and whether these services can be offered remotely, and establish referral linkages.  Make these available to health care providers and easily accessible to patients/clients coming to your facility.  Support the health care providers in your facility to continue to support women survivors of violence during this time. Be prepared to shift rapidly to providing care through alternative ways, by creating effective response plans; for example, by ensuring frontline healthcare workers have phones and can charge them.  Ensure there is a protocol in place to ensure continued safe document storage in case of sudden lockdown. Inform survivors of ways they can protect themselves, and provide small credit card-size cards listing relevant phone numbers for support"},{"id":413,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"I am a policy maker. What can I do to prevent and address violence against women during COVID-19?","response":"When making preparedness and response plans for the COVID-19 pandemic, include essential services for violence against women. Allocate adequate resources for services for survivors and identify ways to make them accessible – particularly in the context of measures to restrict people’s movement. Explore the use of telemedicine, digital health, or mhealth to enhance access to support and services for survivors, while ensuring this is safe for them.  Explore alternative shelters for women who may require this. Ensure that lockdown measures do not penalize women for seeking support when experiencing violence, such as by going to the police or hospital to report violence."},{"id":414,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"Has violence against women increased since the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"Violence against women is highly prevalent, and intimate partner violence is the most common form of violence. During health emergencies, such as the COVID-19 pandemic, violence against women tends to increase.  Whilst data are scarce, reports from across the world, including China, the United Kingdom, the United States of America, and other countries suggest a significant increase in domestic violence cases related to the COVID-19 pandemic. Reports from other countries suggest a reduction in survivors seeking services due to a combination of lockdown measures and not wanting to attend health services for fear of infection."},{"id":415,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"How does COVID-19 increase risks of violence for women?","response":"Stress, the disruption of social and protective networks, loss of income and decreased access to services all can exacerbate the risk of violence for women. In many countries, where people are encouraged or required to stay at home, the risk of intimate partner violence is likely to increase. Please see the following resource for more detail: https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/emergencies/COVID-19-VAW-full-text.pdf In addition, access to sexual and reproductive health services will likely become more limited. Other services, such as hotlines, crisis centers, shelters, legal aid, and protection services, may also be reduced, making it difficult for women to access the few sources of help that would usually be available."},{"id":416,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"Who is most vulnerable?","response":"Women who are displaced, who are migrants or refugees, and those living in conflict-affected areas, older women and women with disabilities are particularly at risk of violence and are likely to be disproportionately affected by violence during COVID-19."},{"id":417,"category":"Violence against women","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-violence-against-women","question":"Why should I care about violence against women during COVID-19?","response":"Violence against women is a grave violation of women’s human rights, no matter when, where, or how it takes place. There are many forms of violence against women, which have many potential negative health consequences for women and their children.  Violence against women can result in injuries and serious physical, mental, sexual and reproductive health problems, including sexually transmitted infections, HIV, and unplanned pregnancies. In extreme cases, violence against women can result in death. The effects of violence are very often long-lived. Violence – in all its forms – can have an impact on a woman’s well-being throughout the rest of her life. This is unacceptable, and the risks of violence that women and their children face during the current COVID-19 crisis cannot be ignored. When we are able to prevent violence, or to support women survivors of violence, we help to safeguard women’s human rights, and promote physical and mental health and well-being for women throughout their lives. This also helps to alleviate pressure on already stretched essential public services, including the health system."},{"id":418,"category":"Virus Evolution","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/sars-cov-2-evolution","question":"What does it mean to say a virus mutates or changes?","response":"When a virus replicates or makes copies of itself, it sometimes changes a little bit. These changes are called “mutations.” A virus with one or several new mutations is  referred to as a “variant” of the original virus. The more viruses circulate, the more they may change. These changes can occasionally result in a virus variant that is better adapted to its environment compared to the original virus. This process of changing and selection of successful variants is called “virus evolution.”Some mutations can lead to changes in a virus’s characteristics, such as altered transmission (for example, it may spread more easily) or severity (for example, it may cause more severe disease).Some viruses change quickly and others more slowly. SARS-CoV-2, the virus which causes COVID-19, tends to change more slowly than others such as HIV or influenza viruses. This could in part be explained by the virus’s internal “proofreading mechanism” which can correct “mistakes” when it makes copies of itself. Scientists continue to study this mechanism to better understand how it works."},{"id":419,"category":"Virus Evolution","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/sars-cov-2-evolution","question":"Should I be concerned about SARS-CoV-2 changing?","response":"It is normal for viruses to change, but it is still something scientists follow closely because there can be important implications. All viruses, including SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, change over time. So far hundreds of variations of this virus have been identified worldwide. WHO and partners have been following them closely since January 2020. Most changes have little to no impact on the virus’ properties. However, depending on where the changes are located in the virus’s genetic material, they may affect the virus’s properties, such as transmission (for example, it may spread more easily) or severity (for example, it may cause more severe disease). WHO and its international network of experts, are monitoring changes to the virus so that if significant  mutations are identified, WHO can report any modifications to interventions needed by countries and individuals to prevent the spread of that variant.  The current strategies and measures recommended by WHO continue to work against virus variants identified since the start of the pandemic. See WHO’s Disease Outbreak News for reports on variants. The best way to limit and suppress the transmission of COVID-19 is for people to continue taking the necessary precautions to keep themselves and others safe."},{"id":420,"category":"Virus Evolution","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/sars-cov-2-evolution","question":"What is WHO doing to monitor and understand the changes in SARS-CoV-2?","response":"Since the start of the outbreak, WHO has been working with a global network of expert laboratories around the world to support testing and better understanding of SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19.Research groups have sequenced SARS-CoV-2 and shared these on public databases, including GISAID. This global collaboration allows scientists to better track the virus and how it is changing.WHO’s global SARS-CoV-2 laboratory network includes a dedicated SARS-CoV-2 Virus Evolution Working Group, which aims to detect new mutations quickly and assess their possible impact.WHO recommends that all countries increase the sequencing of SARS-CoV-2 viruses where possible and share sequence data internationally to help one another monitor and respond to the evolving pandemic."},{"id":421,"category":"Virus Evolution","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/sars-cov-2-evolution","question":"How does SARS-CoV-2 change when it infects animals, and what are the implications?","response":"SARS-CoV-2 spreads primarily through human-to-human transmission, but there is evidence of transmission between humans and animals. Several animals like mink, dogs, domestic cats, lions, tigers and raccoon dogs have tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 after contact with infected humans.There have been reports of large animal outbreaks in mink farms in several countries. SARS-CoV-2 can change while infecting minks. It has been observed that these mink variants are able to transmit back into humans through close contact with the mink. Preliminary results suggest that the mink variants infecting humans appear to have the same properties as other variants of the SARS-CoV-2 virus.Further research is needed to better understand whether these mink variants will cause sustained transmission among humans and could have a negative impact on countermeasures, such as vaccines.  See WHO’s Disease Outbreak News on DenmarkWHO works closely with other organizations, such as the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, and the World Organisation for Animal Health, to evaluate situations of SARS-CoV-2 in animals and transmission occurring between animals and humans."},{"id":422,"category":"Working in hotels and other accommodation establishments","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-working-in-hotels","question":"What can staff do to stay safe while working at a hotel or other accommodation establishment?","response":"Everyone should follow basic precautions: Wash all parts of your hands frequently (at least 20 seconds if using an alcohol-based hand rub, and at least 40 seconds with soap and water), including after exchanging objects such as money or credit cards with guests.Cover a cough or sneeze with a bent elbow or tissue and throw away the tissue in a closed bin.Maintain at least a 1 metre distance from other staff and guests. This includes avoid hugging, kissing, or shaking hands. If you can’t guarantee the distance, wear a fabric mask. Be sure to check local and national guidelines on the use of masks. Staying behind plexiglass boards at reception and concierge desks can prevent droplet transmission. Teleworking may be a possibility for some jobs, which can help reduce physical contact with others."},{"id":423,"category":"Working in hotels and other accommodation establishments","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-working-in-hotels","question":"Should staff wear a mask while working?","response":"In areas where the virus that causes COVID-19 is circulating, staff aged 60 or over, or who have any underlying health conditions such as heart disease, diabetes or lung cancer, should wear a medical mask because of their higher risk of getting seriously ill from COVID-19. Staff under the age of 60 and who are in general good health can wear fabric masks when they cannot guarantee at least a 1 metre distance from others. This is particularly important for staff who are in close contact or potential close contact with others. Everyone should follow local policies and regulations."},{"id":424,"category":"Working in hotels and other accommodation establishments","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-working-in-hotels","question":"What should staff do if a guest becomes sick at an accommodation establishment?","response":"If a guest at the accommodation develops symptoms of COVID-19, such as fever, dry cough or tiredness, staff at the accommodation establishment should contact the local health authority and follow their instructions. The sick person should be isolated in a room, alone, or at least 1 metre away from others, according to local health authorities’ instructions. No visitors should be permitted to enter the room occupied by the affected guest. Staff should also move people traveling with the sick person to a different room, if possible. It is usually the relevant public health authority, not the management of the hotel and accommodation establishment, which has the authority to demand sick guests to temporarily remain in their room or to prevent them from receiving visits from other guests. National law will guide the rights of the guests to refuse or not the recommended measures.Staff entering the room of an ill person should maintain at least a 1 metre distance from the ill person, and request that the ill person put on a medical mask.  If staff need to assist an ill guest within a 1 metre distance, they should clean their hands before putting on appropriate personal protective equipment (medical mask and eye protection, gloves and isolation gown), and clean their hands after providing assistance. Training should be provided on how to avoid contaminating themselves."},{"id":425,"category":"Working in hotels and other accommodation establishments","source":"https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/question-and-answers-hub/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-working-in-hotels","question":"What should staff do if they have symptoms?","response":"If staff develop COVID-19 symptoms while at work, such as fever, dry cough or tiredness, they should immediately stop working, put on a medical mask and isolate in a suitable room while medical services are notified. Disposable tissues and an appropriate waste bin with a lid should be available in the designated isolation area while waiting for medical assessment or transfer to an assessment facility.If staff develop symptoms while at home, they should stay at home and seek medical attention, following instructions from a health worker that will include a period of time for self-isolation away from others, including family members, according to local guidance.  The staff member should inform the management accordingly."},{"id":426,"category":"Basics","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What is COVID-19?","response":"COVID-19 is a disease caused by a virus called SARS-CoV-2. Most people with COVID-19 have mild symptoms, but some people can become severely ill. Although most people with COVID-19 get better within weeks of illness, some people experience post-COVID conditions. Post-COVID conditions are a wide range of new, returning, or ongoing health problems people can experience more than four weeks after first being infected with the virus that causes COVID-19. Older people and those who have certain underlying medical conditions are more likely to get severely ill from COVID-19. Vaccines against COVID-19 are safe and effective."},{"id":427,"category":"Basics","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Why is the disease being called coronavirus disease 2019, COVID-19?","response":"On February 11, 2020 the World Health Organization announced an official name for the disease that is causing the 2019 novel coronavirus pandemic, first identified in Wuhan China. The new name of this disease is coronavirus disease 2019, abbreviated as COVID-19. In COVID-19, “CO” stands for corona, “VI” for virus, and ”D” for disease. Formerly, this disease was referred to as “2019 novel coronavirus” or “2019-nCoV.”"},{"id":428,"category":"Spread","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"How does the virus spread?","response":"COVID-19 is thought to spread mainly through close contact from person to person, including between people who are physically near each other (within about 6 feet). People who are infected but do not show symptoms can also spread the virus to others. Cases of reinfection with COVID-19  have been reported but are rare. We are still learning about how the virus spreads and the severity of illness it causes.\nCOVID-19 spreads very easily from person to person. How easily a virus spreads from person to person can vary. The virus that causes COVID-19 appears to spread more efficiently than influenza but not as efficiently as measles, which is among the most contagious viruses known to affect people.\nFor more information about how COVID-19 spreads, visit the How COVID-19 Spreads page to learn how COVID-19 spreads and how to protect yourself."},{"id":429,"category":"Spread","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What is community spread?","response":"Community spread means people have been infected with the virus in an area, including some who are not sure how or where they became infected. Each health department determines community spread differently based on local conditions. For information on community spread in your area, please visit your local health department’s website."},{"id":430,"category":"Spread","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can mosquitoes or ticks spread the virus that causes COVID-19?","response":"At this time, CDC has no data to suggest that this new coronavirus or other similar coronaviruses are spread by mosquitoes or ticks. The main way that COVID-19 spreads is from person to person. See How Coronavirus Spreads for more information."},{"id":431,"category":"Prevention","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"How can I protect myself?","response":"Visit the How to Protect Yourself & Others page to learn about how to protect yourself from respiratory illnesses, like COVID-19."},{"id":432,"category":"Prevention","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Does CDC recommend the use of masks to prevent COVID-19?","response":"Yes. CDC recommends that people wear masks in public settings, at events and gatherings, and anywhere they will be around other people. When you wear a mask, you protect others as well as yourself. Masks work best when everyone wears one. A mask is NOT a substitute for social distancing. Masks should still be worn in addition to staying at least 6 feet apart, especially when indoors around people who don’t live in your household.\nEffective February 2, 2021, masks are required on planes, buses, trains, and other forms of public transportation traveling into, within, or out of the United States and in U.S. transportation hubs such as airports and stations.\nWhile masks are strongly encouraged to reduce the spread of COVID-19, CDC recognizes there are specific instances when wearing a mask may not be feasible. In these instances, adaptations and alternatives should be considered whenever possible.\nMore information about masks can be found on our masks site.\n\nYour Guide to Masks\nHow to Wear\nHow to Store and Wash\nImprove How Your Mask Protects You\nTypes of Masks\nGuidance for Wearing Masks\nImprove Fit and Filtration of Your Mask"},{"id":433,"category":"Prevention","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Is it safe to get care for my other medical conditions during this time?","response":"Continue taking care of your health and wellness\n\n\nContinue your medications, and do not change your treatment plan without talking to your healthcare provider.\nContinue to manage your disease the way your healthcare provider has told you.\nHave at least a 2-week supply of all prescription and non-prescription medications.\nTalk to your healthcare provider about whether your vaccinations and other preventative services are up to date.\nCall your healthcare provider\n\nif you have any concerns about your medical conditions, or if you get sick.\nto find out about different ways you can connect with your healthcare provider for chronic disease management or other conditions.\n\nIf you must visit in-person, protect yourself and others.\n\n\n\n\nDo not delay getting emergency care for your health problems or any underlying medical condition that requires immediate attention.\n\nIf you need emergency help, call 911.\nEmergency departments have infection prevention plans to protect you from getting COVID-19 if you need care for your medical condition.\n\n\nContinue to practice everyday prevention. Wash your hands often, avoid close contact, wear a mask, cover coughs and sneezes, and clean frequently touched surfaces often.\n\n\nWhen picking up medicines, use drive-thru windows, curbside services (prescriptions brought to you in your car), mail-order, or other delivery services.\n\nFor more information, see Groups at Higher Risk for Severe Illness."},{"id":434,"category":"Prevention","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Am I at risk for COVID-19 from mail, packages, or products?","response":"Coronaviruses are thought to be spread most often by respiratory droplets. Although the virus can survive for a short period on some surfaces, it is unlikely to be spread from domestic or international mail, products, or packaging. However, it may be possible that people can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes, but this is not thought to be the main way the virus spreads.\nLearn more about safe handling of deliveries and mail."},{"id":435,"category":"Prevention","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Is it okay for me to donate blood?","response":"In healthcare settings across the United States, donated blood is a lifesaving, essential part of caring for patients. The need for donated blood is constant, and blood centers are open and in urgent need of donations. CDC encourages people who are well to continue to donate blood if they are able, even if they are practicing social distancing because of COVID-19. CDC is supporting blood centers by providing recommendations that will keep donors and staff safe. Examples of these recommendations include spacing donor chairs 6 feet apart, thoroughly adhering to environmental cleaning practices, and encouraging donors to make donation appointments ahead of time."},{"id":436,"category":"Prevention","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Should contact lens wearers take special precautions to prevent COVID-19?","response":"Currently, there is no evidence to suggest contact lens wearers are more at risk for acquiring COVID-19 than eyeglass wearers.\nContact lens wearers should continue to practice safe contact lens wear and care hygiene habits to help prevent against transmission of any contact lens-related infections, such as always washing hands with soap and water before handling lenses.\nPeople who are healthy can continue to wear and care for their contact lenses as prescribed by their eye care professional.\n\nFind more information about how coronavirus spreads and how to protect yourself.\nVisit CDC’s contact lens website for more information on healthy contact lens wear and care."},{"id":437,"category":"Prevention","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Is contact lens disinfecting solution effective against COVID-19?","response":"Hydrogen peroxide-based systems for cleaning, disinfecting, and storing contact lenses should be effective against the virus that causes COVID-19.\n\nFor other disinfection methods, such as multipurpose solution and ultrasonic cleaners, there is currently not enough scientific evidence to determine efficacy against the virus.\n\n\nAlways use solution to disinfect your contact lenses and case to kill germs that may be present.\nHandle your lenses over a surface that has been cleaned and disinfected.\n\nFind more information about how coronavirus spreads and how to protect yourself.\nVisit CDC’s contact lens website for more information on healthy contact lens wear and care."},{"id":438,"category":"Prevention","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Should I use soap and water or hand sanitizer to protect against COVID-19?","response":"Handwashing is one of the best ways to protect yourself and your family from getting sick. Wash your hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds, especially after blowing your nose, coughing, or sneezing; going to the bathroom; and before eating or preparing food. If soap and water are not readily available, use an alcohol-based hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol."},{"id":439,"category":"Prevention","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What cleaning products should I use to protect against COVID-19?","response":"Clean frequently touched surfaces such as tables, doorknobs, light switches, countertops, handles, desks, phones, keyboards, toilets, faucets, and sinks. Cleaning with products containing soap or detergent reduces germs on surfaces and objects by removing contaminants and may weaken or damage some of the virus particles, which decreases risk of infection from surfaces. You may choose to also disinfect depending on certain conditions or everyday practices required by your home. To disinfect, most common Environmental Protection Agency-registered household disinfect ants will work. See CDC’s recommendations for household cleaning and disinfection."},{"id":440,"category":"If You or Someone You Know is Sick or Had Contact with Someone who Has COVID-19","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What should I do if I get sick or someone in my house gets sick?","response":"Most people who get COVID-19 will be able to recover at home. /coronavirus/2019-ncov/if-you-are-sick/index.html for people who are recovering at home and their caregivers, including:\n\nStay home when you are sick, except to get medical care.https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/guidance-prevent-spread.htmlCDC has directions\nIf you have COVID-19, tell your close contacts so that they can quarantine at home and get tested.\nUse a separate room and bathroom for sick household members (if possible).\nThe person who is sick should isolate. Learn when and how to isolate.\nWash your hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds, especially after blowing your nose, coughing, or sneezing; going to the bathroom; and before eating or preparing food.\nIf soap and water are not readily available, use an alcohol-based hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol. Always wash hands with soap and water if hands are visibly dirty.\nThe person who is sick should wear a mask when they are around other people at home. They do not need to wear a mask if they are alone.\nClean the sick room and bathroom, as needed, to avoid unnecessary contact with the sick person.\n\nHowever, some people may need emergency medical attention. Watch for symptoms and learn when to seek emergency medical attention.\nCall 911 or call ahead to your local emergency facility: Notify the operator that you are seeking care for someone who has or may have COVID-19."},{"id":441,"category":"If You or Someone You Know is Sick or Had Contact with Someone who Has COVID-19","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What should I do if I have had close contact with someone who has COVID-19?","response":"The best way to protect yourself and others is to quarantine by staying home for 14 days if you think you’ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department’s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period.\nBe alert for symptoms of COVID-19.\nIf possible, stay away from others, especially people who are at higher risk for getting very sick from COVID-19.\nYou may NOT need to quarantine if:\n\nYou have been fully vaccinated and have no symptoms\nYou were previously diagnosed with COVID-19 within the last three months and don’t develop any new symptoms"},{"id":442,"category":"Children","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What is the risk of my child becoming sick with COVID-19?","response":"Children can be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19 and can get sick with COVID-19. Most children with COVID-19 have mild symptoms or they may have no symptoms at all (“asymptomatic”). Fewer children have been sick with COVID-19 compared to adults. Babies younger than 1 and children with certain underlying medical conditions may be more likely to have serious illness from COVID-19. Some children have developed a rare but serious disease that is linked to COVID-19 called multisystem inflammatory syndrome (MIS-C).\nFor more information for parents or caregivers of children, see Children and Teens and the COVID-19 Parental Resources Kit.\nFor more information about how people get sick with the virus that causes COVID-19, see How COVID-19 Spreads."},{"id":443,"category":"Children","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Should children wear masks?","response":"In general, children 2 years and older should wear a mask. However, CDC recognizes that wearing masks may not be possible in every situation or for some people. Appropriate and consistent use of masks may be challenging for some children, such as children with certain disabilities, including cognitive, intellectual, developmental, sensory and behavioral disorders. Learn more about what you should do if your child or you cannot wear masks in certain situations and special considerations for children who may have difficulties with techniques for improved fit and filtration."},{"id":444,"category":"Children","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What is multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C)?","response":"Multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C) is a serious condition associated with COVID-19 where different body parts can become inflamed, including the heart, lungs, kidneys, brain, skin, eyes, or gastrointestinal organs. For information, see MIS-C."},{"id":445,"category":"Children","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can my child spend time with older adults and people with chronic medical conditions?","response":"Older adults and people who have certain underlying medical conditions are at increased risk for getting severely ill from COVID-19. To protect those who are at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19, you may consider taking these extra precautions.\n\nSeparate your child from others in your household who have an increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19.\nCarefully consider who might be best to provide childcare if you are unable to care for your child (for example, you are not able to stay with your child while childcare or school is closed).\nLimit your child’s contact with other people if someone at higher risk for COVID-19 will be providing care (such as an older adult or someone with an underlying medical condition).\nPostpone visits or trips to see grandparents, older family members and family members who are at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19. Consider connecting virtually or by writing letters."},{"id":446,"category":"Children","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"My child has an underlying medical condition. What additional steps should my family take?","response":"Children with underlying medical conditions are at increased risk for severe illness compared to children without underlying medical conditions. Current evidence on which underlying medical conditions in children are associated with increased risk is limited. Children with the following conditions might be at increased risk for severe illness: obesity, medical complexity, severe genetic disorders, severe neurologic disorders, inherited metabolic disorders, sickle cell disease, congenital (since birth) heart disease, diabetes, chronic kidney disease, asthma and other chronic lung disease, and immunosuppression due to malignancy or immune-weakening medications. In addition to following the recommendations to prevent getting sick, families can take steps recommended for children with underlying conditions.\n\nConsider identifying potential alternative caregivers, in case you or other regular caregivers become sick and are unable to care for your child. If possible, these alternative caregivers should not be at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19. For more information, see Sick Parents and Caregivers. Make sure these caregivers take extra precautions if your child has a disability.\nIf your child receives any support care services in the home, such as services from personal care attendants, direct support professionals, or therapists, make plans for what you will do if your child’s direct care providers or anyone in your family gets sick. You can review CDC’s recommendations for Direct Service Providers.\n\nFor more information, see Children and Teens and Others who Need Extra Precautions."},{"id":447,"category":"Children","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Should my infant or child be tested for COVID-19?","response":"Not everyone needs to be tested. Your infant or child may need to be tested for COVID-19 if your child:\n\nHas symptoms of COVID-19, or\nHad close contact (within 6 feet of an infected person for a cumulative total of 15 minutes or more over a 24-hour period) with someone who tested positive for COVID-19, or\nTook part in activities that put them at higher risk for COVID-19, because they could not stay at least 6 feet apart as needed (such as travel, attending large social or mass gatherings, or being in a crowded or poorly ventilated indoor setting), or\nWas asked or referred to get testing by their state, tribal, localexternal icon, or territorial health department or healthcare provider.\n\nIf your child is tested because they have COVID-19 symptoms or have been in close contact with someone with COVID-19, keep your child home until they can safely end isolation or quarantine and follow the advice of your healthcare provider or a public health professional. If your child has recovered from COVID-19 in the past 3 months and does not have symptoms of COVID-19, they do not need to be retested for up to 3 months from their last positive test result."},{"id":448,"category":"Symptoms & Emergency Warning Signs","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What are the symptoms and complications that COVID-19 can cause?","response":"People with COVID-19 have reported a wide range of symptoms – from mild symptoms to severe illness. Symptoms may appear 2-14 days after exposure to the virus. If you have fever, cough, or other symptoms, you might have COVID-19."},{"id":449,"category":"Symptoms & Emergency Warning Signs","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"When should I seek emergency care if I have COVID-19?","response":"Look for emergency warning signs* for COVID-19. If someone is showing any of these signs, seek emergency medical care immediately\n\nTrouble breathing\nPersistent pain or pressure in the chest\nNew confusion\nInability to wake or stay awake\nPale, gray, or blue-colored skin, lips, or nail beds, depending on skin tone\n\n*This list is not all possible symptoms. Please call your medical provider for any other symptoms that are severe or concerning to you.\nCall 911 or call ahead to your local emergency facility: Notify the operator that you are seeking care for someone who has or may have COVID-19."},{"id":450,"category":"Symptoms & Emergency Warning Signs","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Is it possible to have the flu and COVID-19 at the same time?","response":"Yes. It is possible to test positive for flu (as well as other respiratory infections) and COVID-19 at the same time. Because some of the symptoms of flu and COVID-19 are similar, it may be hard to tell the difference between them based on symptoms alone. Testing may be needed to help confirm a diagnosis.\nThe best way to prevent seasonal flu is to get vaccinated every year. Flu vaccines will not prevent COVID-19, but they will reduce your chances of getting flu. See Prevent Seasonal Flu for more information."},{"id":451,"category":"Testing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Is at-home specimen collection or testing available?","response":"Yes. At-home testing and collection allow you to collect a specimen at home and either send it to a testing facility or preform the test at home.\nYou and your healthcare provider might consider either an at-home collection kit or an at-home test if you have signs and symptoms of COVID-19 or if you can’t get testing at a local healthcare facility.\nFor more information, see At-Home Testing."},{"id":452,"category":"Testing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Should I be tested for a current infection?","response":"The following should be tested for current infection:\n\nPeople who have symptoms of COVID-19.\nMost people who have had close contact (within 6 feet for a total of 15 minutes or more over a 24-hour period) with someone with confirmed COVID-19.\n\nFully vaccinated people with no COVID-19 symptoms do not need to be tested following an exposure to someone with COVID-19.\nPeople who have tested positive for COVID-19 within the past 3 months and recovered do not need to get tested following an exposure as long as they do not develop new symptoms.\n\n\nPeople who have taken part in activities that put them at higher risk for COVID-19 because they cannot physically distance as needed to avoid exposure such as travel, attending large social or mass gatherings, or being in crowded or poorly-ventilated indoor settings.\nPeople who have been asked or referred to get tested by their healthcare provider, or state, tribal, localexternal icon, or territorial health department.\n\nCDC recommends that anyone with any signs or symptoms of COVID-19 get tested, regardless of vaccination status or prior infection.  If you get tested because you have symptoms or were potentially exposed to the virus, you should stay away from others pending test results and follow the advice of your health care provider or a public health professional."},{"id":453,"category":"Testing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"How can I get tested for a current infection (viral test) and what does my test mean?","response":"A viral test checks specimens from your nose or your mouth  to find out if you are currently infected with SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19.\nContact your healthcare provider or visit your state, tribal, localexternal icon, and territorial health department’s website to find the latest local information on testing. The type of viral COVID-19 tests offered differ by location. You and your healthcare provider might also consider either an at-home collection kit or an at-home test if you have signs and symptoms of COVID-19 and if you are not able to be tested by a healthcare provider or public health official.\nWhile waiting for test results pdf icon[2 pages, 224KB], you should self-quarantine at home and stay away from others, including those living in your household. If your test results are positive, isolate yourself. If you have symptoms of COVID-19 or you have been in close contact with someone with COVID-19 and are not tested, it is still important to stay home.  For more information, visit What to Do if You Are Sick and When to Quarantine."},{"id":454,"category":"Testing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"How can I get tested for a past infection (antibody test) and what does my test mean?","response":"Antibody tests for COVID-19 are available through healthcare providers and laboratories. Check with your healthcare provider to see if they offer antibody tests and whether you should get one.\nA positive test result shows you might have antibodies from an infection with the virus that causes COVID-19. However, there is a chance a positive result means that you have antibodies from an infection with a virus from the same family of viruses (called coronaviruses), such as the one that causes the common cold.\nHaving antibodies to the virus that causes COVID-19 might provide some protection from getting infected with the virus again. If it does, we do not know how much protection the antibodies might provide or how long this protection might last. Confirmed and suspected cases of reinfection have been reported, but remain rare.\nYou should continue to protect yourself and others since you could get infected with the virus again.\nIf you test negative, you might not have ever had COVID-19. Talk with your healthcare provider about your test result and the type of test you took to understand what your result means.\nRegardless of whether you test positive or negative, the results do not confirm whether or not you are able to spread the virus that causes COVID-19. Until we know more, continue to take steps to protect yourself and others.\nIf you want more information about antibody tests, see Test for Past Infection."},{"id":455,"category":"Testing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can someone test negative and later test positive on a viral test for COVID-19?","response":"Yes, it is possible. You may test negative if the sample was collected early in your infection and test positive later during this illness. You could also be exposed to COVID-19 after the test and get infected then. Even if you test negative, you still should take steps to protect yourself and others. See Testing for Current Infection for more information."},{"id":456,"category":"People at Higher Risk for Severe Illness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Who is at increased risk for developing severe illness from COVID-19?","response":"People at increased risk include:\n\nOlder adults\nPeople of all ages with certain underlying medical conditions\n\nPregnant and recently pregnant people are also at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19.\nLong-standing systemic health and social inequities have put many people from racial and ethnic minority groups at increased risk of getting sick and dying from COVID-19.\nIn addition to those at increased risk, there are certain groups of people who require extra precautions during the pandemic."},{"id":457,"category":"People at Higher Risk for Severe Illness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Are there any medications I should avoid taking if I have COVID-19?","response":"Currently, there is no evidence to suggest that taking any specific medications, like blood pressure medication or ibuprofen, leads to more severe illness from COVID-19.\n\nContinue to take your medications and to follow your treatment plan as prescribed by your healthcare provider. Any changes to your medications should only be made after talking with your healthcare provider.\nContact your healthcare provider if you have questions or concerns.\n\nFor more information, see People with Underlying Medical Conditions."},{"id":458,"category":"People at Higher Risk for Severe Illness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Are people with disabilities at higher risk?","response":"Adults with disabilities are more likely to have an underlying medical condition that may put them at increased risk of severe illness from COVID-19 including, but not limited to, heart disease, stroke, diabetes, chronic kidney disease, cancer, high blood pressure, and obesity. In addition, having a disability may make it harder to practice social distancing, wear a mask, and practice hand hygiene.\nFor more information, see People with Disabilities and People who May Need Extra Precautions."},{"id":459,"category":"People with Seasonal Allergies","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What is the difference between COVID-19 and seasonal allergies?","response":"COVID-19 is a contagious respiratory illness caused by infection with a new coronavirus (called SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19). Seasonal allergies triggered by airborne pollen can lead to seasonal allergic rhinitis, which affects the nose and sinuses, and seasonal allergic conjunctivitis, which affects the eyes.\nCOVID-19 and seasonal allergies share many symptoms, but there are some key differences between the two. For example, COVID-19 can cause fever, which is not a common symptom of seasonal allergies. The image below compares symptoms caused by allergies and COVID-19.\nBecause some of the symptoms of COVID-19 and seasonal allergies are similar, it may be difficult to tell the difference between them, and you may need to get a test to confirm your diagnosis\n\n508 version\n*Seasonal allergies do not usually cause shortness of breath or difficulty breathing, unless a person has a respiratory condition such as asthma that can be triggered by exposure to pollen.\nThis is not a complete list of all possible symptoms of COVID-19 or seasonal allergies. Symptoms vary from person to person and range from mild to severe. You can have symptoms of both COVID-19 and seasonal allergies at the same time.\nIf you think you have COVID-19, follow CDC’s guidance on ”What to do if you are sick.” If you have an emergency warning sign (including trouble breathing), seek emergency medical care immediately.\nGet more information on COVID-19 symptoms, or more information on seasonal allergy symptomsexternal icon."},{"id":460,"category":"People with Seasonal Allergies","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Does having seasonal allergies increase my risk of contracting COVID-19 or having more severe symptoms if I do contract COVID-19?","response":"There is not enough scientific information at this time to know whether having seasonal allergies puts you at higher risk of contracting COVID-19 or having more severe symptoms if you do contract COVID-19. We do know that older adults and people who have severe underlying medical conditions like obesity, diabetes, or heart or lung disease are at higher risk for developing more serious complications when they have COVID-19. Get more information on people at high risk for severe COVID-19."},{"id":461,"category":"People with Seasonal Allergies","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Will I be protected from seasonal allergies if I wear a mask?","response":"CDC recommends wearing masks to slow the spread of COVID-19. Everyone should wear a mask covering unless they are under 2 years of age, have breathing problems, or are unconscious or incapacitated and would need assistance removing a mask.  Masks also offer some protection against seasonal allergies because they can prevent some larger particles from being inhaled. However, if you have seasonal allergies, masks should not be your only protection against pollen exposure because smaller particles can still get through the covering and be inhaled.\nWash your masks after each use, particularly if you suffer from seasonal allergies, because the covering may carry particles such as pollen. See information on how to wash masks."},{"id":462,"category":"People with Seasonal Allergies","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"How can I protect myself from seasonal allergies?","response":"The best way to protect yourself against seasonal allergies is to reduce your exposure to pollen. During high pollen days:\n\nLimit your time outdoors and seek indoor spaces with clean air.\nCreate a cleaner air space at home to protect yourself from outdoor air irritants during the COVID-19 pandemic. Use a portable air cleaner in one or more rooms. Portable air cleaners work best when run continuously with doors and windows closed. Do-it-yourself box fan filtration units are a low-cost filtration alternative, but they should never be left unattended.\nKeep your cleaner air space a comfortable temperature by using air conditioners, heat pumps, fans, and window shades.\nIf you have a forced air system in your home, consult a qualified heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) professional about different filters (HEPA or MERV-13 or higher) and settings (“Recirculate” and “On” rather than “Auto”) that can be used to reduce indoor air irritants.\nIf outdoors, avoid activities that stir up pollen, such as mowing lawns or raking leaves. When you return indoors, take a shower and change your clothes.\n\nThe EPA website on indoor air and COVID-19external icon and the EPA Guide to Air Cleaners in the Home pdf icon[7 pages, 2.93mb]external icon provide additional information on improving indoor air quality. You can also find out the daily pollen levels in your area by checking local weather forecasts and pollen counting stationsexternal icon. Learn more about reducing your exposure to respiratory triggers."},{"id":463,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What is contact tracing?","response":"Contact tracing has been used for decades by state and local health departments to slow or stop the spread of infectious diseases.\nContact tracing slows the spread of COVID-19 by\n\nLetting people know they may have been exposed to COVID-19 and should monitor their health for signs and symptoms of COVID-19\nHelping people who may have been exposed to COVID-19 get tested\nAsking people to self-isolate if they have COVID-19 or self-quarantine if they are a close contact of someone with COVID-19\n\nDuring contact tracing, the health department staff will not ask you for\n\nMoney\nSocial Security number\nBank account information\nSalary information\nCredit card numbers"},{"id":464,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What will happen with my personal information during contact tracing?","response":"Discussions with health department staff are confidential. This means that your personal and medical information will be kept private and only shared with those who may need to know, like your health care provider.\nIf you have been diagnosed with COVID-19, your name will not be shared with those you came in contact with. The health department will only notify people you were in close contact with that they might have been exposed to COVID-19. Each state and jurisdiction use their own method for collecting and protecting health information. To learn more, contact your state or local health department.\nYou may also be interested in: If I participate contact tracing for COVID-19 using a digital tool, is my personal health information secure?"},{"id":465,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Who is considered a close contact of someone with COVID-19?","response":"For COVID-19, a close contact is anyone who was within 6 feet of an infected person for a total of 15 minutes or more over a 24-hour period (for example, three individual 5-minute exposures for a total of 15 minutes). An infected person can spread COVID-19 starting from 2 days before they have any symptoms (or, if they are asymptomatic, 2 days before their specimen that tested positive was collected), until they meet the criteria for discontinuing home isolation.\nYou may also be interested in: What should I do if I have had close contact with someone who has COVID-19?"},{"id":466,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"I have COVID-19. How do I tell the people I was around?","response":"If you have COVID-19, tell your close contacts pdf icon[93 KB, 2 Pages] you have COVID-19 so that they can quarantine at home and get tested. By letting your close contacts know they may have been exposed to COVID-19, you are helping to protect them and others within your community.\nYou can call, text, or email your contacts. If you would like to stay anonymous, there is also an online tool that allows you to tell your contacts by sending out emails or text notifications anonymously (www.tellyourcontacts.orgexternal icon)."},{"id":467,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Does mask use help determine if someone is considered a close contact?","response":"A person is still considered a close contact even if one or both people wore a mask when they were together.\nMasks work best when everyone wears one. However, masks are not 100% effective at preventing spread of COVID-19, and the type of masks used and whether or not they are used consistently and correctly varies throughout the general population. Therefore, mask use is not considered when determining whether someone is a close contact during case investigation and contact tracing."},{"id":468,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"If I am a close contact, will I be tested for COVID-19?","response":"If you have been in close contact with someone who has COVID-19, you should be tested, even if you do not have symptoms of COVID-19. The health department may be able to provide resources for testing in your area.\n\nWhile you are waiting for your COVID-19 test result, stay home away from others (self-quarantine) and monitor your health for symptoms of COVID-19 to protect your friends, family, and others from possibly getting COVID-19.\nIf your test is positive, you should continue to stay home and self-isolate away from others and monitor your health. If you have symptoms of COVID-19 and they worsen or become severe, you should seek emergency medical care. Severe symptoms include trouble breathing, persistent pain or pressure in the chest, confusion, inability to wake or stay awake, or pale, gray, or blue-colored skin, lips, or nail beds, depending on skin tone. Someone from the health department may call you to\n\nCheck on your health,\nDiscuss who you have been around, and\nAsk where you have spent time while you may have been able to spread COVID-19 to others.\n\n\nThe best way to protect yourself and others is to stay home for 14 days if you think you’ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department’s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period.\nIf your test is negative and you don’t have symptoms, you should continue to stay home and self-quarantine away from others for 14 days after your last exposure to COVID-19 and follow all recommendations from the health department. This is important because symptoms can appear up to 14 days after you’ve been exposed and are infected. A negative result before the end of your quarantine period does not rule out possible infection. Additionally, you do not need a repeat test unless you develop symptoms, or if you require a test to return to work.\nIf your test is negative and you have symptoms, you should continue to self-quarantine away from others for 14 days after your last exposure to COVID-19 and follow all recommendations from the health department. Additional medical consultation and a second test may be needed if your symptoms do not improve."},{"id":469,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What will happen during contact tracing if I am diagnosed with COVID-19?","response":"If you are diagnosed with COVID-19, someone from the health department may call you to check on your health, discuss who you have been around, and ask where you spent time while you may have been able to spread COVID-19 to others. You will also be asked to continue to stay at home and self-isolate, away from others.\n\nYour name will not be shared with those you came in contact with.\nThe health department staff will not ask you for\n\nMoney\nSocial Security number\nBank account information\nSalary information, or\nCredit card numbers\n\n\nSelf-isolation means staying at home in a specific room away from other people and pets, and using a separate bathroom, if possible.\nSelf-isolation helps slow the spread of COVID-19 and can help protect the health of your family, friends, neighbors, and others you may come in contact.\nIf you need support or assistance while in self-isolation, your health department or community organizations may be able to provide assistance.\n\nWatch for or monitor your symptoms of COVID-19. If your symptoms worsen or become severe, you should seek medical care."},{"id":470,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What will happen during contact tracing if I have been around someone with COVID-19?","response":"If you were around someone who has been diagnosed with COVID-19, someone from the health department may call you to let you know that you may have been exposed to COVID-19.\nThe best way to protect yourself and others is to stay home for 14 days if you think you’ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department’s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period. Health department staff will help identify the dates for your self-quarantine. Health department staff can also provide resources for COVID-19 testing in your area.\n\nSelf-quarantine means staying home away from others and monitoring your health.\nIf you need to be around other people or animals in or outside of the home, wear a mask. This will help protect the people around you.\nIf you need support or assistance while in self-quarantine, your health department or community organizations may be able to provide assistance.\n\nMonitor your health and watch for symptoms of COVID-19. Remember, symptoms may appear 2-14 days after you were exposed to COVID-19. Tell the health department if you develop any symptoms. Tell people you were around recently if you become ill, so they can monitor their health. If your symptoms worsen or become severe, seek medical care. Severe symptoms include trouble breathing, persistent pain or pressure in the chest, new confusion, inability to wake or stay awake, or pale, gray, or blue-colored skin, lips, or nail beds, depending on skin tone.\nThe health department staff will not ask you for\n\nMoney\nSocial Security number\nBank account information\nSalary information, or\nCredit card numbers"},{"id":471,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"I was around someone who has COVID-19, and my COVID-19 test came back negative. Do I still need to quarantine for 14 days after I was last exposed?","response":"Yes. You should still self-quarantine for 14 days since your last exposure. It can take up to 14 days after exposure to the virus for a person to develop COVID-19 symptoms. A negative result before end of the 14-day quarantine period does not rule out possible infection. By self-quarantining for 14 days, you lower the chance of possibly exposing others to COVID-19. The best way to protect yourself and others is to stay home for 14 days if you think you’ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department’s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period."},{"id":472,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"I was recently around someone who has COVID-19, but I feel fine. Why should I stay at home?","response":"People with COVID-19 can still spread the virus even if they don’t have any symptoms. If you were around someone who had COVID-19, it is critical that you stay home and away from others for 14 days from the last day that you were around that person. Staying home and away from others at all times helps your health department in the fight against COVID-19 and helps protect you, your family, and your community. The best way to protect yourself and others is to stay home for 14 days if you think you’ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department’s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period."},{"id":473,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What if I have been around someone who was identified as a close contact?","response":"The best way to protect yourself and others is to quarantine by staying home for 14 days if you think you’ve been exposed to someone who has COVID-19. Check your local health department’s website for information about options in your area to possibly shorten this quarantine period.\nBe alert for symptoms of COVID-19.\nIf possible, stay away from others, especially people who are at higher risk for getting very sick from COVID-19.\nYou may NOT need to quarantine if:\n\nYou have been fully vaccinated and have no symptoms\nYou were previously diagnosed with COVID-19 within the last three months and don’t develop any new symptoms"},{"id":474,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Will there be a national app for contact tracing?","response":"No, there will not be a national app for contact tracing. There are many options available now, and it is up to each state and individual to decide which tools best fit their needs."},{"id":475,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"If I participate in contact tracing for COVID-19 using a digital tool, is my personal health information secure?","response":"Yes, if you agree to participate in contact tracing for COVID-19 with the health department, your information is secure.\nDiscussions with health department staff are confidential. This means that your personal and medical information will be kept private and only shared with those who may need to know, like your health care provider. Your name will not be shared with those you came in contact with. If you have been diagnosed with COVID-19, the health department will only notify people you were in close contact with that they might have been exposed to COVID-19.\nHealth departments may use case management tools to help make the contact tracing process more efficient. If you choose to provide information through one of these tools, your information is secure and stored with the health department. These tools also help health departments quickly receive and analyze information about COVID-19. Case management tools are under the same laws and regulations for all sensitive health information use (e.g. HIPPA). You must provide consent for the health department to collect information using a case management tool. Just like traditional contact tracing, digital tools will not collect information regarding money, Social Security numbers, bank account information, salary information, or credit card numbers.\nExposure notification tools may be an app that you can download on your personal cell phone. If you choose to download an exposure notification app for COVID-19, your information is secure. Exposure notification apps are developed in collaboration with or endorsed by health departments. These apps undergo rigorous testing to determine their trustworthiness, security, and ability to protect people’s privacy. Until you give consent to share information with your local health department, any information you have entered into the app is stored only on your personal phone. Your information is stored only on your own phone and is not sent to the health department or any other third party. The app and your information can be deleted any time. When you consent to share your information with the local health department, your information is secure."},{"id":476,"category":"Contact Tracing","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Will I be required to download a contact tracing app for COVID-19 on my phone?","response":"No, you are not required to download an app to give information for contact tracing for COVID-19. Health departments commonly use case management tools to make the contact tracing process more efficient. These types of tools are not downloaded on personal cell phones.\nIf you choose to give information to your local or state health department for contact tracing for COVID-19, you do not need to download an app on your cell phone. The health department staff may call you to\n\nCheck on your health,\nDiscuss who you have been around, and\nAsk where you have spent time while you may have been able to spread COVID-19 to others.\n\nIt is up to you to decide if you download an exposure notification app for COVID-19."},{"id":477,"category":"Funerals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Am I at risk if I go to a funeral or visitation service for someone who died of COVID-19?","response":"There is currently no known risk associated with being in the same room at a funeral or visitation service with the body of someone who died of COVID-19. However, you may be at risk of getting COVID-19 if you attend a funeral where there are multiple people congregating. For more information about what you can do to help protect yourself and others from COVID-19 during these services, and to help cope with the loss of a loved one, see Funeral Guidance."},{"id":478,"category":"Funerals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What should loved ones know about handling belongings and the body of someone who died from COVID-19?","response":"The virus that causes COVID-19 is thought to spread from close contact (i.e., within about 6 feet) with a person who is infected with the virus. The virus spreads primarily through respiratory droplets produced when an infected person coughs, sneezes, or talks.\nThis type of spread is not a concern after death. It may be possible that a person can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes, but this is not thought to be the main way the virus spreads. If the deceased person had confirmed or suspected COVID-19, avoid kissing, washing, or shrouding the body before, during, and after the body has been prepared, if possible. For more information on recommended precautions while handling the belongings and the body of someone who died from COVID-19, see Funeral Guidance."},{"id":479,"category":"Cleaning and Disinfection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Do disinfectants kill new strains of COVID-19?","response":"CDC, in collaboration with EPAexternal icon, expects all products on List N: Disinfectants for Coronavirus (COVID-19)external icon to kill all strains of SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19.\nGenetic mutations to COVID-19 do not impact the effectiveness of disinfectants. Destroying a virus is dependent on its physical properties, and recent genetic changes have not changed the basic physical properties of the virus that causes COVID-19.​\nLearn more about cleaning and disinfection recommendations for facilities and homes."},{"id":480,"category":"Cleaning and Disinfection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Do car seats and booster seats need extra cleaning and disinfection to prevent spread of COVID-19? If so, how should car seats and booster seats be cleaned and disinfected?","response":"It may be possible that people can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes, but this isn’t thought to be the main way the virus spreads. Cleaning with products containing soap or detergent reduces germs on surfaces and objects by removing contaminants and may weaken or damage some of the virus particles, which decreases risk of infection from surfaces. You may choose to also disinfect depending on certain conditions or everyday practices required by your home. Washing hands frequently or using hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol also prevent the spread of COVID-19.\nSome cleaning and disinfectexternal icon products are not recommended for use on car seats and booster seats. Owners should follow the manufacturer’s cleaning instructions for their car seats and booster seats."},{"id":481,"category":"Cleaning and Disinfection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What is the difference between cleaning and disinfecting?","response":"Cleaning with soap and water or a detergent removes germs, dirt, and impurities from surfaces. It lowers the risk of spreading infection. Disinfecting with a household disinfectant on List N: Disinfectants for Coronavirus (COVID-19)external icon kills germs on the surface. By disinfecting or killing germs on a surface after cleaning the surface, it can further lower the risk of spreading infection. For more information review cleaning and disinfection recommendations for facilities and homes."},{"id":482,"category":"Cleaning and Disinfection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Is it safe to vacuum in a school, business, or community facility after someone with COVID-19 was there?","response":"The risk of spreading COVID-19 during vacuuming is unknown. At this time, there are no reported cases of COVID-19 associated with vacuuming.\n\nAfter cleaning:\n\nUse a vacuum equipped with a high-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filter and bags, if available.\nDo not vacuum a room or space that has people in it. Wait until the room or space is empty to vacuum, such as at night, for common spaces, or during the day for private rooms.\nWhile vacuuming, temporarily turn off in-room, window-mounted, or on-wall recirculation HVAC to avoid contamination of the HVAC units.\nDo NOT deactivate central HVAC systems. These systems tend to provide better filtration capabilities and introduce outdoor air into the areas that they serve."},{"id":483,"category":"Cleaning and Disinfection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"How effective are alternative disinfection methods, such as ultrasonic waves, high intensity UV radiation, and LED blue light?","response":"The efficacy of these disinfection methods against the virus that causes COVID-19 is not known. EPA only recommends use of the surface disinfectants identified on List Nexternal icon against the virus that causes COVID-19. EPA does not routinely review the safety or efficacy of pesticidal devices, such as UV lights, LED lights, or ultrasonic devices. However, CDC is producing guidance on use of Germicidal ultraviolet as an alternative disinfection method. Therefore, EPA cannot confirm whether, or under what circumstances, such products might be effective against the spread of COVID-19. For more information on CDC’s recommendations for primary surface disinfection in occupied environments please visit the CDC/EPA guidance for surface disinfection."},{"id":484,"category":"Cleaning and Disinfection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can sanitizing tunnels be used at facility entrances or exits to prevent the spread of COVID-19?","response":"CDC does not recommend the use of sanitizing tunnels. There is no evidence that they are effective in reducing the spread of COVID-19. In addition, chemicals used in sanitizing tunnels could cause skin, eye, or respiratory irritation or damage."},{"id":485,"category":"Cleaning and Disinfection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Should sidewalks, roads, and other outdoor spaces be disinfected to prevent the spread of COVID-19?","response":"CDC does not recommend disinfection of sidewalks, roads, or most other outdoor spaces. Spraying disinfectant on sidewalks, roads, and other outdoor spaces is not an efficient use of disinfectant supplies and has not been proven to reduce the risk of COVID-19 to the public. The risk of spreading the virus that causes COVID-19 from these surfaces is very low and disinfection is not effective on these surfaces."},{"id":486,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can I get COVID-19 from my pets or other animals?","response":"Based on the available information to date, the risk of animals spreading COVID-19 to people is considered to be low. See If You Have Pets for more information about pets and COVID-19.\nHowever, since animals can spread other diseases to people, it’s always a good idea to practice healthy habits around pets and other animals, such as washing your hands and maintaining good hygiene. For more information on the many benefits of pet ownership, as well as staying safe and healthy around animals including pets, livestock, and wildlife, visit CDC’s Healthy Pets, Healthy People website."},{"id":487,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can animals carry the virus that causes COVID-19 on their skin or fur?","response":"Although we know certain bacteria and fungi can be carried on fur and hair, there is no evidence that viruses, including the virus that causes COVID-19, can spread to people from the skin, fur, or hair of pets.\nHowever, because animals can sometimes carry other germs that can make people sick, it’s always a good idea to practice healthy habits around pets and other animals, including washing hands before and after interacting with them."},{"id":488,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can I use hand sanitizer on pets?","response":"Do not wipe or bathe your pet with chemical disinfectants, alcohol, hydrogen peroxide, or other products, such as hand sanitizer, counter-cleaning wipes, or other industrial or surface cleaners. If you have questions about appropriate products for bathing or cleaning your pet, talk to your veterinarian. If your pet gets hand sanitizer on their skin or fur, rinse or wipe down your pet with water immediately. If your pet ingests hand sanitizer (such as by chewing the bottle) or is showing signs of illness after use, contact your veterinarian or pet poison control immediately."},{"id":489,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can I take my dog to a dog park?","response":"Dog parks provide socialization and exercise for dogs, which is an important part of their wellbeing. Because there is a risk that people with COVID-19 could spread it to animals, CDC recommends that you do not let pets interact with people outside of your household, especially in places with community spread of COVID-19. Therefore, you should consider avoiding dog parks or other places where large numbers of people and dogs gather.\nSome areas are allowing dog parks to open. If you choose to go to a dog park, follow local guidelines. There are ways to reduce the risk of you or your dog getting infected with COVID-19 if you go to a dog park.\n\nDo not take your dog to a dog park if you are sick or if you have recently been in close contact with a person with COVID-19.\nDo not take your dog to a dog park if your dog is sick. Signs of sickness in dogs may include fever, coughing, difficulty breathing or shortness of breath, lethargy, sneezing, discharge from the nose or eyes, vomiting, or diarrhea.\nIf your dog has tested positive for the virus that causes COVID-19, talk to your veterinarian about when it is appropriate for your pet to go back to normal activities.\nTry to limit your dog’s interaction with other people outside of your household while at the dog park.\nAs much as possible, avoid touching common items in the dog park like water bowls. Wash your hands or use hand sanitizer after touching items from the park. To make sure your dog has fresh water, consider bringing your own portable water bowl.\nLimit other pet items brought to the dog park, such as toys. Clean and disinfect anything taken to the park and returned home (leashes, toys, water bowls).\nDo not wipe or bathe your dog with chemical disinfectants, alcohol, hydrogen peroxide, or other products, such as hand sanitizer, counter-cleaning wipes, or other industrial or surface cleaners. If you have questions about appropriate products for bathing or cleaning your pet, talk to your veterinarian.\n\nSee more information on pets and COVID-19 and recommendations for how to help keep your pet safe."},{"id":490,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can I take my dog to daycare or a groomer?","response":"Until we know more about how this virus affects animals, CDC encourages pet owners to treat pets as you would other human family members to protect them from possible infection. This means limiting contact between your pets and people outside your household as much as possible and avoiding places where large numbers of people gather.\nSome areas are allowing groomers and boarding facilities such as dog daycares to open. If you must take your pet to a groomer or boarding facility, follow any protocols put into place at the facility, such as wearing a mask and maintaining at least 6 feet of space between yourself and others if possible.\nLimit pet items brought from home to the groomer or boarding facility, and disinfect any objects that are taken into a facility and returned home (such as leashes, bowls, and toys). Use an EPA-registered disinfectantexternal icon to clean items and rinse thoroughly with clean water afterwards. Do not wipe or bathe your pet with chemical disinfectants, alcohol, hydrogen peroxide, or other products, such as hand sanitizer, counter-cleaning wipes, or other industrial or surface cleaners. If you have questions about appropriate products for bathing or cleaning your pet, talk to your veterinarian.\nDo not put masks on pets, and do not take a sick pet to a groomer or boarding facility. Signs of sickness in dogs may include fever, coughing, difficulty breathing or shortness of breath, lethargy, sneezing, discharge from the nose or eyes, vomiting, or diarrhea. If you think your pet is sick, call your veterinarian. Some veterinarians may offer telemedicine consultations or other plans for seeing sick pets. Your veterinarian can evaluate your pet and determine the next steps for your pet’s treatment and care.\nSee more information on pets and COVID-19 and recommendations for how to help keep your pet safe."},{"id":491,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What should I do if my pet gets sick and I think it’s COVID-19?","response":"Most pets that have gotten sick from the virus that causes COVID-19 were infected after close contact with a person with COVID-19. Talk to your veterinarian about any health concerns you have about your pets.\nIf your pet gets sick after contact with a person with COVID-19, call your veterinarian and let them know the pet was around a person with COVID-19. If you are sick with COVID-19, do not take your pet to the veterinary clinic yourself. Some veterinarians may offer telemedicine consultations or other plans for seeing sick pets. Your veterinarian can evaluate your pet and determine the next steps for your pet’s treatment and care. Routine testing of animals for COVID-19 is not recommended at this time."},{"id":492,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What should I do if there are pets at my long-term care facility or assisted living facility?","response":"Based on the available information to date, the risk of animals spreading COVID-19 to people is considered to be low. However, it appears that the virus that causes COVID-19 can spread from people to animals after close contact with people with COVID-19.\nUntil we learn more about how this virus affects animals, use similar precautions for pets and other animals in your facility as you would for other people in your facility. This will help protect both people and pets in your facility from COVID-19.\n\nDo not let pets in the facility interact with sick people.\nPets or other animals should not be allowed to roam freely around the facility, and cats should be kept indoors.\nResidents should avoid letting their pets interact with people as much as possible.\nDogs should be walked on a leash at least 6 feet (2 meters) away from others.\nPeople sick with COVID-19 should avoid contact with pets and other animals.\nDo not allow pets into common areas of the facility such as cafeterias and social areas.\n\nTalk to a veterinarian if a pet in your facility gets sick or if you have any concerns about the health of any pets in the facility. If you think a pet in the facility was exposed to or is showing signs consistent with COVID-19, contact your state health official to discuss guidance on testing pets or other animals for the virus that causes COVID-19.\nPeople who are at higher risk for severe illness from COVID-19 should avoid providing care for sick pets, if possible.\nFor more information, visit CDC’s If You Have Pets webpage."},{"id":493,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Are imported animals or animal products safe?","response":"CDC does not have any evidence to suggest that imported animals or animal products pose a risk for spreading COVID-19 in the United States. This is a rapidly evolving situation and information will be updated as it becomes available. CDC, the U. S. Department of Agriculture (USDA), and the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (FWS) play distinct but complementary roles in regulating the importation of live animals and animal products into the United States.\n\nCDC regulates animals and animal products that pose a threat to human health,\nUSDA regulatesexternal icon animals and animal products that pose a threat to agriculture; and\nFWS regulatesexternal icon importation of endangered species and wildlife that can harm the health and welfare of humans, the interests of agriculture, horticulture, or forestry, and the welfare and survival of wildlife resources."},{"id":494,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can I travel to the United States with dogs or import dogs into the United States during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"Beginning July 14, 2021, there is a temporary suspension for dogs imported from countries that CDC considers high risk for dog rabies. Please refer to CDC’s requirements for bringing a dog into the United States."},{"id":495,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What precautions should be taken for animals that have recently been imported from outside the United States (for example, by shelters, rescues, or as personal pets)?","response":"Imported animals will need to meet CDC and USDA’sexternal iconexternal icon requirements for entering the United States. At this time, there is no evidence that companion animals, including pets and service animals, can spread the virus that causes COVID-19. As with any animal introduced to a new environment, animals recently imported should be observed daily for signs of illness. If an animal becomes ill, the animal should be examined by a veterinarian. Call your local veterinary clinic before bringing the animal into the clinic and let them know that the animal was recently imported from another country.\nThis is a rapidly evolving situation and information will be updated as it becomes available."},{"id":496,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can wild animals spread the virus that causes COVID-19 to people or pets?","response":"Currently, there is no evidence to suggest the virus that causes COVID-19 is circulating in free-living wildlife in the United States, or that wildlife might be a source of infection for people in the United States.\nIf a wild animal were to become infected with the virus, we don’t know whether the infection could then spread among wildlife or if it could spread to other animals, including pets. Further studies are needed to understand if and how different animals, including wildlife, could be affected by COVID-19. Because wildlife can carry other diseases, even without looking sick, it is always important to enjoy wildlife from a distance.\nTake steps to prevent getting sick from wildlife in the United States:\n\nKeep your family, including pets, a safe distance away from wildlife.\nDo not feed wildlife or touch wildlife droppings.\nAlways wash your hands and supervise children washing their hands after working or playing outside.\nLeave orphaned animals alone. Often, the parents are close by and will return for their young.\nConsult your state wildlife agency’s guidance if you are preparing or consuming legally harvested game meat.\nDo not approach or touch a sick or dead animal – contact your state wildlife agency instead.\n\nSee COVID-19 and Animals for more information."},{"id":497,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can bats in United States get the virus that causes COVID-19, and can they spread it back to people?","response":"Other coronaviruses have been found in North American bats in the past, but there is currently no evidence that the virus that causes COVID-19 is present in any free-living wildlife in the United States, including bats. In general, coronaviruses do not cause illness or death in bats, but we don’t yet know if this new coronavirus would make North American species of bats sick. Bats are an important part of natural ecosystems, and their populations are already declining in the United States. Bat populations could be further threatened by the disease itself or by harm inflicted on bats resulting from a misconception that bats are spreading COVID-19. However, there is no evidence that bats in the United States are a source of the virus that causes COVID-19 for people. Further studies are needed to understand if and how bats could be affected by COVID-19."},{"id":498,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Is hunter-harvested game meat safe to eat during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"Currently, there is no evidence that you can get infected with the virus that causes COVID-19 by eating food, including wild hunted game meat. However, hunters can get infected with other diseases when processing or eating game.  Hunters should always practice good hygiene when processing animals by following these food safety recommendations:\n\nDo not harvest animals that appear sick or are found dead.\nKeep game meat clean and cool the meat down as soon as possible after harvesting the animal.\nAvoid cutting through the backbone and spinal tissues and do not eat the brains of any wild animal.\nWhen handling and cleaning game:\n\nWear rubber or disposable gloves.\nDo not eat, drink, or smoke.\n\n\nWhen finished handling and cleaning game:\n\nWash your hands thoroughly with soap and water.\nClean knives, equipment, and surfaces that were in contact with game meat with soap and water and then disinfect them. While these recommendations apply to general food safety practices, if you are concerned about COVID-19, you may use a product on the EPA list of disinfectants for use against the COVID-19 virusexternal icon.\n\n\nCook all game meat thoroughly (to an internal temperature of 165°F or higher).\nCheck with your state wildlife agency regarding any testing requirements for other diseases and for any specific instructions regarding preparing, transporting, and consuming game meat."},{"id":499,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"How can I safely run my equestrian facility?","response":"You should follow your state and/or local jurisdictional guidance regarding continuing operations at your facility. There have not been any reports of horses testing positive for the virus that causes COVID-19. Based on the limited information available to date, the risk of animals spreading the virus that causes COVID-19 to people is considered to be low. COVID-19 is primarily spread from person to person, so steps should be taken to reduce the risks for people visiting your facility.\n\nEncourage employees and other visitors, including boarders, owners, farriers, veterinarians, and those taking lessons, not to enter the facility if they are sick. Employees should not return to work until the criteria to discontinue home isolation are met, after talking with their doctor. Implement sick leave policies that are flexible, nonpunitive, and consistent with public health guidance, allowing employees to stay home if they have symptoms of respiratory infection.\nConsider conducting daily health checks (e.g., symptom and/or temperature screening) of employees and others visiting the facility before they enter the premises. People with a fever of 100.40(38.00C) or above or other signs of illness should not be admitted to the premises. If implementing health checks, conduct them safely and respectfully. See General Business FAQs for more information.\n\nEmployees or visitors who appear to have symptoms upon arrival or who become sick during their visit should immediately be separated from other employees and visitors and sent home.\n\n\nLimit the number of people entering the facility. Consider staggering lesson and visiting times to limit the number of people in the facility and potential for person-to-person contact. If possible, you can also take steps to decrease high-traffic areas by limiting areas open to visitors/owners or staggering use of common areas like grooming or wash stalls and tack rooms.\nIncrease distance and limit duration of contact between employees and visitors in the facility. Whenever possible, people should maintain at least 6 feet of distance between each other at the facility, including instructors teaching lessons. Allow for social distancing and avoid large numbers of people within the facility, including in employee-only areas.\nVisitors and employees should wear masks especially where social distancing measures are difficult to maintain. Masks offer some protection to the wearer and are also meant to protect those around the wearer, in case they are infected with the virus that causes COVID-19. Wearing a mask does NOT replace the need to practice social distancing.\nSet up hand hygiene stations at the entrance and within the facility, so that employees and people entering can clean their hands before they enter. Employees should wash hands regularly with soap and water for at least 20 seconds. An alcohol-based hand sanitizer containing at least 60% alcohol can be used, but if hands are visibly dirty, they should be washed with soap and water before using an alcohol-based hand sanitizer. Examples of hand hygiene stations may be a hose and soap located at entrances to allow for handwashing before entry.\nCleaning high touch surfaces and shared objects once a day is usually enough to sufficiently remove virus that may be on surfaces unless someone with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 has been in the equestrian facility. Disinfecting (using disinfectants on U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)’s List Nexternal icon) removes any remaining germs on surfaces, which further reduces any risk of spreading infection.  For more information on cleaning regularly and cleaning when someone is sick, see Cleaning and Disinfecting Your Facility.\nFollow local guidance on shelter in place and travel recommendations when traveling for showing, training, or trail riding.\nIf traveling to a new facility, limit contact between people, horses, tack, equipment, and other supplies from different facilities, and maintain a distance of at least 6 feet between horses and riders.\n\nFollow state and local guidance on travel. People who are sick should not travel to other facilities.\nPeople visiting other facilities should follow the same precautions as they would normally, including maintaining at least 6 feet of distance between each other, wearing a mask to protect others, and washing hands frequently with soap and water.\n\n\nIf other animals, such as barn cats, are present at the facility, be aware that a small number of pets have been reported to be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19, mostly after contact with people with COVID-19.\n\nFor more information, see Guidance on Preparing Workplaces for COVID-19 pdf icon[35 pages, 1.4mb]external icon and Interim Guidance for Businesses and Employers to Plan and Respond to Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19)."},{"id":500,"category":"Pets and Animals","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can the virus that causes COVID-19 get back into the environment from wastewater and infect wildlife?","response":"SARS-CoV-2 (the virus that causes COVID-19) can be shed in the feces of people with COVID-19. Genetic material from SARS-CoV-2 has been found in untreated wastewater. However, while data are limited, there is little evidence of infectious virus in wastewater, and no information to date that anyone has become sick with COVID-19 because of exposure to wastewater. It is possible that wildlife could become infected with SARS-CoV-2 from contact with untreated wastewater, but evidence from studies of virus infectivity in feces and survival in wastewater suggests that this transmission route is unlikely to occur."},{"id":501,"category":"Community Mitigation","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What is community mitigation?","response":"Community mitigation is a set of actions that people and communities can take to slow the spread of infectious diseases like COVID-19. The goal of community mitigation in areas with local COVID-19 transmission is to slow its spread and to protect all individuals, especially those at increased risk for severe illness, while minimizing the negative impacts of these strategies. For more information, see Community Mitigation Framework."},{"id":502,"category":"Community Mitigation","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"What are community mitigation actions for COVID-19?","response":"There are several actions that individuals and communities can take to help reduce the chance that they, their families and friends, and their communities get COVID-19. In general, the more cases spreading in your community, the more likely it will spread to you or your family. Also, the more people an individual interacts with, and the longer each interaction lasts, the higher the risk of viral spread. Location can be a factor, too, with outdoor activities generally being less risky than indoor activities.\n Individuals can take the following community mitigation actions:\n\nWear a mask (with some exceptions) when in public settings or around others not living in the same household\nFollow healthy hygiene practices, such as frequent hand washing\nPractice social distancing\nStay home when sick\nClean frequently touched surfaces daily\n\nCommunities can take the following actions:\n\nPromote behaviors that prevent spread\nMaintain healthy environments\nEnsure institutions in the community are practicing appropriate precautions\nPrepare for when someone gets sick\nClose businesses and schools, and limit other services\n\nFor more information, see Community Guidance, Community Mitigation, and Community Mitigation Framework."},{"id":503,"category":"Food and Water","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can I get COVID-19 from food (including restaurant take-out, produce, refrigerated, or packaged food) or drinking water?","response":"Currently there is no evidence that people can get COVID-19 by eating or handling food.\nIt may be possible that people can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object, such as a food package or dining ware that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes. However, this is not thought to be the main way the virus spreads. Follow food safety guidelines when handling and cleaning fresh produce. Do not wash produce with soap, bleach, sanitizer, alcohol, disinfectant or any other chemical.\nThere is also no current evidence that people can get COVID-19 by drinking water. The COVID-19 virus has not been detected in drinking water. Conventional water treatment methods that use filtration and disinfection, such as those in most municipal drinking water systems, should remove or kill the virus that causes COVID-19.​ Learn more about food and COVID-19."},{"id":504,"category":"Food and Water","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can the virus that causes COVID-19 spread through treated drinking water?","response":"The virus that causes COVID-19 has not been detected in treated drinking water. Water treatment plants use filters and disinfectants to remove or kill germs, like the virus that causes COVID-19. The Environmental Protection Agency regulates water treatment plants to ensure that treated water is safe to drink.\nCurrently, there is no evidence that the virus that causes COVID-19 can be spread to people by drinking treated water. COVID-19 is spread mainly through close contact from person-to-person. You can continue to use and drink water from your tap as usual."},{"id":505,"category":"Food and Water","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Is the virus that causes COVID-19 found in feces (stool)?","response":"The virus that causes COVID-19 has been found in the feces of some patients diagnosed with COVID-19. However, it is unclear whether the virus found in feces may be capable of causing COVID-19. There has not been any confirmed report of the virus spreading from feces to a person. Scientists also do not know how much risk there is that the virus could be spread from the feces of an infected person to another person. However, they think this risk is low based on data from previous pandemics of diseases caused by related coronaviruses, such as severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS)."},{"id":506,"category":"Food and Water","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can the COVID-19 virus spread through wastewater systems?","response":"SARS-CoV-2 (the virus that causes COVID-19) can be shed in the feces of individuals with COVID-19. Genetic material from SARS-CoV-2 has been found in untreated wastewater. However, while data are limited, there is little evidence of infectious virus in wastewater, and no information to date that anyone has become sick with COVID-19 because of exposure to wastewater. Wastewater treatment plants use chemical and other disinfection processes to remove and degrade many viruses and bacteria. SARS-CoV-2 is inactivated by the disinfection methods used in wastewater treatment. At this time, the risk of transmission of the virus that causes COVID-19 through properly designed and maintained wastewater systems is thought to be low."},{"id":507,"category":"Food and Water","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Should wastewater workers take extra precautions to protect themselves from the virus that causes COVID-19?","response":"Recently, ribonucleic acid (RNA) from the virus that causes COVID-19 has been found in untreated wastewater. While data are limited, there is little evidence of infectious virus in wastewater, and no information to date that anyone has become sick with COVID-19 because of exposure to wastewater.\nStandard practices associated with wastewater treatment plant operations should be sufficient to protect wastewater workers from the virus that causes COVID-19. These standard practices can include engineering and administrative controls, hygiene precautions, specific safe work practices, and personal protective equipment (PPE) normally required when handling untreated wastewater. No additional COVID-19–specific protections are recommended for workers involved in wastewater management, including those at wastewater treatment facilities.\nSee Information for Wastewater and Sanitation System Workers on COVID-19 for additional information."},{"id":508,"category":"Food and Water","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"If my utility has issued a Boil Water Advisory, can I still use tap water to wash my hands?","response":"In most cases, it is safe to wash your hands with soap and tap water during a Boil Water Advisory. Follow the guidance from your local public health officials. If soap and water are not available, use an alcohol-based hand sanitizer containing at least 60% alcohol."},{"id":509,"category":"Food and Water","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can the virus that causes COVID-19 spread to people through floodwater?","response":"There is no evidence that COVID-19 can spread to people through water, including floodwater.\nSometimes floodwater can mix with wastewater. CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus being spread by swallowing or coming in contact with water contaminated by feces from an infected person. Stay out of floodwater to avoid hazards and illnesses from contaminants that are not associated with COVID-19. To learn more about COVID-19 and wastewater, see question, “Can the COVID-19 virus spread through sewerage systems?”"},{"id":510,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can the virus that causes COVID-19 spread to people through the water in pools, hot tubs, or water playgrounds?","response":"CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus that causes COVID-19 spreading to people through the water in pools, hot tubs, or water playgrounds. Plus, proper operation of public pools, hot tubs, and water playgrounds (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) and disinfection of the water (with chlorine or bromine) should inactivate the virus.\nThe virus mainly spreads when respiratory droplets from infected people land in the mouths or noses of others or possibly when inhaled into the lungs by others. If a public pool, hot tub, or water playground is open, it is important for all visitors and staff to take steps to slow the spread of the virus:\n\nStay home if you are infected or might be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19.\nStay at least 6 feet apart (in and out of the water) from people you don’t live with.\nWear cloth masks when not in water.\nCover coughs and sneezes with a tissue (or use the inside of your elbow), throw used tissues in the trash, and wash hands.\nWash your hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds. Use hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol if soap and water are not readily available.\n\nSee Considerations for Public Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds for more information."},{"id":511,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can the virus that causes COVID-19 spread to people through the water in saltwater pools?","response":"CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus that causes COVID-19 spreading to people through the water in pools, including saltwater pools. Plus, proper operation of public pools (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) and disinfection of the water (with chlorine or bromine) should inactivate the virus. Saltwater pools are chlorinated pools.\nIn traditional pools, chlorine products (such as granules or liquid bleach) are added to the water to disinfect it. In saltwater pools, table salt (made up of sodium and chloride) is added to the water, and an electrical current is then run through the water with dissolved salt. This creates the same disinfecting form of chlorine that is created when chlorine products are added to the water in traditional pools."},{"id":512,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can the virus that causes COVID-19 spread to people through the water in lakes, oceans, or rivers?","response":"CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus that causes COVID-19 spreading to people through the water in lakes, oceans, rivers, or other natural bodies of water.\nThe virus mainly spreads when respiratory droplets from infected people land in the mouths or noses of others or possibly when inhaled into the lungs by others. If a public beach or other swim area in a natural body of water is open, it is important for all visitors and staff to take steps to slow the spread of the virus:\n\nStay home if you are infected or might be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19.\nStay at least 6 feet apart (in and out of the water) from people you don’t live with.\nWear cloth masks when not in water.\nCover coughs and sneezes with a tissue (or use the inside of your elbow), throw used tissues in the trash, and wash hands.\nWash your hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds. Use hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol if soap and water are not readily available.\n\nSee Considerations for Public Beaches for more information.\nRNAexternal icon of the virus that causes COVID-19 has been found in untreated wastewater, which can come from combined sewer overflowsexternal icon (rainwater runoff, domestic sewage, and industrial wastewater) and other sourcesexternal icon (such as, leaking septic tanks or animal waste from farms nearby) and enter swim areas. While data are limited, there is little evidence of infectious virus in wastewater. Plus, CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus being spread by swallowing or coming in contact with water contaminated by feces (poop) from an infected person.\nAt lakes, oceans, and rivers with routine water quality monitoring programs, staff look for changes in fecal (poop) contamination of the water. Water quality advisories and beach closures alert the public to avoid getting in or on the water because of increased fecal contamination. Learn more about healthy swimming in natural bodies of water and access water quality information by state."},{"id":513,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can cloth masks be worn in the water?","response":"No, do NOT wear a cloth mask in the water. It can be difficult to breathe through a cloth mask when it is wet. Plus, wet cloth masks don’t slow the spread of the virus that causes COVID-19 as well as dry cloth masks. All of this means it is particularly important to stay at least 6 feet apart in the water from people you don’t live with.\nIn case cloth masks do get wet by mistake, bring a second (or extra) cloth mask for everyone heading out to the public pool or beach."},{"id":514,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can Lycra (Spandex or elastane), the cloth used to make swimsuits, be used to make cloth masks?","response":"CDC does not yet have evidence on the effectiveness of different types of cloth materials.\nMasks offer some protection to you and are also meant to protect those around you, in case you are unknowingly infected with the virus that causes COVID-19. Make sure your cloth mask:\n\nfits snugly but comfortably against the side of the face,\ncompletely covers the nose and mouth,\nis secured with ties or ear loops,\nincludes multiple layers of fabric,\nallows for breathing without restriction, and\ncan be laundered and machine dried without damage or change to shape.\n\nCloth masks should NOT be worn by children less than 2 years old or anyone who has trouble breathing or is unconscious, incapacitated, or otherwise unable to remove the mask without assistance. Learn more about how to wear, take off, and wash your cloth masks."},{"id":515,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"How many people, visitors and staff, can be in and around a public pool, hot tub, or water playground (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) at the same time?","response":"The design of the public pool, hot tub, or water playground and surrounding deck and if visitors live together or not will affect how many people can stay at least 6 feet apart from those they don’t live with.\nCDC recommends operators of public pools, hot tubs, and water playgrounds:\n\ncomply with local, state, territorial, federal, and tribal regulatory agency policies and requirements on gathering (so the number of swimmers in the water isn’t more than the maximum allowed) and\nteach and reinforce social (physical) distancing among visitors and staff.\n\nOperators might want to limit the number of people in and around the water so if the water needs to be evacuated (because of lightning or other health or safety threat) social distancing can be maintained on the deck. Otherwise, if the water is evacuated and social distancing cannot be maintained on the deck, close the deck to visitors. There is no standard formula to determine how many people can maintain social distancing in the water and on the surrounding deck.\nSee Considerations for Public Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds for more information."},{"id":516,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can I use pool, hot tub, or water playground water to disinfect surfaces or shared objects?","response":"No. Only List N disinfectants approved by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agencyexternal icon should be used to disinfect surfaces (such as handrails and in bathrooms) and shared objects (such as kickboards and pool noodles).\nThe list includes hundreds of disinfectants. Operators of public pools, hot tubs, or water playgrounds (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) should consult with the design company or engineer to determine which disinfectants are best suited for surfaces and with manufacturers to determine which disinfectants are best suited for shared objects.\nRemember to clean surfaces and shared objects before disinfecting them and to follow directions on labels of cleaning products and disinfectants."},{"id":517,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can the sun’s ultraviolet (UV) light disinfect surfaces and shared objects?","response":"We don’t know yet. Early scientific data suggest that SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, can be inactivated by the sun’s UV light. However, the ability of the sun’s UV light to inactivate the virus on surfaces (such as handrails and in bathrooms) and shared objects (such as kickboards and pool noodles) needs more research. Factors — such as cloudiness, latitude (distance from equator), time of day, and amount of time exposed to the sun’s UV light — will determine how effectively the virus is inactivated.\nRemember to clean surfaces and shared objects before disinfecting them and to follow directions on labels of cleaning products and disinfectantsexternal icon."},{"id":518,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"How often do surfaces (such as handrails and in bathrooms) at public pools, hot tubs, or water playgrounds (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) need to be cleaned and disinfected?","response":"The more frequently a surface is touched by multiple people, the more frequently it should be cleaned and then disinfected with a List N disinfectant approved by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agencyexternal icon. Frequently touched surfaces should be cleaned and disinfected at least daily.\nRemember to clean surfaces and shared objects before disinfecting them and to follow directions on labels of cleaning products and disinfectants."},{"id":519,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Do procedures for responding to formed fecal (poop) or diarrheal incidents in public pools, hot tubs, or water playgrounds (such as at an apartment complex or owned by a community) need to change during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"No. RNAexternal icon of the virus that causes COVID-19 has been found in feces (poop). While data are limited, there is little evidence of infectious virus in feces. Plus, CDC is not aware of any scientific reports of the virus being spread by swallowing or coming in contact with water contaminated by feces from an infected person. As a result, CDC has not changed its fecal incident response recommendations. Remember, do NOT vacuum feces out of the water."},{"id":520,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"Can lifeguards monitor how visitors socially distance (stay at least 6 feet apart from people you don’t live with), wear cloth masks, or wash hands?","response":"Not when lifeguards are actively lifeguarding. Lifeguards actively lifeguarding should not be doing other tasks that could distract them. Drowning deaths have resulted, at least in part, from lifeguards being distracted. \nDrowning can occur quickly and quietly. Learn and take steps to prevent drowning."},{"id":521,"category":"Pools, Hot Tubs, and Water Playgrounds","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html","question":"How can the spread of the virus that causes COVID-19 be slowed during lifeguard training?","response":"Lifeguard trainers can consider the following steps to slow the spread of the virus that causes COVID-19:\n\nHave the virus? Stay home to save lives.\n\nEducate instructors, lifeguard students, and others about when they should stay home to isolate (if they have symptoms of COVID-19 or tested positive for COVID-19) or quarantine (if they have been in close contact with someone who has COVID-19) and when they can return or reschedule training.\nConduct daily health checks (see frequently asked question on screening) or ask instructors, students, and others to conduct self-checks (such as temperature screening or symptom checking), if possible.\n\nConduct health checks safely and respectfully and in accordance with any applicable local, state, territorial, federal, and tribal privacy and confidentiality laws, rules, and regulations.\n\n\n\n\nBe smart, stay at least 6 feet apart\n\nConduct knowledge training virtually or online, when possible, to limit contact among instructors, students, and others.\nTeach and reinforce social (physical) distancing during in-person skills training in and out of the water — maintaining at least 6 feet between people who don’t live together.\n\nProvide physical cues or guides (such as lane lines in the water or chairs and tables on the deck) and visual cues (such as posted signs or tape on the deck).\n\n\nLimit close contact, particularly face-to-face interactions, between people who don’t live together, as recommended by the lifeguarding-certifying organization. Such as\n\nAquatic rescue\n\nFor practice rescues\n\nHave each student practice rescues on his or her household member instead of another student.\n\n\nFor actual rescues\n\nStress the need to keep the number of people involved in rescue and resuscitation to the minimum number needed to provide proper care.\nStress the need to 1) perform rescues from the deck (using an extending or throwing device) if conditions allow and 2) if possible, have people on the deck wear cloth masks, when removing victim from the water because social distancing cannot be maintained. If an in-water rescue is needed, minimize exposure to the distressed swimmer’s face without protection, if possible approaching him or her from behind.\n\n\n\n\nCardiopulmonary Resuscitation (CPR)\n\nFor practice resuscitation\n\nLimit student-to-manikin ratio and student-to-automated external defibrillator (AED) training device ratio to 1:1. Have each student use his or her own breathing barrier when doing rescue breathing on a manikin.\n\n\nFor actual resuscitation\n\nStress the need for and train with personal protective equipment (PPE) during resuscitation, as recommended by the CPR-certifying organization (such as the American Red Crossexternal icon), and use a bag-valve mask (BVM) with a high-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filter. BVM ventilation is best delivered with two rescuers.\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\nWear a mask. Save lives.\n\nTeach and reinforce use of cloth masks in public settings when around people you don’t live with, particularly when it is difficult to maintain social distancing.\n\nAdvise people wearing masks to not wear them in the water. Cloth masks can be difficult to breathe through when they’re wet. This means it is particularly important to maintain social distancing in the water. Plus, wet cloth masks don’t slow the spread of the virus that causes COVID-19 as well as dry cloth masks.\n\n\n\n\nCover coughs and sneezes\n\nTeach and reinforce covering coughs and sneezes with a tissue (or use the inside of elbow), throw used tissues in the trash, and wash hands.\n\n\nWash hands often\n\nTeach and reinforce handwashing with soap and water for at least 20 seconds, particularly after being in a public place or after blowing your nose, coughing, or sneezing.\n\nUse hand sanitizer with at least 60% alcohol, if soap and water are not readily available.\n\n\n\n\n\n\nClean and then disinfect\n\nCleaning with a household cleaner that contains soap or detergent reduces the amount of germs on surfaces and decreases risk of infection from surfaces. In most situations, cleaning alone removes most virus particles on surfaces. Disinfection to reduce spread of COVID-19 at home is likely not needed unless someone in your home is sick or someone with COVID-19 has been in your home within the last 24 hours. For more information on cleaning your home regularly and cleaning your home when someone is sick, see Cleaning and Disinfecting Your Home.\nCDC has more COVID-19–related considerations for public pools and public beaches and non-COVID-19–related healthy and safe swimming resources."},{"id":522,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html","question":"If I have already had COVID-19 and recovered, do I still need to get vaccinated with a COVID-19 vaccine?","response":"Yes, you should be vaccinated regardless of whether you already had COVID-19. That’s because experts do not yet know how long you are protected from getting sick again after recovering from COVID-19. Even if you have already recovered from COVID-19, it is possible—although rare—that you could be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19 again. Studies have shown that vaccination provides a strong boost in protection in people who have recovered from COVID-19. Learn more about why getting vaccinated is a safer way to build protection than getting infected.\nIf you were treated for COVID-19 with monoclonal antibodies or convalescent plasma, you should wait 90 days before getting a COVID-19 vaccine. Talk to your doctor if you are unsure what treatments you received or if you have more questions about getting a COVID-19 vaccine.\nIf you or your child has a history of multisystem inflammatory syndrome in adults or children (MIS-A or MIS-C), consider delaying vaccination until you or your child have recovered from being sick and for 90 days after the date of diagnosis of MIS-A or MIS-C. Learn more about the clinical considerations people with a history of multisystem MIS-C or MIS-A.\nExperts are still learning more about how long vaccines protect against COVID-19. CDC will keep the public informed as new evidence becomes available.\nRelated pages:\n\nBenefits of Getting Vaccinated\nPreparing for Your COVID-19 Vaccination"},{"id":523,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html","question":"Is it safe for my child to get a COVID-19 vaccine?","response":"Yes. Studies show that COVID-19 vaccines are safe and effective. Like adults, children may have some side effects after COVID-19 vaccination. These side effects may affect their ability to do daily activities, but they should go away in a few days. Children 12 years and older are now eligible to get vaccinated against COVID-19. COVID-19 vaccines have been used under the most intensive safety monitoring in U.S. history, including studies in children 12 years and older. Your child cannot get COVID-19 from any COVID-19 vaccine.\nRelated page:\n\nCOVID-19 Vaccines for Children and Teens"},{"id":524,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html","question":"Why should my child get vaccinated against COVID-19?","response":"COVID-19 vaccination can help protect your child from getting COVID-19. Although fewer children have been sick with COVID-19 compared to adults, children can be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19, can get sick from COVID-19, and can spread the virus that causes COVID-19 to others. Getting your child vaccinated helps to protect your child and your family. Vaccination is now recommended for everyone 12 years and older. Currently, the Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 Vaccine is the only one available to children 12 years and older.\nRelated page:\n\nCOVID-19 Vaccines for Children and Teens"},{"id":525,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html","question":"What are the ingredients in COVID-19 vaccines?","response":"Vaccine ingredients can vary by manufacturer. To learn more about the ingredients in authorized COVID-19 vaccines, see\n\nInformation about the Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 Vaccine\nInformation about the Moderna COVID-19 Vaccine\nInformation about the Johnson & Johnson’s Janssen COVID-19 Vaccine\nIngredients Included in COVID-19 Vaccines"},{"id":526,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html","question":"Do I need to wear a mask and avoid close contact with others if I am fully vaccinated?","response":"No. Fully vaccinated people can resume activities without wearing a mask or physically distancing, except where required by federal, state, local, tribal, or territorial laws, rules, and regulations, including local business and workplace guidance. If you are fully vaccinated, you can resume activities that you did before the pandemic.\nAdditional recommendations can be found at When You’ve Been Fully Vaccinated.\nRelated pages:\n\nWhen You’ve Been Fully Vaccinated\nKey Things to Know\nProtect Yourself and Others"},{"id":527,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html","question":"Can I choose which COVID-19 vaccine I get?","response":"Yes. All currently authorized and recommended COVID-19 vaccines are safe and effective, and CDC does not recommend one vaccine over another. The most important decision is to get a COVID-19 vaccination as soon as possible. Widespread vaccination is a critical tool to help stop the pandemic.\nPeople should be aware that a risk of a rare condition called thrombosis with thrombocytopenia syndrome (TTS) has been reported following vaccination with the J&J/Janssen COVID-19 Vaccine. TTS is a serious condition that involves blood clots with low platelet counts. This problem is rare, and most reports were in women between 18 and 49 years old. For women 50 years and older and men of any age, this problem is even more rare. There are other COVID-19 vaccine options available for which this risk has not been seen (Pfizer-BioNTech, Moderna).\nLearn more about your COVID-19 vaccination, including how to find a vaccination location, what to expect at your appointment, and more.\nRelated page:\n\nYour Vaccination"},{"id":528,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html","question":"If I am pregnant, can I get a COVID-19 vaccine?","response":"Yes, if you are pregnant, you can receive a COVID-19 vaccine.\nYou might want to have a conversation with your healthcare provider to help you decide whether to get vaccinated. While such a conversation might be helpful, it is not required before vaccination. Learn more about vaccination considerations for people who are pregnant or breastfeeding.\nIf you are pregnant and have received a COVID-19 vaccine, we encourage you to enroll in v-safe, CDC’s smartphone-based tool that provides personalized health check-ins after vaccination. A v-safe pregnancy registry has been established to gather information on the health of pregnant people who have received a COVID-19 vaccine.\nRelated pages:\n\nCOVID-19 Vaccines for Pregnant or Breastfeeding People\nMonitoring Systems for Pregnant People\nV-safe Pregnancy Registry"},{"id":529,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html","question":"How long does protection from a COVID-19 vaccine last?","response":"We don’t know how long protection lasts for those who are vaccinated. What we do know is that COVID-19 has caused very serious illness and death for a lot of people. If you get COVID-19, you also risk giving it to loved ones who may get very sick. Getting a COVID-19 vaccine is a safer choice.\nExperts are working to learn more about both natural immunity and vaccine-induced immunity. CDC will keep the public informed as new evidence becomes available.\nRelated page:\n\nVaccines Work"},{"id":530,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html","question":"How many doses of COVID-19 vaccine will I need to get?","response":"The number of doses needed depends on which vaccine you receive. To get the most protection:\n\nTwo Pfizer-BioNTech vaccine doses should be given 3 weeks (21 days) apart.\nTwo Moderna vaccine doses should be given 1 month (28 days) apart.\nJohnson & Johnsons Jansen (J&J/Janssen) COVID-19 vaccine requires only one dose.\n\nIf you receive a vaccine that requires two doses, you should get your second shot as close to the recommended interval as possible. However, your second dose may be given up to 6 weeks (42 days) after the first dose, if necessary.. You should not get the second dose earlier than the recommended interval.\nRelated pages:\n\nPfizer-BioNTech\nModerna\nJohnson & Johnson / Janssen"},{"id":531,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html","question":"If I have an underlying condition, can I get a COVID-19 vaccine?","response":"People with underlying medical conditions can receive a COVID-19 vaccine as long as they have not had an immediate or severe allergic reaction to a COVID-19 vaccine or to any of the ingredients in the vaccine. Learn more about vaccination considerations for people with underlying medical conditions. Vaccination is an important consideration for adults of any age with certain underlying medical conditions because they are at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19.\nRelated pages:\n\nUnderlying Medical Conditions\nPeople at High Risk\nPeople with Allergies"},{"id":532,"category":"Vaccines","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/faq.html","question":"Can I get vaccinated against COVID-19 while I am currently sick with COVID-19?","response":"No. People with COVID-19 who have symptoms should wait to be vaccinated until they have recovered from their illness and have met the criteria for discontinuing isolation; those without symptoms should also wait until they meet the criteria before getting vaccinated. This guidance also applies to people who get COVID-19 before getting their second dose of vaccine.\nRelated pages:\n\nWhen to Quarantine\nEnding Home Isolation"},{"id":533,"category":"Travel : General","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"Can people who have recently recovered from COVID-19 travel?","response":"If you had COVID-19 in the past 3 months, follow all requirements and recommendations for fully vaccinated travelers except:\n\nYou can show documentation of recovery from COVID-19 instead of a negative test result before boarding an international flight to the United States.\nYou do NOT need to tested 3-5 days after travel to the United States unless you have symptoms of COVID-19.\n\nWe know that people can continue to test positive for up to 3 months after they had COVID-19 and not be infectious to others."},{"id":534,"category":"Travel : General","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"What if I recently traveled and am sick?","response":"See CDC’s website What to Do If You Are Sick."},{"id":535,"category":"Travel : General","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"How can I protect myself from COVID-19 when using different types of transportation?","response":"See CDC’s website Protect Yourself When Using Transportation."},{"id":536,"category":"Travel : General : Domestic Travel","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"Can traveling to visit family or friends increase my chances of getting and spreading COVID-19?","response":"Yes. CDC recommends delaying travel until you are fully vaccinated, because travel increases your chance of getting and spreading COVID-19. If you are not fully vaccinated and must travel, follow CDC’s Domestic Travel or International Travel recommendations for unvaccinated people."},{"id":537,"category":"Travel : General : Domestic Travel","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"Am I required to quarantine after domestic travel?","response":"CDC does not require travelers to undergo a mandatory federal quarantine. However, CDC recommends that unvaccinated travelers self-quarantine after travel for 7 days with a negative test and for 10 days if they don’t get tested.\nCheck CDC’s Domestic Travel pages for the latest recommendations for fully vaccinated and unvaccinated travelers.\nFollow all state and local recommendations or requirements."},{"id":538,"category":"Travel : General : Domestic Travel : International Travel","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"How does CDC determine the COVID-19 Travel Health Notice Level of a destination?","response":"CDC reviews data reported to the World Health Organization daily to determine a destination’s COVID-19 Travel Health Notice level. There are a few factors that CDC considers when determining the level of a destination. To find out more about the COVID-19 Travel Health Notice levels, visit How CDC Determines the Level for COVID-19 Travel Health Notices.\nThese notices offer travel recommendations based on the level of COVID-19 in a destination. To learn more about COVID-19 travel recommendations for a specific destination, visit COVID-19 Travel Recommendations by Destination."},{"id":539,"category":"Travel : General : Domestic Travel : International Travel","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"How often are international travel recommendations related to COVID-19 updated?","response":"Recommendations are updated weekly. CDC reviews data reported to the World Health Organization daily to determine a destination’s COVID-19 Travel Health Notice level and makes appropriate level changes once a week. To find out more about the COVID-19 Travel Health Notice levels, visit How CDC Determines the Level for COVID-19 Travel Health Notices."},{"id":540,"category":"Travel : General : Domestic Travel : International Travel","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"What restrictions do other countries have in place that might affect US travelers?","response":"Check with your destination’s Office of Foreign Affairs or Ministry of Health or the U.S. Department of State, Bureau of Consular Affairs, Country Informationexternal icon for details about entry requirements and restrictions for arriving travelers."},{"id":541,"category":"Travel : General : Domestic Travel : International Travel","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"Does CDC require COVID-19 testing before coming to the United States?","response":"All air passengers coming to the United States, including U.S. citizens and fully vaccinated people, are required to have a negative COVID-19 test result no more than 3 days before travel or documentation of recovery from COVID-19 in the past 3 months before they board a flight to the United States."},{"id":542,"category":"Travel : General : Domestic Travel : International Travel","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"Does CDC require quarantine after international travel?","response":"CDC does not require travelers to undergo a mandatory federal quarantine. However, CDC recommends that unvaccinated travelers self-quarantine after travel for 7 days with a negative test and for 10 days if they don’t get tested.\nCheck CDC’s International Travel pages for the latest recommendations for vaccinated and unvaccinated travelers.\nFollow all state and local recommendations or requirements."},{"id":543,"category":"Travel : General : Domestic Travel : International Travel : Air or Cruise Travel","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"Can flying on an airplane increase my risk of getting COVID-19?","response":"Yes. Air travel requires spending time in security lines and airport terminals, which can bring you in close contact with other people and frequently touched surfaces. Most viruses and other germs do not spread easily on flights because of how air circulates and is filtered on airplanes. However, social distancing is difficult on crowded flights, and you may have to sit near others (within 6 feet), sometimes for hours. This may increase your risk for exposure to the virus that causes COVID-19."},{"id":544,"category":"Travel : General : Domestic Travel : International Travel : Air or Cruise Travel","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"Do I have to wear a mask when I travel?","response":"Masks are required on planes, buses, trains, and other forms of public transportation traveling into, within, or out of the United States and in U.S. transportation hubs such as airports and stations."},{"id":545,"category":"Travel : General : Domestic Travel : International Travel : Air or Cruise Travel","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"What happens if there is a sick passenger on an international or domestic flight?","response":"Under current federal regulations, pilots must report all illnesses and deaths to CDC before arriving to a U.S. destination. According to CDC protocols, if a sick traveler has a contagious disease that is a risk to others on board the airplane, CDC works with local and state health departments and international public health agencies to contact exposed passengers and crew.\nBe sure to give the airline your current contact information when booking your ticket so you can be notified if you are exposed to a sick traveler on a flight.\nFor more information, see the CDC webpage Protecting Travelers’ Health from Airport to Community: Investigating Contagious Diseases on Flights."},{"id":546,"category":"Travel : General : Domestic Travel : International Travel : Air or Cruise Travel","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/travelers/faqs.html","question":"Should I delay going on a cruise?","response":"Yes. CDC recommends that all travelers avoid all cruise ship travel worldwide, including river boats. Reports of COVID-19 on cruise ships highlight the risk of infection to cruise ship passengers and crew. Like many other viruses, COVID-19 appears to spread more easily between people in close quarters aboard ships. At this time, cruise ship passenger operations remain suspended in U.S. waters under CDC’s Framework for Conditional Sailing Order."},{"id":547,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Who is at risk for infection with SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19?","response":"Currently, those at greatest risk of infection are persons who have had prolonged, unprotected close contact (i.e., within 6 feet for 15 minutes or longer) with a patient with confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, regardless of whether the patient has symptoms. Persons frequently in congregate settings (e.g., homeless shelters, assisted living facilities, college or university dormitories) are at increased risk of acquiring infection because of the increased likelihood of close contact. Those who live in or have recently been to areas with sustained transmission may also be at higher risk of infection. All persons can reduce the risk to themselves and others by wearing a mask, practicing physical distancing, washing their hands often, and taking other prevention measures. For more information, see Risk Assessment and Your Health."},{"id":548,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What should healthcare providers (HCP) do outside of work to prevent transmission of SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19?","response":"To prevent transmission of SARS-CoV-2 outside of work, HCP should follow CDC’s Guidance on Public Health Recommendations for Community-Related Exposure and the general guidance at Your Health. Because of their potential for exposure to SARS-CoV-2 at work, some HCP may choose to implement extra measures when arriving home from providing healthcare, such as removing any clothing they wore while delivering healthcare, taking off their shoes, washing their clothing, and immediately showering. However, these practices are optional and based on a personal decision; there is insufficient evidence to determine whether these additional practices can lower infection risk.\nBecause person-to-person transmission through respiratory droplets within a radius of 6 feet is currently thought to be the main way the virus spreads, everyone — including HCP —can reduce the risk to themselves and others by wearing a mask, practicing physical distancing, washing their hands often, and taking other prevention measures.\nCDC updates its guidance, including specific guidance in the links above, as additional information becomes available."},{"id":549,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Who is at risk for severe COVID-19?","response":"COVID-19 is a new disease and CDC is learning more about it every day. Among adults, the risk for severe illness from COVID-19 increases with age, with older adults at highest risk. Severe illness means that the person with COVID-19 may require hospitalization, intensive care, or a ventilator to help them breathe, or they may even die. People of any age with certain underlying medical conditions are also at increased risk for severe illness from SARS-CoV-2 infection.\nSee also Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) and Information for Healthcare Professionals: COVID-19 and Underlying Conditions."},{"id":550,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If my patient has an underlying medical condition associated with an increased risk of severe disease from COVID-19, what is my patient’s risk of developing severe COVID-19, and what should I tell my patient to reduce their risk?","response":"Stay up to date on the latest evidence about the risk for patients with underlying medical conditions. CDC analyzes data to determine the level of risk for people with underlying medical conditions and will provide updates over time as new information is available.\nYou know your patients’ overall health and how well their conditions are managed. Use your clinical judgment to evaluate each patient’s level of risk.\nHelp patients manage their underlying conditions to the best of their ability, encouraging them to take medicines as prescribed and ensuring that patients have sufficient medication and supplies. For example, you may prescribe 3-month supplies of medications to ensure they have access to sufficient medications.\nExplain to all patients which symptoms of their chronic conditions require emergency care or in-person visits. Stress the importance of obtaining emergency care if needed.\nReassure your patients who require emergency care that emergency departments (ED) have infection prevention plans to protect them from acquiring SARS-CoV-2 infection in the ED.\nTell patients with underlying medical conditions that increase their risk of severe illness or poorer outcomes from COVID-19 to:\n\nTake precautions to reduce the risk of getting COVID-19.\nClosely follow your care plans for managing their chronic disease, including, for example, achieving better glycemic or blood pressure control.\nSeek emergency care if any of their underlying medical conditions worsen and require immediate attention.\n\n\nEncourage all patients, regardless of risk, to:\n\nTake steps to protect themselves.\nCall their healthcare provider if you are sick with a fever, cough, or shortness of breath.\nFollow CDC travel guidelines and the recommendations of your state and local health officials.\n\n\nFear and anxiety about a new disease can feel overwhelming, especially for those with underlying risk factors, those in close contact with infected patients, and those with sources of stress outside the workplace. Follow guidance on ways to take care of yourself and encourage your patients to do the same.\n\nAdditional resources for healthcare providers"},{"id":551,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Are pregnant healthcare providers (HCP) at increased risk for adverse outcomes if they care for patients with COVID-19?","response":"Pregnant HCP should follow risk assessment and infection control guidelines for HCP exposed to patients with suspected or confirmed COVID-19. Adherence to recommended infection prevention and control practices is an important part of protecting all HCP in healthcare settings. Based on what we know at this time, pregnant and recently pregnant people are at an increased risk for severe illness from SARS-CoV-2 infection compared to non-pregnant people. In addition, pregnant people with COVID-19 are at increased risk for preterm birth and there might be at an increased risk of other poor pregnancy outcomes. Facilities may want to consider limiting exposure of pregnant HCP to patients with confirmed or suspected COVID-19, especially during higher risk procedures (e.g., aerosol-generating procedures) if feasible based on staffing availability.\nAdditional information about COVID-19 during pregnancy"},{"id":552,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What is multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C) and who is at risk?","response":"CDC continues to investigate multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C) associated with COVID-19. Children and adolescents with MIS-C have presented with a persistent fever and a variety of signs and symptoms including involvement of multiple organs (e.g., cardiac, gastrointestinal, renal, hematologic, dermatologic, neurologic) and elevated inflammatory markers. CDC is collaborating with domestic and international partners to better understand this new syndrome, including how common it is and its risk factors. For more information, including a full case definition and how to report MIS-C to your health department, visit MIS-C Information for Healthcare Providers."},{"id":553,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Are the alternatives to the 14-day quarantine described in the Options to Reduce Quarantine for Contacts of Persons with SARS-CoV-2 Infection Using Symptom Monitoring and Diagnostic Testing recommended for healthcare facilities?","response":"Given the need for often extensive and close contact between patients and healthcare personnel, a 14-day quarantine period continues to be recommended for patients receiving healthcare and healthcare personnel with exposures to SARS-CoV-2 warranting quarantine1 or work restrictions, respectively.  This option maximally reduces post-quarantine transmission risk and is the strategy with the greatest collective experience at present.\nAlternatives to the 14-day quarantine period are described in the Options to Reduce Quarantine for Contacts of Persons with SARS-CoV-2 Infection Using Symptom Monitoring and Diagnostic Testing.  Healthcare facilities could consider these alternatives as a measure to mitigate staffing shortages, space limitations, or PPE supply shortages but, due to the special nature of healthcare settings (e.g., patients at risk for worse outcomes, critical nature of healthcare personnel, challenges with social distancing), not as a preferred option.\nHealthcare facilities should understand that shortening the duration of work restriction or patient quarantine might pose additional transmission risk.  They should also counsel patients and healthcare personnel about the need to monitor for and immediately self-isolate if symptoms occur during the 14 days after their exposure and the importance of adhering to all recommended non-pharmaceutical interventions.\n1In healthcare settings, patients under quarantine are typically isolated in a single-person room and cared for by healthcare personnel using all PPE recommended for a patient with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection.  However, these patients should not be cohorted with patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection unless they are also confirmed to have SARS-CoV-2 infection through testing."},{"id":554,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Are there circumstances in healthcare settings when repeat testing for SARS-CoV-2 or quarantining might be considered for asymptomatic patients and residents who have recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection but are re-exposed to SARS-CoV-2 within 3 months of their prior infection?","response":"CDC currently recommends that asymptomatic patients and residents who have recovered and are within 3 months of a positive test for SARS-CoV-2 infection may not need to be quarantined or tested following re-exposure to SARS-CoV-2. However, there might be clinical scenarios in which the certainty about a prior infection or the durability of the immune response exist, for which providers could consider testing for SARS-CoV-2 and recommending quarantine following an exposure that occurs less than 3 months after their initial infection. Examples could include:\n\nPatients or residents with underlying immunocompromising conditions (e.g., patient after organ transplantation) or who become immune compromised (e.g., receive chemotherapy) in the 3 months following SARS-CoV-2 infection and who might have an increased risk for reinfection. However, data on which specific conditions may lead to higher risk and the magnitude of risk are not available.\nPatients or residents for whom there is concern that their initial diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection might have been based on a false positive test result (e.g., resident was asymptomatic, antigen test positive, and a confirmatory nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT) was not performed).\nPatients or residents for whom there is evidence that they were exposed to a novel SARS-CoV-2 variant (e.g., exposed to a person known to be infected with a novel variant) for which the risk of reinfection might be higher\n\nCDC continues to actively investigate the frequency of reinfection and the circumstances surrounding these episodes, including the role that new variants might play in reinfection, and will adjust guidance as necessary as more information becomes available."},{"id":555,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Do CDC’s interim infection prevention and control recommendations for COVID-19 apply to psychiatric hospitals or other behavioral health facilities?","response":"Yes. To keep patients and healthcare personnel (HCP) healthy and safe, CDC’s infection prevention and control guidance applies to all settings where healthcare is delivered. However, as with any guidance, facilities can tailor certain recommendations to their setting. For example, inpatient psychiatric care includes communal experiences and group activities that may need to continue. If so, these activities might need to be adapted to align with social distancing recommendations. Other recommended infection control measures (for example, ensuring access to alcohol-based hand sanitizer, cohorting patients with COVID-19 and assigning dedicated staff, or implementing universal source control measures) might not be safe or appropriate to implement in all locations or for all patients due to security and behavioral concerns.\nChallenges and potential solutions specific to behavioral health settings might include:\n\nCohorting\n\nChallenge: To prevent transmission, it is generally recommended that patients with COVID-19 be transferred to a separate area of the facility where they can be cared for by dedicated HCP. Because of security concerns or specialized care needs, it might not be possible to cohort certain patients together or change HCP assigned to their care.\nPotential Solutions: When cohorting is not possible, implement measures to maintain social distancing (at least 6 feet) between patients with COVID-19 and others on the unit. Ideally, this would include a separate bathroom for COVID-19 patients. Ensure HCP wear all recommended personal protective equipment (PPE) when caring for patients with suspected or confirmed COVID-19.\n\n\nGroup Therapy Sessions\n\nChallenge: Group counseling, therapy, and discussion sessions are a critical component of psychiatric treatment and care plans, but the traditional set-up for these activities is not compatible with social distancing recommendations.\nPotential Solutions: When possible, use virtual methods, or decrease group size so social distancing can be maintained. In the event that COVID-19 is transmitted in the facility, sessions should stop or move to a video discussion forum until additional infection prevention measures are in place to stop the spread.\n\n\nCloth Face Coverings\n\nChallenge: For some patients, the use of cloth face coverings or facemasks might pose an additional danger or may cause distress. Some patients may be unable or unwilling to use them as intended. Elastic and cloth straps can be used for strangling oneself or others, and metal nasal bridges can be used for self-harm or as a weapon.\nPotential Solutions: Consider allowing patients at low risk for misuse to wear cloth face coverings or facemasks, with a preference for those with short ear-loops rather than longer ties. Consider use of cloth face coverings or facemasks during supervised group activities. Ensure that HCP interacting with patients who cannot wear a cloth face covering or facemask are wearing eye protection and a facemask (or a respirator if the patient is suspected to have COVID-19 and respirators are available).\n\n\nAlcohol-based Hand Sanitizer\n\nChallenge: While alcohol-based hand sanitizer (ABHS) containing 60-95% alcohol is an important tool to increase adherence to hand hygiene recommendations, ABHS must be used carefully in psychiatric facilities to ensure it is not ingested by patients.\nPotential Solutions: Consider not placing ABHS in patients’ rooms in psychiatric facilities, nor in locations where the patients have unsupervised access. Encourage frequent hand washing with soap and water for patients and HCP. Consider providing personal, pocket-sized ABHS dispensers for HCP.\n\n\nDining\n\nChallenge: As part of social distancing, communal dining is generally not recommended. However, eating needs to remain supervised due to the potential for self-harm with eating utensils and because commonly used psychiatric medications may cause side effects (e.g., tardive dyskinesia, dysphagia, hypo- and hypersalivation) that increase choking risk for patients.\nPotential Solutions: One option is to position staff in patients’ rooms to monitor their dining. Another option is to allow communal dining in shifts so that staff can monitor patients while ensuring they remain at least 6 feet apart. A third option is to have patients sit in appropriately spaced chairs in the hallway outside their rooms so they can be monitored while they eat.\n\n\nSmoking\n\nChallenge: A higher proportion of psychiatric patients smoke cigarettes compared to the general population. Patients might congregate in outdoor smoking spaces without practicing appropriate social distancing.\nPotential Solutions: Limit the number of patients allowed to access smoking spaces at the same time, and position staff to observe and ensure patients are practicing appropriate physical distancing."},{"id":556,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If a long-term care facility has a resident or staff member with suspected or confirmed COVID-19, how and to whom should this be communicated?","response":"Facilities should follow the reporting requirements of their state or jurisdiction. Those regulated by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) (e.g., nursing homes) should also follow all CMS requirementsexternal icon, which are being updated to include new requirements for reporting to CDC and to residents and their representatives.\nIn addition, CDC recommends that health departments be promptly notified about:\n\nResidents or healthcare personnel (HCP) with suspected or confirmed COVID-19,\nResidents with severe respiratory infection resulting in hospitalization or death, and\n ≥ 3 residents or HCP with new-onset respiratory symptoms within 72 hours of each other.\n\nThese could signal an outbreak of COVID-19 or other respiratory disease in the facility. The health department can provide important guidance to assist with case finding and halting transmission.\nThe facility should also have a plan and mechanism to regularly communicate with residents, family members, and HCP, including if cases of COVID-19 are identified in the facility. Often, information in nursing homes is communicated through town hall meetings and staff meetings, along with letters or emails. However, during the COVID-19 pandemic, in-person gatherings should not occur. Instead, communication should occur through virtual meetings over phone or web platforms. These should be supplemented with written communications that provide contact information for a staff member who can respond to questions or concerns. Communications should include information describing the current situation, plans for limiting spread within the facility, and recommended actions they can take to protect themselves and others. Facilities should make this information available in a timely manner and offer periodic updates as the situation develops and more information becomes available."},{"id":557,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Is a negative test for SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, required before a hospitalized patient can be discharged to a nursing home?","response":"No. For patients hospitalized with SARS-CoV-2 infection, decisions about discharge from the hospital should be based on their clinical status and the ability of an accepting facility to meet their care needs and adhere to recommended infection prevention and control practices. Decisions about hospital discharge are distinct from decisions about discontinuation of Transmission-Based Precautions.\nFor patients with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, decisions about discontinuing Transmission-Based Precautions should be based on the strategies outlined here. The test-based strategy is recommended only for use in limited circumstances.\nIf a patient with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection has not met criteria for discontinuing Transmission-Based Precautions, they should be transferred to a facility with the ability to adhere to infection prevention and control recommendations for the care of residents with SARS-CoV-2 infection, including placement in a unit or area of the facility designated to care for residents with SARS-CoV-2 infection and provision of recommended personal protective equipment to healthcare personnel.\nIf the patient has met the criteria for discontinuing Transmission-Based Precautions, they do not require additional restrictions.\nA patient hospitalized for non-COVID-related illnesses who is not known to have SARS-CoV-2 infection can be transferred to a nursing home without testing. To ensure a patient was not exposed and might subsequently develop SARS-CoV-2 infection, nursing homes should place the patient in Transmission-based Precautions in a separate observation area or in a single-person room for 14 days after admission.\nAs part of universal source control measures, all residents (including those described in the scenarios above) should wear a cloth face covering or facemask (if tolerated) whenever they leave their room."},{"id":558,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"During the COVID-19 pandemic, are there special considerations for surgical and other procedural care settings, including performance of aerosol-generating procedures (AGPs)?","response":"As part of routine practices, healthcare personnel (HCP) should be applying Standard Precautions. HCP should always deliberately assess potential risks of exposure to infectious material before engaging in activities and procedures in healthcare delivery. Based on their risk assessment, safe work practices, including engineering controls that reduce the release of infectious material, administrative controls, and use of personal protective equipment (PPE) should be implemented at the point of care according to CDC guidelines and standards of practice for the activity performed.\nTo reduce SARS-CoV-2 exposure during the COVID-19 pandemic, CDC recommends that facilities:\n\nconsider nonoperative approaches when feasible;\nminimize the use of procedures or techniques that might produce infectious aerosols when feasible;\nminimize the number of people in the operating or procedure room to reduce exposures;\nuse the extent of community transmission and an assessment of the likelihood for patient harm if care is delayed to make decisions about cancelling or postponing elective surgeries and procedures; and\nimplement universal source control measures, which includes having patients wear a cloth face covering (as tolerated) and having HCP wear a facemask at all times while they are in the healthcare facility.\n\nIf surgery or procedures cannot be postponed, HCP caring for patients with suspected or confirmed COVID-19 should adhere to all recommended infection prevention and control practices for COVID-19.  This includes:\n\nUsing all recommended PPE: an N95 or equivalent or higher-level respirator (or facemask if respirators are not available), eye protection, gloves, and a gown.\n\nRespirators with exhalation valves should not be used during surgical procedures as unfiltered exhaled breath would compromise the sterile field.\nIf shortages exist, N95 or equivalent or higher-level respirators should be prioritized for procedures involving higher risk techniques (e.g., that generate potentially infectious aerosols) or that involve anatomic regions where viral loads might be higher (e.g., nose and throat, oropharynx, respiratory tract).\n\n\nAs part of routine practice, HCP should also be using additional engineering controls for source control, when applicable (e.g., smoke evacuation devices).\n\nBecause SARS-CoV-2 can be transmitted by individuals who are infected but do not have symptoms, some infected individuals will not be identified by screening for clinical signs and symptoms.  HCP providing surgical or procedural care to patients not suspected of having SARS-CoV-2 infection should use a tiered approach based on the level of community transmission to inform the need for universal eye protection and respirator use.  HCP should continue to use eye protection or an N95 or equivalent or higher-level respirator whenever recommended for patient care as a part of Standard or Transmission-Based Precautions.\nIn addition to the use of universal PPE and source control in healthcare settings, targeted SARS-CoV-2 testing of patients without signs or symptoms of COVID-19 might be used to identify those with asymptomatic or pre-symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection and further reduce risk for exposures in some healthcare settings. Depending on guidance from local and state health departments, testing availability, and how rapidly results are available, facilities can consider implementing pre-admission or pre-procedure diagnostic testing with authorized nucleic acid or antigen detection assays for SARS-CoV-2.\nTesting results might inform decisions about rescheduling elective procedures or about the need for additional Transmission-Based Precautions when caring for the patient. Limitations of using this testing strategy include obtaining negative results in patients during their incubation period who later become infectious and false negative test results, depending on the test method used."},{"id":559,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Why does CDC continue to recommend respiratory protection equivalent or higher to the level provided by an N95 disposable filtering facepiece respirator for care of patients with known or suspected COVID-19?","response":"CDC’s guidance to use NIOSH-approved N95 disposable filtering facepiece or higher level respirators when providing care for patients with suspected or known COVID-19 is based on the current understanding of SARS-CoV-2 and related respiratory viruses.\nCurrent data suggest that close-range aerosol transmission by droplet and inhalation, and contact followed by self-delivery to the eyes, nose, or mouth are likely routes of transmission. Long-range aerosol transmission, such as is seen with measles, has not been a feature of SARS-CoV-2.\nPotential routes of close-range transmission include splashes and sprays of infectious material onto mucous membranes and inhalation of infectious virions exhaled by an infected person. The relative contribution of each of these is not known for SARS-Co-V-2.\nFacemasks commonly used during surgical procedures will provide barrier protection against droplet sprays contacting mucous membranes of the nose and mouth, but they are not designed to protect wearers from inhaling small particles. N95 and higher level respirators, such as other disposable filtering facepiece respirators, powered air-purifying respirators (PAPRs), and elastomeric respirators, provide both barrier and respiratory protection because of their tight fit and filtration characteristics.\nRespirators should be used as part of a respiratory protection program that provides staff with medical evaluations, training, and fit testing.\nAlthough facemasks are routinely used for the care of patients with common viral respiratory infections, N95 or higher level respirators are routinely recommended for emerging pathogens like SARS CoV-2, which have the potential for transmission via small particles, the ability to cause severe infections, and no specific treatments or vaccines.\nCDC recommendations acknowledge the current challenges with limited supplies of N95s and other respirators. Facilities that do not have sufficient supplies of N95s and other respirators for all patient care should prioritize their use for activities and procedures that pose high risks of generating infectious aerosols and use facemasks for care that does not involve those activities or procedures. Detailed strategies for optimizing the supply of N95 respirators are available on the CDC website. Once availability of supplies is reestablished, the guidance states that the use of N95 and higher level respirators should resume."},{"id":560,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What personal protective equipment (PPE) should be worn by individuals transporting patients with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection within a healthcare facility? For example, what PPE should be worn when transporting the patient to radiology for imaging that cannot be performed in the patient room?","response":"In general, transport and movement of a patient with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection outside of their room should be limited to medically essential purposes. If being transported outside of the room, such as to radiology, healthcare personnel (HCP) in the receiving area should be notified in advance of transporting the patient. For transport, the patient should wear a facemask or cloth face covering (if tolerated) to contain secretions and be covered with a clean sheet.\nIf transport personnel must prepare the patient for transport (e.g., transfer them to the wheelchair or gurney), transport personnel should wear all recommended PPE (gloves, a gown, respiratory protection that is at least as protective as a fit tested NIOSH-certified disposable N95 filtering facepiece respirator or facemask—if a respirator is not available—and eye protection [i.e., goggles or disposable face shield that covers the front and sides of the face]). This recommendation is needed because these interactions typically involve close, often face-to-face, contact with the patient in an enclosed space (e.g., patient room). Once the patient has been transferred to the wheelchair or gurney (and prior to exiting the room), transporters should remove their gown and gloves and perform hand hygiene.\nThe transporter should continue to wear a respirator or facemask.  The continued use of eye protection by the transporter is also recommended if there is potential that the patient might not be able to tolerate their facemask or cloth face covering for the duration of transport.   Additional PPE should not be required unless there is an anticipated need to provide medical assistance during transport (e.g., helping the patient replace a dislodged facemask).\nAfter arrival at their destination, receiving personnel (e.g., in radiology) and the transporter (if assisting with transfer) should perform hand hygiene and wear all recommended PPE. If still wearing their original respirator or facemask and eye protection, the transporter should take care to avoid self-contamination when donning the remainder of the recommended PPE. This cautious approach will be refined and updated as more information becomes available and as response needs change in the United States.\nInterim guidance for EMS personnel transporting patients with confirmed or suspected SARS-CoV-2 infection is available here. EMS personnel should wear all recommended PPE because they are providing direct medical care and in close contact with the patient for longer periods of time."},{"id":561,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What personal protective equipment (PPE) should be worn by environmental services (EVS) personnel who clean and disinfect rooms of hospitalized patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection?","response":"In general, only essential personnel should enter the room of patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection. Healthcare facilities should consider assigning daily cleaning and disinfection of high-touch surfaces to nursing personnel who will already be in the room providing care to the patient. If this responsibility is assigned to EVS personnel, they should wear all recommended PPE when in the room. PPE should be removed upon leaving the room, immediately followed by performance of hand hygiene.\nAfter discharge, terminal cleaning can be performed by EVS personnel. They should delay entry into the room until time has elapsed for enough air changes to remove potentially infectious particles. After this time has elapsed, EVS personnel can enter the room and should wear a facemask (for source control) along with a gown and gloves when performing terminal cleaning. Eye protection should be added if splashes or sprays during cleaning and disinfection activities are anticipated or otherwise required based on the selected cleaning products. Shoe covers are not recommended at this time for personnel caring for patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection."},{"id":562,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Which procedures are considered aerosol generating procedures in healthcare settings?","response":"Some procedures performed on patients are more likely to generate higher concentrations of infectious respiratory aerosols than coughing, sneezing, talking, or breathing. These aerosol generating procedures (AGPs) potentially put healthcare personnel and others at an increased risk for pathogen exposure and infection.\nDevelopment of a comprehensive list of AGPs for healthcare settings has not been possible, due to limitations in available data on which procedures may generate potentially infectious aerosols and the challenges in determining if reported transmissions during AGPs are due to aerosols or other exposures.\nThere is neither expert consensus, nor sufficient supporting data, to create a definitive and comprehensive list of AGPs for healthcare settings.\nCommonly performed medical procedures that are often considered AGPs, or that create uncontrolled respiratory secretions, include:\n\nopen suctioning of airways\nsputum induction\ncardiopulmonary resuscitation\nendotracheal intubation and extubation\nnon-invasive ventilation (e.g., BiPAP, CPAP)\nbronchoscopy\nmanual ventilation\n\nBased on limited available data, it is uncertain whether aerosols generated from some procedures may be infectious, such as:\n\nnebulizer administration*\nhigh flow O2 delivery\n\n*Aerosols generated by nebulizers are derived from medication in the nebulizer. It is uncertain whether potential associations between performing this common procedure and increased risk of infection might be due to aerosols generated by the procedure or due to increased contact between those administering the nebulized medication and infected patients.\nReferences related to aerosol generating procedures:\nTran K, Cimon K, Severn M, Pessoa-Silva CL, Conly J (2012) Aerosol Generating Procedures and Risk of Transmission of Acute Respiratory Infections to Healthcare Workers: A Systematic Review. PLoS ONE 7(4); https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3338532/#!po=72.2222external iconexternal iconexternal icon)."},{"id":563,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"How long does an examination room need to remain vacant after being occupied by a patient with confirmed or suspected COVID-19?","response":"Although spread of SARS-CoV-2 is believed to be primarily via respiratory droplets, the contribution of small respirable particles to close proximity transmission is currently uncertain. Airborne transmission from person-to-person over long distances is unlikely.\nThe amount of time that the air inside an examination room remains potentially infectious is not known and may depend on a number of factors including the size of the room, the number of air changes per hour, how long the patient was in the room, if the patient was coughing or sneezing, and if an aerosol-generating procedure was performed. Facilities will need to consider these factors when deciding when the vacated room can be entered by someone who is not wearing PPE.\nFor a patient who was not coughing or sneezing, did not undergo an aerosol-generating procedure, and occupied the room for a short period of time (e.g., a few minutes), any risk to HCP and subsequent patients likely dissipates over a matter of minutes. However, for a patient who was coughing and remained in the room for a longer period of time or underwent an aerosol-generating procedure, the risk period is likely longer.\nFor these higher risk scenarios, it is reasonable to apply a similar time period as that used for pathogens spread by the airborne route (e.g., measles, tuberculosis) and to restrict HCP and patients without PPE from entering the room until sufficient time has elapsed for enough air changes to remove potentially infectious particles.\nGeneral guidance on clearance rates under differing ventilation conditions is available.\nIn addition to ensuring sufficient time for enough air changes to remove potentially infectious particles, HCP should clean and disinfect environmental surfaces and shared equipment before the room is used for another patient."},{"id":564,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"My hospital is experiencing a shortage of isolation gowns. To preserve our supply, can we stop using gowns for the care of patients with methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) and other endemic multidrug-resistant organisms (MDROs), and Clostridioides difficile?","response":"CDC has released information about strategies to optimize the supply of isolation gowns. Healthcare facilities should refer to that guidance and implement the recommended strategies to optimize their current supply of gowns. This includes shifting toward the use of washable cloth gowns, if feasible.\nThe use of gowns as part of Contact Precautions in the context of MDROs has been implemented primarily to reduce the risk of transmission to other patients rather than to protect healthcare personnel (HCP). Facilities with shortages could consider suspending the use of gowns for the care of patients with endemic MDROs, such as MRSA, VRE, and ESBL-producing Gram-negative bacilli except as required for Standard Precautions. Facilities should assess their local epidemiology to determine which MDROs are considered endemic. Regardless of the use of gowns, HCP at facilities should continue to wear gloves for contact with these patients and their environment. Hand hygiene should continue to be emphasized. Facilities should also attempt to place patients colonized or infected with an MDRO in a private room, if available.\n\nCaring for patients who have highly resistant Gram-negative organisms (e.g., carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriacae) and other MDROs (e.g., Candida auris) that are not considered endemic:  Rather than gowns being donned for every room entry, they should be reserved for use as part of Standard Precautions and also prioritized for high-contact patient care activities that pose highest risk for transfer of pathogens from the patient to HCP. Examples of such high-contact care activities include dressing, bathing/showering, transferring, providing hygiene, changing linens, changing briefs or assisting with toileting, device care or use (central line, urinary catheter, feeding tube, tracheostomy/ventilator), and wound care. To further preserve gowns, HCP are recommended to bundle high-contact care activities as part of individual care encounters.  Regardless of the use of gowns, HCP at facilities should continue to wear gloves for contact with these patients and their environment. Hand hygiene should continue to be emphasized. Facilities should also attempt to place patients colonized or infected with an MDRO in a private room, if available.\nCaring for patients with Clostridioides difficile infections (CDI):  Facilities should continue using Contact Precautions (putting on a gown and gloves upon entry into the patient’s room and placing the patient in a private room) for the care of symptomatic patients with CDI.  As part of a supplemental strategy to prevent transmission of CDI, some facilities have implemented Contact Precautions for the care of patients at high risk for CDI who have asymptomatic carriage of Clostridioides difficile. There are limited data about the role of asymptomatic carriage in transmission of CDI. In this setting of a critical national shortage of gowns, facilities should consider suspending this approach until the shortage is addressed. Gowns should still be used as part of Standard Precautions."},{"id":565,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"A healthcare provider at our facility was recently diagnosed with COVID-19. What time period and criteria do we use to determine the patients, visitors, and other healthcare personnel (HCP) who might have been exposed to this individual while he/she was potentially infectious?","response":"Anyone who had prolonged close contact (within 6 feet for a cumulative total of 15 minutes or more over a 24-hour period) with the infected healthcare provider might have been exposed.\n\nIf the provider had COVID-19 symptoms, the provider is considered potentially infectious beginning 2 days before symptoms first appeared until the provider meets criteria to discontinue Transmission-Based Precautions or Home Isolation.\nIf the provider did not have symptoms, collecting information about when the provider may have been exposed could help inform the period when they were infectious.\n\nIf an exposure is identified. The provider should be considered potentially infectious beginning 2 days after the exposure until criteria to discontinue Transmission-Based Precautions or Home Isolation are met.\nIf the date of exposure cannot be determined. For the purposes of contact tracing, it is reasonable to use a cutoff of 2 days before the specimen testing positive for SARS-CoV-2 was collected as the starting point, continuing until the criteria to discontinue Transmission-Based Precautions or Home Isolation are met. Although the infectious period is generally accepted to be 10 days after onset of infection, eliciting contacts during the entire 10 days before obtaining the specimen that tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 is likely inefficient.  In most situations an exposed provider cannot recall all contacts over the preceding 10 days.  Also, because recent data suggest that asymptomatic persons may have a lower viral burden at diagnosis than symptomatic persons, the additional resources required may divert case investigation and contact tracing resources away from activities most likely to interrupt ongoing transmission.\n\n\n\nContact tracing is generally recommended for anyone who had prolonged close contact with the person with SARS-CoV-2 infection during these time periods.  While this question addresses exposure to a potentially infectious provider, the following actions are also recommended if the potentially infectious individual is a patient or visitor.\nRecommended actions for HCP, patients, and visitors:\n\nPerform a risk assessment and apply work restrictions for other HCP who were exposed to the infected provider based on whether these HCP had prolonged, close contact and what PPE they were wearing. More detailed information is available in the Interim U.S. Guidance for Risk Assessment and Work Restrictions for Healthcare Personnel with Potential Exposure to COVID-19.\nPlace exposed patients who are currently admitted to the healthcare facility in appropriate Transmission-Based Precautions and monitor them for onset of SARS-CoV-2 infection until 14 days after their last exposure.\nContacts who are within 3 months of onset of prior SARS-CoV-2 infection might not require quarantine or testing if they remain asymptomatic.\nPerform contact tracing of exposed patients who are not currently admitted to the healthcare facility and for visitors as described in Health Departments: Interim Guidance on Developing a COVID-19 Case Investigation and Contact Tracing Plan.\n\nHealthcare facilities should have a process for notifying the health department about known or suspected cases of SARS-CoV-2 infection, and should establish a plan, in consultation with local public health authorities, for how exposures in a healthcare facility will be investigated and how contact tracing will be performed.  The plan should address the following:\n\nWho is responsible for identifying contacts and notifying potentially exposed individuals?\nHow will such notifications occur?\nWhat actions and follow-up are recommended for those who were exposed?\n\nContact tracing should be carried out in a way that protects the confidentiality of affected individuals to the extent possible and is consistent with applicable laws and regulations.  HCP and patients who are currently admitted to the facility or were transferred to another healthcare facility should be prioritized for notification.  These groups, if infected, have the potential to expose a large number of individuals at higher risk for severe disease, or in the situation of admitted patients, be at higher risk for severe illness themselves.\nInformation for health departments about case investigation and contact tracing is available in the Health Departments:  Interim Guidance on Developing a COVID-19 Case Investigation and Contact Tracing Plan.  This guidance could also be helpful to healthcare facilities performing such activities."},{"id":566,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"A healthcare provider in our facility worked while infected with SARS-CoV-2. However, the provider wore a facemask at all times while interacting with patients. Are the patients at risk for SARS-CoV-2 and should they be notified?","response":"Anyone who had prolonged close contact (within 6 feet for at least 15 minutes) should be considered potentially exposed.  The use of a facemask for source control and adherence to other recommended infection prevention and control (IPC) measures (e.g., hand hygiene) by the provider help to reduce the risk of transmission or severe illness. In areas with moderate to substantial community transmission, patients are already at risk for exposure to SARS-CoV-2 due to exposures outside their home and should be alert to the development of signs or symptoms consistent with COVID-19.\nThe following should be considered when determining which patients are at higher risk for transmission and might be prioritized for evaluation and testing:\n\nFacemask use by the patient – Mirroring the risk assessment guidance for healthcare personnel, patients not wearing a facemask would likely be at higher risk for infection compared to those that were wearing a facemask.\nType of interaction that occurred between the patient and infected provider – An interaction involving manipulation or prolonged close contact with the patient’s eyes, nose, or mouth (e.g., dental cleaning) likely poses higher risk of transmission to the patient compared to other interactions (e.g., blood pressure check).\nPPE used by infected HCP – HCP wearing a facemask (or respirator) and face shield that extends down below the chin might have had better source control than wearing only a facemask. Note that respirators with exhalation valves might not provide source control.\nCurrent status of patient – Is the patient currently admitted to a hospital or long-term care facility?  These individuals, if infected, can be at higher risk for severe illness and have the potential to expose large numbers of individuals at risk for severe disease."},{"id":567,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Questions addressing the proper handling of healthcare personnel (HCP) who have recovered from SARS-CoV-2 Infection, but are still within 3 months of onset of their prior infection.","response":"1. If HCP have recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection but have a high-risk exposure within 3 months of their initial infection to a patient with SARS-CoV-2 infection, should they be restricted from work for 14 days after the exposure?\nCDC has posted interim guidance for risk assessment and work restrictions for HCP with potential exposure to SARS-CoV-2. Because of their often extensive and close contact with people who are at high risk for severe illness, this guidance recommends a conservative approach to HCP monitoring and applying work restrictions to prevent transmission from potentially contagious HCP to patients, other HCP, and visitors. Review of currently available evidence suggests that most people do not become re-infected in the 3 months after SARS-CoV-2 infection. Testing of asymptomatic people during this 3-month period is complicated by the fact that some people have detectable virus from their prior infection during this period; a positive test during this period may more likely result from a prior infection rather than a new infection that poses risk for transmission.\nIn light of this, exposed HCP who are within 3 months of their initial infection, could continue to work, while monitoring for symptoms consistent with COVID-19 and following all recommended infection prevention and control practices (e.g., universal use of well-fitting source control). If symptoms develop, exposed HCP should be assessed and potentially tested for SARS-CoV-2, if an alternate etiology is not identified. Some facilities might still choose to institute work restrictions for asymptomatic HCP following a higher risk exposure, particularly if there is uncertainty about a prior infection or the durability of the person’s immune response. Examples could include:\n\nHCP with underlying immunocompromising conditions (e.g., after organ transplantation) or who become immune compromised (e.g., receive chemotherapy) in the 3 months following SARS-Cov-2 infection who might  be at increased risk for reinfection. However, data on which specific conditions may lead to higher risk and the magnitude of risk are not available.\nHCP for whom there is concern that their initial diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection might have been based on a false positive test result (e.g., individual was asymptomatic, antigen test positive, and a confirmatory nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT) was not performed).\nHCP for whom there is evidence that they were exposed to a novel SARS-CoV-2 variant for which the risk of reinfection might be higher (e.g., exposed to a person known to be infected with a novel variant).\n\nCDC continues to actively investigate the frequency of reinfection and the circumstances surrounding these episodes, including the role that new variants might play in reinfection, and will adjust guidance as necessary as more information becomes available.\n2. If HCP within 3 months of their initial infection develop symptoms consistent with COVID-19, should they be excluded from work and retested?\nHCP within 3 months of a confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection who develop symptoms consistent with COVID-19 should be evaluated to identify potential alternative etiologies for their symptoms. If an alternate etiology for the symptoms cannot be identified, they may need to be retested for SARS-CoV-2 infection with the understanding that a positive viral test could represent residual viral particles from the previous infection, rather than new infection. Decisions about the need for and duration of work exclusion should be based upon their suspected diagnosis (e.g., influenza, SARS-CoV-2 infection).\n3. Do HCP within 3 months of their initial infection need to wear all recommended personal protective equipment (PPE) when caring for patients with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection? For example, if there are limited respirators, should respirators be prioritized for HCP who have not been previously infected?\nRegardless of suspected or confirmed immunity, healthcare personnel should always wear all recommended PPE when caring for patients. In situations of PPE shortages, facilities should refer to CDC strategies for optimizing PPE supply. However, as with other infectious diseases (e.g., measles), allocation of available PPE should not be based on whether HCP have been previously infected or have evidence of immunity.\n4. Should HCP within 3 months of their initial infection be preferentially assigned to care for patients with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection?\nWhile individuals who have recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection might develop some protective immunity, the duration and extent of such immunity are not known. Staffing decisions should be based on usual facility practices. Any HCP assigned to care for patients with suspected or confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, regardless of history of infection, should follow all recommended infection prevention and control practices when providing care. Guidance on mitigating staff shortages is also available."},{"id":568,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If healthcare personnel (HCP) are living with someone who has been diagnosed with SARS-CoV-2 infection, should they be excluded from work? If so, for how long?","response":"Yes. HCP who have any kind of exposure for which home quarantine is recommended should be excluded from work:\n\nIf HCP are able to quarantine away from the infected individual living with them, they should quarantine at home and not come into work for 14 days following their last exposure to the infected individual.\nIf HCP are not able to quarantine away from the infected individual living with them and have ongoing unprotected exposure throughout the duration of the individual’s illness, they should remain in home quarantine and be excluded from work until 14 days after the infected individual meets criteria for discontinuation of home isolation.\nIf HCP develop SARS-CoV-2 infection while they are in quarantine, they should be excluded from work until they meet all return to work criteria for HCP with SARS-CoV-2 infection.\n\nHome quarantine and work exclusion of asymptomatic exposed HCP who have recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection in the prior 3 months might not be necessary.  Additional information about this scenario is available here."},{"id":569,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If a confirmatory test is performed on a person with a potential false-positive antigen test result or a potential false-negative result, what infection prevention and control (IPC) measures should be enacted while the result is pending?","response":"When confirmatory testing is performed on a person with a potential false-positive antigen test result, IPC measures should be maintained pending the result. Additional testing of close contacts can be delayed until results of confirmatory testing are available unless symptomatic individuals are identified.\n\nFor asymptomatic healthcare personnel (HCP), this includes continuing exclusion from work pending confirmatory testing.\nFor asymptomatic patients or residents, this includes placement on Transmission-Based Precautions in a single room or, if single rooms are not available, remaining in their current room pending results of confirmatory testing. They should not be transferred to a COVID-19 unit or placed in another shared room with new roommates.\n\nGiven the generally lower sensitivity of antigen tests, people with COVID-19–like symptoms who have a negative antigen test result should have a confirmatory nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT), such as reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), in most situations. Pending the results of confirmatory testing, maintain the following IPC measures:\n\nPatients and residents with COVID-19–like symptoms should be placed on Transmission-Based Precautions in a single room (not on the COVID-19 unit)\nHCP with COVID-19–like symptoms should be excluded from work until the confirmatory test results are available.\n\nDespite the potential need for confirmatory testing of negative results, the initial use of antigen tests for symptomatic people is still preferred if turnaround time for a NAAT is >2 days because a positive antigen test would initiate contact tracing and implementation of IPC measures."},{"id":570,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Using two masks at the same time, including the use of a cloth mask over a medical facemask*, to improve the fit of facemasks in healthcare settings","response":"CDC has recommended several ways to improve the fit and filtration of masks, including covering a medical facemask with a cloth mask. However, layering masks requires special care in healthcare settings.\n\nAlthough a cloth mask can be used over a medical facemask to improve fit, there may be better alternatives such as framed “fitters” or using a knot-and-tuck approach to achieve a good fit. If a good fit is achieved using a single medical facemask, additional approaches like adding layers to achieve a better fit might not be necessary.\nCloth masks are not personal protective equipment (PPE). They should not be used in place of medical facemasks or NIOSH-approved respirators as part of Standard or Transmission-based Precautions.\nWearing a medical facemask or cloth mask over an N95 respirator is not recommended for healthcare personnel in healthcare settings except as a contingency or crisis strategy during extended use of N95 respirators to protect the respirator from contamination during aerosol-generating procedures or procedures that might generate splashes and sprays.\nWearing a medical facemask or cloth mask under an N95 respirator is never recommended as it will interfere with the seal.\n\nIn healthcare settings, medical facemasks are used by healthcare personnel for two general purposes.\n\nFirst, as PPE to protect a healthcare worker’s nose and mouth from exposure to splashes, sprays, splatter, and respiratory secretions, such as when treating patients on Droplet Precautions. When used as PPE, medical facemasks should be removed and discarded after each patient encounter unless extended use is being practiced as part of a crisis or contingency capacity strategy.\n\nIf a cloth mask is used over the medical facemask, it should be removed and laundered after each patient encounter.\nCloth masks are not PPE and should not be used alone to protect against splashes and sprays, such as when used while treating patients on Droplet Precautions.\n\n\nSecond, for source control to cover a healthcare worker’s nose and mouth to prevent spread of respiratory secretions from the healthcare worker to other people. When used for source control, medical facemasks, including cloth masks that are used to cover medical facemasks to improve the fit, may be used for the duration of a shift unless they become soiled, damaged, or hard to breathe through; medical facemasks, including cloth masks, used for source control should be removed and discarded (or laundered if a cloth mask) at least after each workday.\n\nOnce put on, healthcare personnel should not touch their medical facemask or cloth mask. If they touch or adjust their medical facemask or cloth mask, they must perform hand hygiene before and after contact.\nIf laundering at the intervals described above cannot be performed, then cloth masks should not be used by healthcare personnel in healthcare settings.\n*Medical facemasks are personal protective equipment (PPE) and are often referred to as surgical masks or procedure masks. Use facemasks according to product labeling and local, state, and federal requirements. FDA-cleared surgical masks are designed to protect against splashes and sprays and are prioritized for use when such exposures are anticipated, including surgical procedures. Facemasks that are not regulated by FDA, such as some procedure masks, which are typically used for isolation purposes, may not provide protection against splashes and sprays."},{"id":571,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"When is someone infectious?","response":"The onset and duration of viral shedding and the period of infectiousness for COVID-19 are not yet known with certainty. Based on current evidence, scientists believe that persons with mild to moderate COVID-19 may shed replication-competent SARS-CoV-2 for up to 10 days following symptom onset, while a small fraction of persons with severe COVID-19, including immunocompromised persons, may shed replication-competent virus for up to 20 days. It is possible that SARS-CoV-2 RNA may be detectable in the upper or lower respiratory tract for weeks after illness onset, similar to infections with MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV. However, detection of viral RNA does not necessarily mean that infectious virus is present. Based on existing literature, the incubation period (the time from exposure to development of symptoms) of SARS-CoV-2 and other coronaviruses (e.g., MERS-CoV, SARS-CoV) ranges from 2–14 days."},{"id":572,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Which body fluids can spread infection?","response":"SARS-CoV-2 RNA has been detected in upper and lower respiratory tract specimens, and SARS-CoV-2 virus has been isolated from upper respiratory tract specimens and bronchoalveolar lavage fluid. SARS-CoV-2 RNA has been detected in blood and stool specimens, and SARS-CoV-2 virus has been isolated in cell culture from the stool of some patients, including a patient with pneumonia 15 days after symptom onset. The duration of SARS-CoV-2 RNA detection in upper and lower respiratory tract specimens and in extrapulmonary specimens is not yet known but may be several weeks or longer. Duration of several weeks or longer has been observed in cases of MERS-CoV or SARS-CoV infection. While viable, infectious SARS-CoV has been isolated from respiratory, blood, urine, and stool specimens, viable, infectious MERS-CoV has only been isolated from respiratory tract specimens. It is not yet known whether other non-respiratory body fluids from an infected person including blood, vomit, urine, breast milk, or semen can contain viable, infectious SARS-CoV-2."},{"id":573,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Can people who recover from COVID-19 be re-infected with SARS-CoV-2?","response":"CDC is aware of recent reports indicating that persons who were previously diagnosed with COVID-19 can be re-infected. These reports can understandably cause concern. The immune response, including duration of immunity, to SARS-CoV-2 infection is not yet understood. Based on what we know from other viruses, including common human coronaviruses, some reinfections are expected. Ongoing COVID-19 studies will help establish the frequency and severity of reinfection and who might be at higher risk for reinfection. At this time, whether you have had COVID-19 or not, the best ways to prevent infection are to wear a mask in public places, stay at least 6 feet away from other people, frequently wash your hands with soap and water for at least 20 seconds, and avoid crowds and confined spaces."},{"id":574,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"How do you test a patient for infection with SARS-CoV-2?","response":"Clinicians are able to access laboratory testing through state and local public health laboratories, as well as commercial and clinical laboratories across the country. The Association of Public Health Laboratoriesexternal icon provides a list of states and territories with laboratories that are using COVID-19 viral tests. For more information, see Testing in U.S. Clinicians should direct testing questions to their state health departments. Commercial reference laboratories are also able to offer a larger volume of testing for SARS-CoV-2.\nCDC has guidance for who should be tested, but decisions about testing are at the discretion of state and local health departments and/or individual clinicians.\nHealthcare providers should report positive  results to their local/state health department CDC does not directly collect these data directly."},{"id":575,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Do existing commercially available multiple respiratory virus panels detect SARS-CoV-2?","response":"Yes. There are commercially developed respiratory panels with multi-pathogen molecular assays that can detect respiratory pathogens, including SARS-CoV-2, influenza, and other human coronaviruses that can cause acute respiratory illness. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) maintains a list of tests that includes viral tests with Emergency Use Authorizationexternal icon (EUA)."},{"id":576,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If a patient tests positive for another respiratory virus, should that exclude SARS-CoV-2 as a cause of illness?","response":"Patients can be infected with more than one virus at the same time. Coinfections with other respiratory viruses in people with COVID-19 have been reported. Therefore, identifying infection with one respiratory virus does not exclude SARS-CoV-2 virus infection."},{"id":577,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should chest CT be used for diagnosis of COVID-19?","response":"Clinicians considering use of chest CT scans for diagnosis or management of COVID-19 patients should consider whether such imaging will change clinical management. The American College of Radiology (ACR) recommends that CT should not be used to screen for COVID-19, or as a first-line test to diagnose COVID-19, and that CT should be used sparingly and reserved for hospitalized, symptomatic patients with specific clinical indications for CT. Appropriate infection control procedures should be followed before scanning subsequent patients. For more information see, ACR Recommendations for the use of Chest Radiography and Computed Tomography (CT) for Suspected COVID-19 Infectionexternal iconexternal icon."},{"id":578,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Whom should healthcare providers notify if they suspect a patient has COVID-19?","response":"Healthcare providers should immediately notify infection control personnel at their facility if they suspect COVID-19 in a patient. If a patient tests positive, providers should report that positive result to their local/state health department."},{"id":579,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"How do you diagnose and report a potential case of multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C)?","response":"Patients with MIS-C have presented with a persistent fever and a variety of signs and symptoms including multiorgan (e.g., cardiac, gastrointestinal, renal, hematologic, dermatologic, neurologic) involvement and elevated inflammatory markers. Not all children will have the same symptoms. For children who may have MIS-C, further evaluation for signs of this syndrome may include (but are not limited to) chest radiograph, echocardiography, and blood testing to evaluate for evidence of inflammation.\nHealthcare providers who have cared or are caring for patients younger than 21 years of age meeting MIS-C criteria should report suspected cases to their local, state, or territorial health department. After hour phone numbers for health departments are available at the Council of State and Territorial Epidemiologists website.external icon  For additional reporting questions, please contact CDC’s 24-hour Emergency Operations Center at 770-488-7100. For more information, including a full case definition, please visit MIS-C Information for Healthcare Providers."},{"id":580,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"How can public health jurisdictions prioritize testing across nursing homes when resources are limited?","response":"Generally, nursing homes are recommended to test:\n\nResidents and healthcare personnel (HCP) with signs or symptoms of COVID-19\nResidents and HCP who are asymptomatic in response to an outbreak in the facility (i.e., a new SARS-CoV-2 infection in any HCP or any SARS-CoV-2 infection in a resident)\nAll residents and HCP once and serially test HCP who are asymptomatic in facilities without an outbreak as required by CMSexternal icon.\n\nHealth departments should have a plan on how to prioritize facilities when testing capacity is limited.\nIf testing capacity is limited for SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, prioritize testing (1) of residents and healthcare personnel (HCP) with signs or symptoms of COVID-19 and (2) asymptomatic residents and HCP in response to an outbreak in the facility.  When testing capacity is limited or test turnaround times are >2 days, testing HCP who are asymptomatic in facilities without an outbreak should be considered lower priority."},{"id":581,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Is there an optimal frequency for testing residents and HCP who previously tested negative in nursing homes as part of an outbreak response?","response":"As part of an outbreak response, CDC recommends that residents and HCP (who have not had a prior infection in the last 90 days) have viral testing (e.g., RT-PCR or antigen) immediately after the first new COVID-19 case is identified at the facility. Then the facility should perform serial testing of all residents and HCP who previously tested negative every 3–7 days until no new positive tests have been identified for 14 days. In nursing homes with outbreaks, most cases are identified within the first two weeks of diagnosing the first new case. These early cases likely occur among people who were previously exposed or were infected before more infection prevention and control (IPC) measures were implemented in response to the outbreak.\nFor this reason, if testing capacity allows and does not divert staff and resources away from performing other critical IPC measures (e.g., ensuring effective implementation of Transmission-Based Precautions for infected and potentially exposed residents), the facility should consider testing more frequently (e.g., every 3 days) for the first two weeks of the outbreak, then test less frequently (e.g., every 7 days) thereafter until no new cases are identified for 14 days. As an example, testing would occur on day 0 (day the first case is identified), days 3, 6, 9, and 12, and then on days 19, 26, etc.\nThis increased frequency of testing might not be possible in many facilities (e.g., lack of testing supplies or diversion of resources from other patient care activities). A minimum frequency of testing every 7 days is recommended until no new positive tests have been identified for 14 days. The effectiveness of increased frequency of testing is substantially diminished if IPC measures are not maintained. Facilities should ensure adherence to appropriate IPC measures in outbreak settings, including use of Transmission-Based Precautions for the care of all residents (even those who have negative tests) on affected units (or facility-wide, if cases are widespread). Facilities should also ensure rapid turnaround time of less than 2 days from specimen collection to test result."},{"id":582,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should residents in nursing homes who are asymptomatic be tested in non-outbreak settings?","response":"Unrecognized SARS-CoV-2 is most often introduced into a nursing home by asymptomatic healthcare personnel (HCP) or visitors with COVID-19 who work at or visit the nursing home, rather than residents. Recommendations for testing of residents who are asymptomatic in nursing homes is generally reserved for situations such as response to an outbreak in the facility (i.e., a new SARS-CoV-2 infection in any HCP or any SARS-CoV-2 infection in a resident) or evaluation of a resident who has had close contact with someone with confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection.\nRegular testing of asymptomatic residents can result in false-positive results and potentially result in additional unnecessary testing. If testing capacity allows, consideration could be given to regular serial testing of residents who are asymptomatic and who frequently leave the facility for medical treatment and then return (e.g. residents who receive regular hemodialysis, including those who are dialyzed at an onsite facility that treats nursing home and community patients), especially in communities where there is moderate to substantial community transmission. Such residents might be at higher risk for SARS-CoV-2 infections because of their frequent exposures outside the nursing home. These exposures can be from community patients, staff members during ambulatory care or during transportation; however, the benefit of serial testing of residents is not known."},{"id":583,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"When should an antigen test result be considered a false positive?","response":"Research studies report that  the specificity of antigen tests and nucleic acid amplification tests (NAAT), such as reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), are generally similar and high. However, false-positive results may occur with any test, even those that have very high sensitivity and specificity.\nA point-of-care antigen test result should be considered a possible false-positive when a positive test result appears inconsistent with the clinical situation (e.g., a positive antigen test in an asymptomatic person who does not have risk factors and resides in a community with lower COVID-19 prevalence). When a false-positive test is suspected, nursing homes and health departments should also review and gather the following information:\n\nReview the FDA EUAexternal icon and instructions for use of the point-of-care antigen test to ensure correct use. For instance, the use of viral transport medium has been shown to produce false-positive results in some tests and should not be used for some antigen platforms (including BD Veritor and Quidel Sofia platforms). For further information on appropriate use of point of care tests, see Specimen Collection and Handling of Point of Care Tests.\nReview recent control results to ensure accuracy of the antigen test platform. If able, perform procedural quality control tests to ensure correct operation of the platform.\nCompare the percent positivity of the samples that were run that day (or week) to their previous percent positivity (e.g., their rolling 7-day average percent positive). Identifying many positives in one day might indicate an issue with the antigen results (either due to operator error or faulty test supplies).\nConsider the pre-test probability of disease. If testing a population with a COVID-19 prevalence of <1% (e.g., screening asymptomatic HCP in non-outbreak settings) with a single test with 99% specificity, the positive predictive value (probability that a positive test is a true-positive) could be <40%. In other words, in such situations, fewer than 4 of every 10 positive tests represent a true positive.  If the prevalence of COVID-19 in the population is >10% (e.g., testing asymptomatic residents and HCP as part of an outbreak response) with that same test with 99% specificity, the positive predictive value may be >90%. In such situations, more than 9 of every 10 positive tests represent a true positive. Therefore, testing in low-prevalence populations with antigen or RT-PCR tests might produce false positives, but that is less likely in outbreak settings."},{"id":584,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If a nursing home is concerned about a false-positive antigen test result, what confirmatory test should be performed?","response":"In most instances, CDC guidance currently recommends performing confirmatory testing when asymptomatic individuals are antigen positive.\nIf confirmatory testing is performed, facilities can optimize the performance of the confirmatory test by doing the following:\n\nUse nucleic acid amplification tests (NAAT), such as reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), as the confirmatory test. The utility of performing a confirmatory test with a second antigen test (either with the same platform or a different platform) is not known; repeating the test using antigen platforms might not be helpful if there are concerns about operator error contributing to false-positive results.\nOptimize sensitivity of the confirmatory test by collecting a high-quality specimen to ensure the confirmatory test does not produce a false negative result.\n\nNasopharyngeal (NP) swabs used correctly have a higher sensitivity than other specimen sources. Therefore, confirmatory tests should be performed using NP swabs.\nThe quality of the specimen can impact sensitivity, which can be lower in residents who are not able to follow instructions or those who are intolerant of being tested. If the person is unable to tolerate a NP swab, then a swab of the anterior nares or mid-turbinate could be considered as collection of these specimen types are more tolerable, and have similar or slightly lower sensitivity.\n\n\nSelect a confirmatory test with high sensitivity. The sensitivity of different RT-PCRNAAT platforms variesexternal icon and the facility can check the FDA EUAexternal icon of the platform.\nPerform the confirmatory test within 2 days of the initial test. Tests performed >2 days apart should be considered separate tests, and discordant results may be due to changes in viral dynamics."},{"id":585,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should residents or HCP who have a positive antibody test for SARS-CoV-2 be tested as part of facility-wide testing?","response":"Yes. To determine if residents and HCP have a current infection, they should have a viral test (e.g., reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction [RT-PCR]) regardless of their antibody test result. A positive antibody test result shows that an individual has antibodies from an infection with the virus that causes COVID-19, or possibly from infection with a related virus from the same family of viruses (called coronavirus), such as one that causes the common cold. We do not know yet if having antibodies to the virus that causes COVID-19 can protect someone from getting infected again or, if they do, how long this protection might last. Therefore, antibody tests should not be used to diagnose COVID-19 and should not be used to inform infection prevention actions."},{"id":586,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"How should facilities approach residents who decline testing?","response":"Residents, or their medical powers of attorney, have the right to decline testing. Clinical discussions about testing may include alternative specimen collection sources that may be more acceptable to residents than nasopharyngeal swabs (e.g., anterior nares). Providing information about the method of testing and reason for pursuing testing may facilitate discussions with residents and their medical powers of attorney.\nIf a resident has symptoms consistent with COVID-19, but declines testing, they should remain on Transmission-Based Precautions until they meet the symptom-based criteria for discontinuation.\nIf a resident is asymptomatic and declines testing at the time of facility-wide testing, decisions on placing the resident on Transmission-Based Precautions for COVID-19 or providing usual care should be based on whether the facility has evidence suggesting SARS-CoV-2 transmission (i.e., confirmed infection in HCP or nursing-home onset infection in a resident).\nOnly residents who have a confirmed positive viral test should be moved to COVID-19-designated units or facilities."},{"id":587,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"How should facilities approach HCP who decline testing?","response":"If HCP with symptoms consistent with COVID-19 decline testing, they should be presumed to have COVID-19 and excluded from work. Return to work decisions should be based on COVID-19 return to work guidance at the discretion of the facility’s occupational health program.\nIf asymptomatic HCP decline testing, work restriction, if any, should be determined by the facility’s occupational health and local jurisdiction policies. All staff should be trained in proper use of personal protective equipment, including universal facemask policies, hand hygiene, and other measures needed to stop transmission of SARS-CoV-2."},{"id":588,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If HCP work at multiple facilities, do they need to receive a viral test at each facility?","response":"No, HCP do not need to be tested at each facility. If documentation of the test result is provided to each facility, the results from one setting are adequate to meet the testing recommendations at any facility. Each facility should maintain appropriate documentation of test results and have a plan to evaluate and manage HCP. HCP should be encouraged to tell facilities if they have had exposures at other facilities with recognized COVID-19 cases."},{"id":589,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should asymptomatic HCP who are tested as part of facility-wide testing be excluded from work while waiting for test results?","response":"If HCP remain asymptomatic, they may continue working while awaiting test results, unless work restrictions have been implemented by the occupational health program because of an exposure warranting exclusion from work."},{"id":590,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should post-exposure prophylaxis be used for people who may have been exposed to a person with COVID-19?","response":"There is currently no FDA-approved post-exposure prophylaxis for people who may have been exposed to COVID-19. For information about registered clinical trials of investigational therapeutics for pre- or post-exposure prophylaxis of SARS-CoV-2 infection, visit ClinicalTrials.govexternal icon.\nFor more information on movement restrictions, monitoring for symptoms, and evaluation after possible exposure to COVID-19, see Interim US Guidance for Risk Assessment and Public Health Management of Persons with Potential Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Exposure in Travel-associated or Community Settings and Interim U.S Guidance for Risk Assessment and Public Health Management of Healthcare Personnel with Potential Exposure in a Healthcare Setting to Patients with Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19).\nThe National Institutes of Health recently published guidelines on prophylaxis use for COVID-19 and testing and management of COVID-19 patients. For more information, please visit: National Institutes of Health: Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Treatment Guidelinesexternal icon."},{"id":591,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"How are COVID-19 patients treated?","response":"Not all patients with COVID-19 will require medical supportive care. Clinical management for hospitalized patients with COVID-19 is focused on supportive care for complications, including supplemental oxygen and advanced organ support for respiratory failure, septic shock, and multi-organ failure. Empiric testing and treatment for other viral or bacterial etiologies may be warranted.\nThe National Institutes of Health has published interim guidelines for the medical management of COVID-19external icon prepared by the COVID-19 Treatment Guidelines Panel.\nFor information on investigational therapies, see Therapeutic Options for Patients with COVID-19."},{"id":592,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Do patients with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 need to be admitted to the hospital?","response":"Not all patients with COVID-19 require hospital admission. Patients whose clinical presentation warrants in-patient clinical management for supportive medical care should be admitted to the hospital under appropriate Transmission-Based Precautions.\nSome patients with initial mild clinical presentation may worsen in the second week of illness. The decision to monitor these patients in the inpatient or outpatient setting should be made on a case-by-case basis. This decision will depend not only on the clinical presentation, but also on the patient’s ability to engage in self-monitoring, the feasibility of safe isolation at home, and the risk of transmission in the patient’s home environment. For more information, see Interim Infection Prevention and Control Recommendations for Patients with Suspected or Confirmed Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) in a Healthcare Setting and Interim Guidance for Implementing Home Care of People Not Requiring Hospitalization for Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19).\nReferences related to hospitalization and outcomes among patients with COVID-19:\nHuang C, Wang Y, Li X, et al. Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China. Lancet 2020;395:497-506.\nWang D, Hu B, Hu C, et al. Clinical Characteristics of 138 Hospitalized Patients With 2019 Novel Coronavirus-Infected Pneumonia in Wuhan, China. JAMA 2020.\nDong Y, Mo X, Hu Y, et al. Epidemiology of COVID-19 Among Children in China. Pediatrics 2020.\nWu Z, McGoogan JM. Characteristics of and Important Lessons From the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Outbreak in China: Summary of a Report of 72 314 Cases From the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention. JAMA 2020."},{"id":593,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"When can patients with confirmed COVID-19 be discharged from the hospital?","response":"Patients can be discharged from the healthcare facility whenever clinically indicated. Meeting criteria for discontinuation of Transmission-Based Precautions is not a prerequisite for discharge from a healthcare facility. Isolation should be maintained at home if the patient returns home before the time period recommended for discontinuation of hospital Transmission-Based Precautions.\nDecisions to discontinue Transmission-Based Precautions or in-home isolation should be made according to the following guidance:\n\nFor hospitalized persons, see Discontinuation of Transmission-Based Precautions and Disposition of Patients with SARS-CoV-2 Infection in Healthcare Settings.\nFor non-hospitalized persons, see Interim Guidance for Implementing Home Care of People Not Requiring Hospitalization for COVID-19 and Discontinuation of Isolation for Persons with COVID-19 Not in Healthcare Settings."},{"id":594,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What do we know about detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA after clinical recovery from COVID-19?","response":"Many recovered persons do not have detectable SARS-CoV-2 RNA in upper respiratory tract specimens. However, viral RNA can be persistently detected by reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) in respiratory tract samples in some persons after apparent clinical recovery.  In some persons, after testing negative by RT-PCR in two consecutive samples, later samples can test positive again. These persistent detections of viral RNA usually are associated with higher cycle threshold (Ct) values (i.e., fewer RNA copies) than Ct values found in RT-PCR results from samples collected shortly before or during clinical illness. Studies that have examined how long SARS-CoV-2 RNA can be detected in adults have demonstrated that, in some persons, it can be detected for weeks."},{"id":595,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Are clinically recovered persons infectious to others if they test persistently or recurrently positive for SARS-CoV-2 RNA?","response":"Whether the presence of detectable but low concentrations of viral RNA after clinical recovery represents the presence of potentially infectious virus is unknown. Based on experience with other viruses, it is unlikely that such persons pose an important infectious risk to others. However, whether this is true for SARS-CoV-2 infection has not been definitively established.\nAfter the onset of illness, the detectable viral burden usually declines. After a week or more, anti-SARS-CoV-2 immunoglobulin becomes detectable and then antibody levels increase. Some of these antibodies may prevent the virus from infecting cells in cell culture. A decline in viral RNA is associated with a decreased ability to isolate live virus. For most patients with COVID-19, efforts to isolate live virus from upper respiratory tract specimens have been unsuccessful when specimens are collected more than 10 days after illness onset. Recovery of live virus between 10 and 20 days after symptom onset has been documented in some persons with severe COVID-19; in some cases, these persons were in an immunocompromised state.\nPersons who have tested persistently or recurrently positive for SARS-CoV-2 RNA have, in some cases, had their signs and symptoms of COVID-19 improve. When viral isolation in tissue culture has been attempted in such persons in South Korea and the United States, live virus has not been isolated. There is no evidence to date that clinically recovered persons with persistent or recurrent detection of viral RNA have transmitted SARS-CoV-2 to others.\nDespite these observations, it’s not possible to conclude that all persons with persistent or recurrent detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA are no longer infectious. There is no firm evidence that the antibodies that develop in response to SARS-CoV-2 infection are protective. If these antibodies are protective, it’s not known what antibody levels are needed to  protect against reinfection.\nThese data and experience with other viral respiratory infections indicate that most persons recovered from COVID-19 who test persistently or recurrently positive by RT-PCR are likely no longer infectious. Isolation and precautions may be discontinued for persons with COVID-19  10 days after symptom onset (the date on which symptoms first began, including non-respiratory symptoms), provided their fever has resolved for at least 24 hours, without the use of fever-reducing medications, and their other symptoms have improved. For some persons with severe or critical illness, or who are severely immunocompromised, isolation and precautions may be maintained for up to 20 days after symptom onset."},{"id":596,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Can cycle threshold (Ct) values be used to assess when a person is no longer infectious?","response":"No. Although attempts to culture virus from upper respiratory specimens have been largely unsuccessful when Ct values are in high but detectable ranges, Ct values are not a quantitative measure of viral burden. In addition, Ct values are not standardized by RT-PCR platform nor have they been approved by FDA for use in clinical management. CDC does not endorse or recommend use of Ct values to assess when a person is no longer infectious. However, serial Ct values may be useful in the context of the entire body of information available when assessing recovery and resolution of infection."},{"id":597,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What further evidence is needed to be reassured that persistent or recurrent shedding of SARS-CoV-2 RNA after recovery does not represent the presence of infectious virus?","response":"Prospectively collecting serial respiratory samples and attempting to isolate live virus in tissue culture from multiple persons testing positive by RT-PCR following illness recovery is needed. If repeated attempts to recover replication-competent virus in culture from such serial samples are unsuccessful, that data would be sufficient evidence that infectious virus is absent. Then we would be sure that persons continuing to test positive do not pose an infectious risk to others."},{"id":598,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Can viral culture be used to demonstrate that a person who had persistently or recurrently detectable viral RNA is not infectious to others?","response":"Yes. However, viral culture is not widely performed for SARS-CoV-2. It must be conducted in Biosafety Level 3 (BSL-3) laboratories using BSL-3 practices by experienced virologists and culture results can take a week or more. Therefore, while persons whose specimens do not yield live virus are considered no longer infectious, the complexity of such testing and the time required to complete it mean that culture cannot be used routinely to guide management of infected persons."},{"id":599,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"A person who previously tested positive by RT-PCR for SARS-CoV-2 and clinically recovered from COVID-19 is later tested again, for example, as part of a contract tracing investigation. If that person again tests positive by RT-PCR, should they be managed as potentially infectious to others, and isolated again for COVID-19?","response":"For persons who remain asymptomatic following recovery from COVID-19, retesting (e.g., as part of a contact tracing investigation) is not necessary during the first 3 months after the date of symptom onset. When a positive test occurs less than 3 months after the person’s symptom onset of their most recent illness, it is possible that the positive test represents a new infection or a persistently positive test associated with the previous infection. If a positive test occurs more than 3 months after a person’s symptom onset, clinicians and public health authorities should consider the possibility of reinfection. Until we have more information, the determination of whether a patient with a positive test in these situations is contagious to others should be made on a case-by-case basis. Consider consultation with infectious diseases specialists and public health authorities to review all available information (e.g., medical history, time from initial positive test, RT-PCR Ct values, and presence of COVID-19 signs or symptoms).  Persons who are determined to be potentially infectious should undergo evaluation and remain isolated until they again meet criteria for discontinuation of isolation or discontinuation of transmission-based precautions, depending on their circumstances."},{"id":600,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If a previously infected person has clinically recovered but later experiences symptoms consistent with COVID-19, should the person be isolated again and tested for SARS-CoV-2?","response":"If a previously infected person experiences new symptoms consistent with COVID-19 3 months or more after the date of the previous illness onset (or date of last positive viral diagnostic test [RT-PCR or antigen test] if the person never experienced symptoms), the person should undergo repeat viral diagnostic testing. However, serologic testing should not be used to establish the presence or absence of SARS-COV-2 infection or reinfection. These people who have a positive test result should be considered infectious and remain isolated until they again meet criteria for discontinuation of isolation or of transmission-based precautions. Contact tracing during the person’s second episode of symptoms is warranted.\nFor persons who have recovered from laboratory-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection and who experience new symptoms consistent with COVID-19 within 3 months since the date of symptom onset of the previous illness episode (or date of last positive viral diagnostic test if the person never experienced symptoms), repeating viral diagnostic testing may be warranted if alternative etiologies for the illness cannot be identified. If reinfection is suspected and retesting is undertaken, the person should follow isolation recommendations for cases of COVID-19 pending clinical evaluation and testing results. Results of repeat testing should also be interpreted in consultation with an infectious disease specialist with consideration of cycle threshold values (if available) and clinical presentations. The determination of whether a patient with a subsequently positive test is contagious to others should be made on a case-by-case basis, in consultation with infectious diseases specialists and/or public health authorities, after review of available information (e.g., medical history, time from initial positive test, RT-PCR Ct values, and presence of COVID-19 signs or symptoms).\nNote: Serologic testing should not be used to establish the presence or absence of SARS-CoV-2 infection or reinfection."},{"id":601,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If an infected person has clinically recovered and then later is identified as a contact of another person with COVID-19, do they need to be quarantined?","response":"If a person has clinically recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection and is then identified as a contact of a new case 3 months or more after the date of symptom onset of their previous illness episode (or date of positive viral diagnostic test [RT-PCR or antigen test] if the person never experienced symptoms), then they should follow general quarantine recommendations for contacts and undergo repeat viral diagnostic testing.\nThe following applies to a person who has clinically recovered from  SARS-CoV-2 infection that was confirmed with a viral diagnostic test and then, within 3 months since the date of symptom onset of the previous illness episode (or date of positive viral diagnostic test if the person never experienced symptoms), is identified as a contact of a new case.  If the person remains asymptomatic since the new exposure, then they do not need to be retested for SARS-CoV-2 and do not need to be quarantined. However, if the person experiences new symptoms consistent with COVID-19 and an evaluation fails to identify a diagnosis other than SARS-CoV-2 infection (e.g., influenza), then repeat viral diagnostic testing may be warranted, in consultation with an infectious disease specialist and public health authorities for isolation guidance."},{"id":602,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If an infected person has clinically recovered using the symptom-based strategy, do they need a test to show they are not infectious?","response":"No. The symptom-based strategy is intended to replace the need for repeated testing."},{"id":603,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If an infected person has clinically recovered, should the person continue to wear a cloth face covering in public?","response":"Yes. It is recommended that all persons, with a few exceptions, wear cloth face coverings in public.1 The primary purpose of cloth face coverings is to limit transmission of SARS-CoV-2 from infected persons who may be infectious but do not have clinical symptoms of illness or may have early or mild symptoms that they do not recognize. Cloth face coverings may provide reassurance to others in public settings and be a reminder of the need to maintain social distancing. However, cloth face coverings are not personal protective equipment (PPE) and should not be used instead of a respirator or a facemask to protect a healthcare worker.\n[1] Cloth face coverings should not be placed on young children under age 2, anyone who has trouble breathing, or anyone who is unconscious, incapacitated, or otherwise unable to remove the mask without assistance."},{"id":604,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What should I do if I suspect a potential case of reinfection?","response":"Although current understanding of reinfection remains limited, CDC is working with its partners to characterize the clinical features, transmissibility, and immunological profile around reinfection with SARS-CoV-2. Therefore, the guidance remains the same to reinfections as to primary infection with SARS-CoV-2. To further our shared understanding of reinfection, CDC has released the Investigative Criteria for Suspected Cases of SARS-CoV-2 Reinfection as well as the Common Investigation Protocol for Investigating Suspected SARS-CoV-2 Reinfection. This protocol is to support public health investigations conducted by interested institutions and jurisdictions. Clinicians with available specimens for suspected cases of reinfection meeting the above investigative criteria are also invited to contact CDC at eocevent461@cdc.gov after consulting with their local health department to pursue investigations with CDC support."},{"id":605,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Does CDC recommend use of facemasks or respirators for healthcare personnel (HCP) caring for pregnant patients with known or suspected COVID-19 infection?","response":"When available, respirators (or facemasks if a respirator is not available), eye protection, gloves, and gowns should be used for the care of patients with known or suspected COVID-19 infection, including women who are pregnant. For more information, please see Interim Infection Prevention and Control Recommendations for Patients with Suspected or Confirmed Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Healthcare Settings."},{"id":606,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"How should the use of N95 respirators be prioritized within obstetric healthcare settings during shortages?","response":"During respirator shortages, care should be taken to ensure that N95 respirators are reserved for situations where respiratory protection is most important, such as performance of aerosol-generating procedures on patients with suspected or confirmed COVID-19 infection. In such shortage situations, facemasks might be used for other types of patient care.\nAlternatives to N95 respirators might be considered where feasible. These include other classes of NIOSH-approved filtering facepiece respirators, half facepiece or full facepiece elastomeric respirators, and powered air-purifying respirators (PAPRs) where feasible. All of these alternatives will provide equivalent or higher protection than N95 respirators when properly worn. However, PAPRs and elastomeric respirators should not be used in surgical settings due to concerns that exhaled air may contaminate the sterile field. For more information please see: Strategies for Optimizing the Supply of N95 Respirators.\nWhen respirator supplies are restored, the facility can switch back to use of N95 respirators for all care of patients with known or suspected COVID-19 infection. For more information, please see Interim Infection Prevention and Control Recommendations for Patients with Suspected or Confirmed Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Healthcare Settings."},{"id":607,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Is forceful exhalation during the second stage of labor considered an aerosol-generating procedure for respirator prioritization during shortages?","response":"Based on limited data, forceful exhalation during the second stage of labor would not be expected to generate aerosols to the same extent as procedures more commonly considered to be aerosol generating (such as bronchoscopy, intubation, and open suctioning. Forceful exhalation during the second stage of labor is not considered an aerosol-generating procedure for respirator prioritization during shortages over procedures more likely to generate higher concentrations of infectious respiratory aerosols.\nWhen respirator supplies are restored, as with all clinical care activities for patients with known or suspected COVID-19, HCP should use respirators (or facemasks if a respirator is not available), eye protection, gloves, and gowns during the second stage of labor, in addition to other personal protective equipment that may be typically indicated for labor and delivery. For more information please see: Healthcare Infection Prevention and Control FAQs"},{"id":608,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Is use of high-flow oxygen considered an aerosol-generating procedure for respirator prioritization during shortages?","response":"Based on limited data, high-flow oxygen use is not considered an aerosol-generating procedure for respirator prioritization during shortages over procedures more likely to generate higher concentrations of infectious respiratory aerosols (such as bronchoscopy, intubation, and open suctioning). Patients with known or suspected COVID-19 should receive any interventions they would normally receive as standard of care. When respirator supplies are restored, as with all clinical care activities for patients with known or suspected COVID-19, respirators (or facemasks if a respirator is not available), eye protection, gloves, and gowns should be used by HCP for the care of pregnant patients with known or suspected COVID-19. For more information please see: Healthcare Infection Prevention and Control FAQs"},{"id":609,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should intrapartum fever be considered as a possible sign of COVID-19 infection?","response":"Clinicians should use their judgment to determine if a patient has signs and symptoms compatible with COVID-19 and whether the patient should be tested. Fever is the most commonly reported sign; most patients with confirmed COVID-19 have developed fever and/or symptoms of acute respiratory illness (cough, difficulty breathing).\nData regarding COVID-19 in pregnancy are limited; according to current information, presenting signs and symptoms are expected to be similar to those for non-pregnant patients, including the presence of fever.\nOther considerations that may guide testing are epidemiologic factors such as the occurrence of local community transmission of COVID-19 infections. As part of evaluation, clinicians are strongly encouraged to test for other causes of respiratory illness and peripartum fever."},{"id":610,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What guidance is available for labor and delivery HCP with potential exposure in a healthcare setting to patients with COVID-19 infection?","response":"HCP in labor and delivery healthcare settings should follow the same infection prevention and control recommendations and personal protective equipment recommendations as all other HCP. If HCP are exposed to patients with COVID-19 infection, guidance is available for HCP and healthcare facilities on steps to take. For more information, please see: Interim U.S. Guidance for Risk Assessment and Public Health Management of Healthcare Personnel with Potential Exposure in a Healthcare Setting to Patients with Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19)"},{"id":611,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Are empiric antibiotics recommended for patients suspected of having COVID-19?","response":"Several patients with COVID-19 have been reported to present with concurrent community-acquired bacterial pneumonia. Decisions to administer antibiotics to COVID-19 patients should be based on the likelihood of bacterial infection (community-acquired or hospital-acquired), illness severity, and antimicrobial stewardship issues. For more information, see Diagnosis and Treatment of Adults with Community-acquired Pneumonia: An Official Clinical Practice Guideline of the American Thoracic Society and Infectious Diseases Society of Americaexternal iconexternal icon."},{"id":612,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What antiviral drugs are available to treat COVID-19?","response":"The National Institutes of Health (NIH) has published guidelines on testing and management of patients with COVID-19. For more information, please visit the NIH Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Treatment Guidelinesexternal icon. The recommendationsexternal icon are based on scientific evidence and expert opinion and are regularly updated as more data become available.\nCurrent clinical management of COVID-19 includes infection prevention and control measures and supportive care, including supplemental oxygen and mechanical ventilatory support when indicated. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has approved one drug, remdesivir (Veklury), for the treatment of COVID-19 in certain situations.\nPersons seeking information about registered clinical trials for COVID-19 in the United States can search for such information here: ClinicalTrials.govexternal icon.\nFor more information on investigational therapies, see Therapeutic Options for Patients with COVID-19.​"},{"id":613,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Do nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) worsen the course of disease for people with COVID-19?","response":"CDC is currently not aware of scientific evidence establishing a link between NSAIDs (e.g., ibuprofen, naproxen) and worsening of COVID‑19. FDAexternal iconexternal icon, the European Medicines Agencyexternal icon, the World Health Organization, and CDC are continuing to monitor the situation and will review new information on the effects of NSAIDs and COVID-19 disease as it becomes available. For those who wish to use treatment options other than NSAIDs, there are other over-the-counter and prescription medications approved for pain relief and fever reduction. Patients who rely on NSAIDs to treat chronic conditions and have additional questions should speak to their healthcare provider for individualized management. Patients should use NSAIDs, and all medications, according to the product labels and advice of their healthcare professional."},{"id":614,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If I have patients with asthma, do I need to make any changes to their daily asthma preventive management regimens to reduce their risk of getting sick with COVID-19?","response":"People with moderate to severe asthma, particularly if not well controlled, might be at higher risk of getting very sick from COVID-19.\nBased on what we currently know about COVID-19, the selection of therapeutic options through guideline-recommended treatment of asthma has not been affected. National asthma guidelinesexternal icon are available. Continuation of inhaled corticosteroids is particularly important for patients already using these medications because there is no evidence of increased risk of COVID-19 morbidity with use of inhaled corticosteroids and an abundance of data showing reduced risk of asthma exacerbation with maintenance of asthma controller therapy.\nPatients with asthma but without symptoms or a diagnosis of COVID-19 should continue any required nebulizer treatments."},{"id":615,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"If my patient experiences an asthma exacerbation, should the exacerbation be treated any differently to reduce risk of COVID-19?","response":"Selection of therapeutic options through guideline-recommended treatment of asthma exacerbations has not been affected by what we currently know about COVID-19.\nSystemic corticosteroids should be used to treat an asthma exacerbation per national asthma guidelinesexternal icon and current standards of care, even if it is caused by COVID-19. Short-term use of systemic corticosteroids to treat asthma exacerbations should be continued. There is currently no evidence to suggest that short-term use of systemic corticosteroids to treat asthma exacerbations increases the risk of developing severe COVID-19, whereas there is an abundance of data to support use of systemic steroids for moderate or severe asthma exacerbations.\nPatients with asthma but without symptoms or a diagnosis of COVID-19 should continue any required nebulizer for treatments, as recommended by national professional organizations, including the American Academy of Allergy, Asthma & Immunology (AAAAI) and the American College of Allergy, Asthma & Immunology (ACAAI). If healthcare providers need to be present during nebulizer use among patients who have either symptoms or a diagnosis of COVID-19, use CDC’s recommended precautions when performing aerosol-generating procedures (AGPs).\nClinicians may be concerned that an asthma exacerbation is related to an underlying infection with COVID-19. Clinicians can access laboratory testing for COVID-19 through a network of state and local public health laboratories across the country. Lists of states and territories with laboratories that are using COVID-19 viral tests are available. For more information, see Testing in U.S. Clinicians should direct testing questions to their state and localexternal icon health departments."},{"id":616,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Are any changes recommended to the asthma treatment plan if my patient with asthma has COVID-19?","response":"Patients can be referred to CDC’s recommendations for caring for themselves or someone else at home sick with COVID-19.\nIf nebulizer use at home is necessary for patients with asthma who have symptoms or a diagnosis of COVID-19, use of the nebulizer in a location that minimizes and preferably avoids exposure to any other members of the household, and preferably a location where air is not recirculated into the home (like a porch, patio, or garage) is recommended by national professional organizations, including the American College of Allergy, Asthma & Immunology (ACAAI) by the ACAAI and the Allergy & Asthma Network (AAN). Limiting the number of people in the room or location where the nebulizer is used is also recommended by the Asthma & Allergy Foundation of America (AAFA). Nebulizers should be used and cleaned according to the manufacturer’s instructions.\nIf nebulizer use in a healthcare setting is necessary for patients who have either symptoms or a diagnosis of COVID-19, use CDC’s recommended precautions when performing aerosol-generating procedures (AGPs)."},{"id":617,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should people with COVID-19 and increased alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) be tested for viral hepatitis?","response":"Yes, for your patients with COVID-19 who have risk factors for viral hepatitis and elevated hepatic enzymes, consider testing them for hepatitis A, B, and C, virus infections. However, ALT or AST may also be associated with COVID-19 alone and indicate greater severity of illness. For more information, review CDC’s Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19)"},{"id":618,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"During the COVID-19 pandemic, should high-risk populations continue to be vaccinated for hepatitis A in response to the ongoing hepatitis A outbreaks?","response":"Yes. People who are unvaccinated and at higher risk for hepatitis A virus (HAV) infection during the widespread outbreaks of hepatitis A across the United States should receive the hepatitis A vaccine when possible. This includes:\n\npeople who use drugs (injection or non-injection)\npeople experiencing unstable housing or homelessness\nmen who have sex with men (MSM)\npeople who are or were recently incarcerated\npeople with chronic liver disease (including cirrhosis, hepatitis B or C) and living or working in areas where the hepatitis A outbreaks are ongoing\n\nVaccination in group settings such as jails, other correctional facilities, and homeless shelters should continue if already planned and organized in a way that would follow infection control practices and where relevant social distancing standards can be maintained. When vaccinating people in non-group settings, ensure that general practices for the safe delivery of vaccination services are followed. Whenever possible, vaccination efforts in non-group settings should continue for people at highest risk of acquiring HAV infection or developing serious complications from HAV infection, if staying at least 6 feet away from others can be maintained.\nNote: For people receiving COVID-19 vaccination, a minimum interval of 14 days is recommended before or after receiving COVID-19 vaccination and any other vaccination. However, mRNA COVID-19 and other vaccines may be administered within a shorter period in situations where the benefits of vaccination are deemed to outweigh the potential unknown risks of vaccine coadministration, such as hepatitis A vaccination during an outbreak."},{"id":619,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should routinely recommended hepatitis A and B vaccines continue to be administered to children?","response":"Routine hepatitis A and B vaccination of children should continue to the extent possible, according to the CDC immunization schedules. For more information on vaccination during the COVID-19 pandemic, see the Immunizations and Well-child Care section on the Information for Pediatric Healthcare Providers page."},{"id":620,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should hepatitis B vaccination of HBV-exposed infants continue during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"Yes. Hepatitis B vaccination of all infants, especially those exposed to hepatitis B virus, should occur according to the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP) recommendations.\nInterim guidance to prevent mother-to-child transmission of hepatitis B virus:  \nLabor and Delivery Care\n\nIdentify the hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) status of all women presenting for delivery.\nIf a woman’s HBsAg status is positive, hepatitis B immune globulin (HBIG) and single antigen hepatitis B vaccine should be administered to her infant within 12 hours of birth.\nIf a woman’s HBsAg status is unknown, single antigen hepatitis B vaccine should be administered to her infant within 12 hours of birth. Administration of HBIG should be determined per ACIP recommendations. Infants weighing <2,000 grams should receive HBIG if the mother’s HBsAg status cannot be determined within 12 hours of birth.\n\nProvide the birth dose of hepatitis B vaccine to all other newborns within 24 hours of birth to prevent hepatitis B virus transmission from household or other close contacts."},{"id":621,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should management of infants born to HBV-infected women continue during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"Yes. Management should continue to prevent mother-to-child transmission of hepatitis B.\nInterim guidance to prevent mother-to-child transmission of hepatitis B virus:  \nPediatric Care of HBV-exposed Infants\n\nMake every effort to ensure HBV-exposed infants complete the hepatitis B vaccine series following the ACIP recommendations. Providers using single-component vaccine who are experiencing immunization service disruption should administer hepatitis B vaccine as close to the recommended intervals as possible, including series completion at 6 months, and follow ACIP recommendations for post-vaccination serologic testing.\nIf post-vaccination serologic testing is delayed beyond 6 months after the hepatitis B series is completed, consider administering a “booster” dose of single antigen hepatitis B vaccine and then ordering post-vaccination serologic testing (HBsAg & antibody to HBsAg [anti-HBs]) 1-2 months after the “booster” dose."},{"id":622,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should hepatitis A and B vaccines continue to be administered to adults at risk for hepatitis A or B?","response":"Yes. Continue to administer these vaccines if an in-person visit must be scheduled or occurs for some other purpose and the clinical preventive service can be delivered during that visit with no additional risk; or an individual patient and their clinician believe that there is a compelling need to receive the service based on an assessment that the potential benefit outweighs the risk of exposure to SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19. The vaccination status of all patients should be assessed at every clinical encounter to reduce missed opportunities for vaccination. See the Interim Guidance for Routine and Influenza Immunization Services During the COVID-19 Pandemic for more information."},{"id":623,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Are patients with hypertension at increased risk for severe illness from COVID-19?","response":"Many patients with severe illness from COVID-19 have underlying hypertension.1 Hypertension is common in the United States. Hypertension is more frequent with advancing age and among non-Hispanic blacks and people with other underlying medical conditions such as obesity and diabetes. At this time, people whose only underlying medical condition is hypertension might be at increased risk  for severe illness from COVID-19.2\n\nGarg S, Kim L, Whitaker M, et al. Hospitalization Rates and Characteristics of Patients Hospitalized with Laboratory-Confirmed Coronavirus Disease 2019 — COVID-NET, 14 States, March 1–30, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2020;69:458–464. DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm6915e3external icon.\nKillerby ME, Link-Gelles R, Haight SC, et al. Characteristics Associated with Hospitalization Among Patients with COVID-19 — Metropolitan Atlanta, Georgia, March–April 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2020;69:790–794. DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm6925e1external icon."},{"id":624,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors (ACE-Is) or angiotensin receptor blockers (ARBs) be stopped in patients with COVID-19?","response":"No. The American Heart Association, the Heart Failure Society of America, and the American College of Cardiology recommendexternal icon continuing ACE-I or ARB medications for all patients already prescribed those medications for indications such as heart failure, hypertension, or ischemic heart disease. At this time, available evidence demonstrates no indication of COVID-specific harm from these agents. Several randomized controlled trials are under way to better answer this important clinical question. Cardiovascular disease patients diagnosed with COVID-19 should be fully evaluated by a healthcare professional before adding or removing any treatments, and any changes to their treatment should be based on the latest scientific evidence. Patients who rely on ACE-Is or ARBs to treat chronic conditions and have additional questions should speak to their healthcare provider for individualized management"},{"id":625,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What do waste management companies need to know about wastewater and sewage coming from a healthcare facility or community setting with either a known COVID-19 patient or person under investigation (PUI)?","response":"Waste generated in the care of PUIs or patients with confirmed COVID-19 does not present additional considerations for wastewater disinfection in the United States. Coronaviruses are susceptible to the same disinfection conditions in community and healthcare settings as other viruses, so current disinfection conditions in wastewater treatment facilities are expected to be sufficient. This includes conditions for practices such as oxidation with hypochlorite (i.e., chlorine bleach) and peracetic acid, as well as inactivation using UV irradiation."},{"id":626,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Do wastewater and sewage workers need any additional protection when handling untreated waste from healthcare or community setting with either a known COVID-19 patient or PUI?","response":"Wastewater workers should use standard practices including basic hygiene precautions and wear the recommended PPE as prescribed for their current work tasks when handling untreated waste. There is no evidence to suggest that employees of wastewater plants need any additional protections in relation to COVID-19."},{"id":627,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Should medical waste or general waste from healthcare facilities treating PUIs and patients with confirmed COVID-19 be handled any differently or need any additional disinfection?","response":"Medical waste (trash) coming from healthcare facilities treating COVID-2019 patients is no different than waste coming from facilities without COVID-19 patients. CDC’s guidance states that management of laundry, food service utensils, and medical waste should be performed in accordance with routine procedures. There is no evidence to suggest that facility waste needs any additional disinfection.\nMore guidance about environmental infection control is available in section 7 of CDC’s Interim Infection Prevention and Control Recommendations for Patients with Confirmed COVID-19 or Persons Under Investigation for COVID-19 in Healthcare Settings."},{"id":628,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management : Cleaning and Disinfection of Environmental Surfaces","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"How are environmental surfaces involved in the transmission of infections?","response":"Surfaces can become contaminated with microorganisms and potential pathogens. However, many of these surfaces are generally not directly associated with transmission of infections to either healthcare workers or patients.  The transfer of pathogens from environmental surfaces is largely due to hand contact with the surface (e.g., frequently touched surfaces). Touch contamination may lead to cross contamination of patient care items, other environmental surfaces, self-contamination, and possible infection after touching one’s face or mouth."},{"id":629,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management : Cleaning and Disinfection of Environmental Surfaces","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"How does one interrupt transmission of pathogens from environmental surfaces?","response":"Both hand hygiene and the cleaning and disinfection of environmental surfaces are fundamental practices to reduce the incidence of healthcare-associated infections."},{"id":630,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management : Cleaning and Disinfection of Environmental Surfaces","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Where can I find detailed information on cleaning and disinfection?","response":"For more information see our guidelines for healthcare facilities that cover cleaning, disinfection, sterilization, and hand hygiene:\n\nGuideline for Environmental Infection Control, 2003\nGuideline for Disinfection and Sterilization, 2008\nGuideline for Hand Hygiene in Healthcare Settings"},{"id":631,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management : Cleaning and Disinfection of Environmental Surfaces","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Why is cleaning of surfaces important?","response":"Cleaning is an important first step for any process that involves disinfection or sterilization because the presence of organic and inorganic soils may cause disinfection or sterilization to fail.  Cleaning is the process of removing both organic and inorganic matter from surfaces with the use of detergents (e.g., anionic, cationic, non-ionic, and zwitter ionic) or enzymatic cleaners.  Cleaning may involve manual, automated, or a combination of manual and automated methods.\n\nDepending on the cleaning method and the surface being cleaned, a 102-106 log reduction of microorganisms may be possible.\nProper cleaning may be enough to make an environmental surface safe to handle and to prevent transmission of pathogens.\nCurrently, no cleaning guidelines apply to all devices or surfaces, nor is there a single accepted standard method to measure the effectiveness of cleaning (examples include adenosine triphosphate (ATP), fluorescent markers, blood, protein, carbohydrate, RODACTM plates, or touch plates).\nSee the CDC Environmental Toolkit for additional information on developing a cleaning evaluation program."},{"id":632,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management : Cleaning and Disinfection of Environmental Surfaces","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What detergents are used for routine environmental cleaning in healthcare settings?","response":"Many cleaners used in healthcare settings for routine cleaning of the general environment are cationic detergents, with many of these being quaternary ammonium compounds which are also low- to intermediate-level disinfectants. For EPA registered detergent disinfectants, refer to the label to determine if the product is a one-step or multiple-step product, and follow the product label instructions for use.\n\nOne-step disinfection product and process combine cleaning and disinfection of a noncritical environmental surface or item into a single step. Depending on the instructions for product use, some do not have to be rinsed off.\nMulti-step products and processes require the user to clean the surface before it is disinfected. In some cases, the disinfectant must be rinsed from the surface following the wet contact time listed on the product label."},{"id":633,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management : Cleaning and Disinfection of Environmental Surfaces","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Are there ways to audit the cleaning process?","response":"Cleaning guidelines vary based on devices and surfaces being cleaned. Multiple methods are used to measure the residual bioburden or effectiveness of cleaning (e.g., ATP, fluorescent markers, blood, protein, carbohydrate, and RODACTM plates, or touch plates)\nSee the CDC Environmental Toolkit for additional information on developing a cleaning evaluation program."},{"id":634,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management : Cleaning and Disinfection of Environmental Surfaces","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What are no-touch devices or NTDs?","response":"No-touch devices (NTDs) are sometimes used in healthcare settings as an adjunct to terminal room cleaning (i.e., after patient discharge or transfer). They are not currently able to replace existing cleaning and disinfection processes. These devices use a variety of different disinfection technologies such as ultraviolet germicidal irradiation (UVGI) and chemical agents. They are called no-touch devices because they use a pre-determined program that allows the device to run unmanned in an unoccupied, pre-cleaned room (e.g., patient room) for a defined period.\nChemical disinfectants used for NTDs vary according to the specific device. Examples include vapor phase hydrogen peroxide, dry mist hydrogen peroxide, combined hydrogen peroxide + antimicrobial silver, dry fog hydrogen peroxide + peroxyacetic acid, ionized hydrogen peroxide, and chlorine dioxide gas.\nThe effectiveness of NTDs is still under investigation; most data are laboratory demonstrations of pathogen inactivation. Thus far, only one study of NTD use has shown a decrease in patient infection rates, the Duke BETR Disinfection Studyexternal icon (Andersen DJ, et al. Lancet Infect Dis 2018; 18(8): 845–853)."},{"id":635,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management : Cleaning and Disinfection of Environmental Surfaces","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"What information is available about the use of electrostatic sprayers or foggers for the disinfection of rooms and surfaces in healthcare environments?","response":"These devices are typically used as an adjunct technology to terminal room cleaning. This means that the patient has been transferred or discharged and is no longer occupying the space.  So that EVS may begin cleaning and disinfecting the room in preparation for a new patient (e.g., terminal cleaning).\nFor information about the application of EPA List N disinfectantsexternal icon with electrostatic sprayers and foggers, refer to the EPA’s Frequent Questions about Disinfectants and Coronavirus (COVID-19external icon). If a product does not have an electrostatic spraying or fogging use on a label, the EPA has not evaluated the safety and efficacy of using that product with an electrostatic sprayer or a fogger.\n\nFoggers can be hand-held or no-touch devices (NTDs).\nWhen using an electrostatic sprayer or a fogger to apply disinfectants, always follow manufacturer directions for operation and maintenance of the sprayer or fogger and the disinfectant label’s use directions (e.g., application rate, distance to surface while applying, and contact time).\nFollow the disinfectant’s label recommendations for appropriate personal protective equipment (PPE) for the operator, and adhere to any recommended re-entry times for bystanders, other staff members, or patients."},{"id":636,"category":"Healthcare Professionals : COVID-19 Risk : Infection Control : Transmission : Testing, Diagnosis, and Notification : Testing in Nursing Homes : Treatment and Management : Testing, Isolation, and Quarantine for Persons Who Have Recovered from Previous SARS-CoV-2 Infection : Obstetrical Care : Drugs and Investigational Therapies : Patients with Asthma : Patients with Liver Disease : Patients with Hypertension : Waste Management : Cleaning and Disinfection of Environmental Surfaces","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/faq.html","question":"Is ultraviolet germicidal irradiation (UVGI) recommended for disinfection of air and surfaces in the healthcare setting?","response":"UVGI can be used as a supplemental treatment for disinfection of air in HVAC systems or above people in occupied spaces (upper-room or upper-air systems) and for supplemental disinfection of surfaces following routine cleaning and disinfection. UVGI, also known as Germicidal Ultraviolet (GUV), uses ultraviolet energy in the UV-C band (wavelengths of 220-280 nanometers), which is effective against SARS-CoV-2 under laboratory conditions. Efficacy of the applied dose (a function of irradiance and time) is highly dependent on many factors, such as the concentration of the virus, inoculum size (in experimental studies), the virus medium, contours and type of material being treated, as well as what the virus is suspended in (e.g., culture media, respiratory droplets, other proteinaceous material). These complex variables may explain the range of results presented in the published literature.\nFor more information on these technologies see the CDC Business FAQs under the heading “Cleaning and Disinfection in the Workplace”\nUV-C can be applied on healthcare environmental surfaces using robots as NTDs following terminal cleaning and is still considered investigational; one study mentioned above the Duke BETR Disinfection Studyexternal icon (Andersen DJ, et al. Lancet Infect Dis 2018; 18(8): 845–853) has shown a decrease in Healthcare-associated infections."},{"id":637,"category":"General Business : Ventilation","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/general-business-faq.html","question":"Can COVID-19 be transmitted through HVAC (ventilation) systems?","response":"The risk of spreading the virus that causes coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) through ventilation systems is not well-known at this time. Viral RNA has reportedly been found on return air grilles, in return air ducts, and on heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) filters, but detecting viral RNA alone does not imply that the captured virus was capable of transmitting disease. One research group reported that the use of a new air-sampling method allowed them to find viable viral particles within a COVID-19 patient’s hospital roomexternal icon with good ventilation, filtration and ultraviolet (UV) disinfection (at distances as far as 16 feet from the patient). However, the concentration of viable virus detected was believed to be too low to cause disease transmission. There may be some implications for HVAC systems associated with these findings, but it is too early to conclude that with certainty. While airflows within a particular space may help spread disease among people in that space, there is no evidence to date that viable virus has been transmitted through an HVAC system to result in disease transmission to people in other spaces served by the same system.\nHealthcare facilities have ventilation requirements in place to help prevent and control infectious diseases that are associated with healthcare environments. For more information, see the CDC Guidelines for Environmental Infection Control in Health-Care Facilities.\nNon-healthcare (businesses and schools) building owners and managers should maintain building ventilation systems according to state/local building codes and applicable guidelines. Ensuring appropriate outdoor air and ventilation rates is a practical step building owners and managers can take to ensure good indoor air quality. Considerations for ventilation and related engineering control interventions for businesses and schools may be found on the following CDC webpages: COVID-19 Employer Information for Office Buildings and Strategies for Protecting K-12 School Staff from COVID-19."},{"id":638,"category":"General Business : Ventilation","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/general-business-faq.html","question":"How long will it take to dilute the concentration of infectious particles in a room once they are generated?","response":"While large droplets (100 micrometers [µm] and larger) will settle to surrounding surfaces within seconds, smaller particles can stay suspended in the air for much longer. It can take several minutes for particles 10 µm in size to settle, while particles 5 µm and smaller may not settle for hours or even days. Dilution ventilation and particle filtration are commonly used to remove these smaller particles from the air. Larger particles can also be removed using these strategies, but since they fall out of the air quickly, they might not have a chance to get captured by filtration systems. The time required to remove airborne particles from a space can be estimated once the source of infectious particles is no longer present and the dilution air is free of new infectious particles (e.g. it is uncontaminated supply air or it is the clean exhaust from a High Efficiency Particulate Air (HEPA) fan/filtration system [See HEPA filtration discussion below]). Table B.1 in the CDC’s Guidelines for Environmental Infection Control in Health-Care Facilities (2003) provides estimates of the time required to remove airborne contaminants, including airborne viral particles, from the air through ventilation dilution, exhaust and filtration. The table provides estimates of the time required for airborne-contaminant removal based upon the room’s ventilation rate, measured in air changes per hour (ACH) and the desired removal efficiency (99% or 99.9%).\nAlthough there are some highly contagious airborne diseases (like measles) where CDC provides specific guidance for 99.9% clearance wait times, the general recommendation in CDC’s Guidelines for Environmental Infection Control in Health-Care Facilities is to wait to allow for a 99% reduction of any generated airborne particles before re-entering the room. In the absence of specific guidance specifying a longer wait period for the virus that causes COVID-19, SARS-CoV-2, the wait time associated with 99% clearance is appropriate for healthcare and other spaces. Regardless of whether the 99% or 99.9% column on Table B.1 is used, the value in the table is usually an under-estimation of the actual dilution clearance time as noted in the table’s footnotes which include the following statement: “The times given assume perfect mixing of the air within the space (i.e., mixing factor = 1). However, perfect mixing usually does not occur. Removal times will be longer in rooms or areas with imperfect mixing or air stagnation.” Appropriate use of Table B.1 to establish clearance times from any space requires multiplying the time in the table by a mixing factor (k) that ranges between 1 and 10. This factor represents how well the ventilation system mixes and dilutes the concentration of airborne particles within the room. As a rule of thumb, rooms with higher airflow rates (6 ACH and higher) and good placement of supply and exhaust grilles (hospital airborne infection isolation rooms) are considered to have “good” mixing and thus a mixing factor of k = 3 is often used for these spaces. In that case, the time identified from Table B.1 should be multiplied by 3 in order to determine the actual clearance time prior to re-entry.  Nonventilated or poorly ventilated spaces have typical values of k ranging from 8 to 10. Increased ACH generally leads to reductions in k, although k can also be reduced by the use of a fan in the space, which does not have an impact on ACH.  Ultimately, wait times can be reduced by increasing ACH, reducing k, or a combination of both.\nExample 1: A room measuring 12 feet x 10 feet with a ceiling height of 9 feet is served with a 100% outdoor air ventilation system that delivers 65 cubic feet per minute (cfm) of supply air (Qs = 65 cfm) and exhausts 72 cfm of air from the room (Qe = 72 cfm). The room has average air mixing, so assign k = 5. How much time is required to reduce the airborne particle concentration by 99 percent?\nSince Qe is larger than Qs by 7 cfm, the heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) system is pulling 7 cfm of air into the room from adjacent areas (i.e., the room is under negative pressure). For this example, the 7 cfm of transfer air is assumed to be free of infectious airborne particles. The clean volumetric air flow rate (Q) is the larger value between Qs and Qe, so Q = 72 cfm. Now, calculate the air changes per hour:\nACH = [Q x 60] / (room volume) = (72 cfm x 60) / (12’ x 10’ x 9’) = 4320/1080 = 4.0 ACH\nUsing Table B.1 the perfect mixing wait time based on 4 ACH and a 99% reduction of airborne particles is 69 minutes.\nUsing the mixing factor of 5, the estimated wait time for 99% reduction of airborne contaminants in the room is 5 x 69 = 345 minutes or 5 hours and 45 minutes.\nNote:  Determining the true value of the mixing factor is difficult and requires special equipment to measure air flows and conduct tracer gas decay testing. Thus, conservative estimates of k are often used (as described above).  Also, the addition of an air cleaning device (e.g., a portable HEPA filtration unit) within the same room will reduce the wait time.  The flow rate from the air cleaning device can be added to Q determined above, which will increase the overall ACH in the room.  The air movement created by the air cleaning device can also decrease the value of k.  Together, the increased ACH and decreased k can help substantially reduce wait times. See Example 2 for more information, including an example of the calculations."},{"id":639,"category":"General Business : Ventilation","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/general-business-faq.html","question":"Can ventilation filters effectively capture SARS-CoV-2 viral particles?","response":"Filters for use in heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) systems are generally tested under procedures outlined in ANSI/ASHRAE Standard 52.2-2017-Method of Testing General Ventilation Air-Cleaning Devices for Removal Efficiency by Particle Size. To access the standard, the end user typically must purchase it, but ASHRAE, which is a global society focused on building systems, indoor air quality, and sustainability in the built environment, has made it available for free online viewingexternal icon during the ongoing pandemic. Based on the filtration efficiency determined by the testing procedures, filters are assigned a Minimum Efficiency Reporting Value (MERV). The MERV provides a measure of the “filter efficiency” over the range of particle sizes prescribed in the test procedure. MERV values range from 1 to 16 and higher MERV values correspond to more efficient filters.\nResearch shows that the particle size of SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, is around 0.1 micrometer (µm). However, the virus generally does not travel through the air by itself. These viral particles are human-generated, so the virus is trapped in respiratory droplets and droplet nuclei (dried respiratory droplets) that are larger than an individual virus. Most of the respiratory droplets and particles exhaled during talking, singing, breathing, and coughing are less than 5 µm in size. CDC recommends using the highest efficiency ventilation filters possible, without having detrimental effects on overall HVAC system performance. ASHRAE, has similar guidance, however, they recommend a minimum filtration efficiency target of MERV 13, provided there are not substantial negative impacts on the HVAC system performance and occupant comfort. A MERV 13 filter is at least 50% efficient at capturing particles in the 0.3 µm to 1.0 µm size range and 85% efficient at capturing particles in the 1 µm to 3 µm size range.  Collectively these particles are capable of remaining airborne for hours and are most associated with deep lung penetration. A MERV 14 filter is at least 75% and 90% efficient, respectively, at capturing those same particles. Efficiencies for MERV 15 and MERV 16 filters are even higher. Thus, the recommended filters are significantly more efficient at capturing particles of concern than a typical MERV 8 filter, which is only around 20% efficient in the 1 µm to 3 µm size range and is not rated for capture efficiency of the smaller 0.3 µm to 1.0 µm particles.\nIncreasing filtration efficiency can increase the pressure drop across the filters. This can lead to increased fan energy, reduced airflow rates, and/or issues controlling indoor temperature and relative humidity levels. Scientific developments in filter design have reduced the amount of the increased pressure drop and its resulting impact on HVAC operations, but not all filters have adopted the newer technology. Prior to a filtration upgrade, the specific filter under consideration should be investigated for its pressure drop ratings at the flow rate(s) of intended use and the potential impacts of that pressure drop evaluated against the capabilities of the existing HVAC system.\nHigh-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filters are even more efficient at filtering human-generated infectious particles than MERV 16 filters. However, outside of a few unique applications, HEPA filters are rarely used in central HVAC systems. [See the question on Portable HEPA Filtration to learn more about them and their application in protective air cleaning]."},{"id":640,"category":"General Business : Ventilation","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/general-business-faq.html","question":"What is meant by “directional airflow?” How and where should we use it?","response":"Directional Airflow is a protective ventilation concept where air movement flows in a clean-to-less-clean direction. This ventilation concept is applied to areas where the “clean” environment requires a higher level of protection and/or where the “less-clean” environment has a higher risk of containing airborne contaminants (activities or occupancy by individuals with a higher risk of being infectious). Examples of “clean” spaces might include healthcare facility triage stations or rooms/corridors adjacent to higher risk activities. Examples of “less-clean” spaces might include spaces that contain known/suspect infectious persons or spaces where a known activity has increased likelihood of generating infectious airborne particles.\nThe creation of directional airflow can be accomplished within a particular space or between two adjacent spaces. This can be done passively, through intentional placement of supply and exhaust heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) grills or by the intentional creation of pressure differentials between adjacent spaces through specification of offset exhaust and supply air flow rates. Creation of the directional airflow can also be done actively, through the use of fans exhausting through open windows, strategic placement of ductwork attached to portable HEPA filtration units, or dedicated exhaust systems (installed or portable) that generate a desired airflow by exhausting air out of windows, doorways, or through temporary ducts.  In specific settings, specialized local control ventilation interventions that establish the desired airflow directions can also be used (see the NIOSH Ventilated Headboard).\nDirectional airflows must be evaluated carefully. Testing of the directional airflow effectiveness can be accomplished using visual tracer techniques that use “smoke tubes” or handheld “fog generators.” Other tools, such electronic monitors or visual aids to monitor pressure differences can be used when directional airflow is established between two adjacent spaces. To reduce the potential for directing airflow from infectious towards non-infectious space occupants, it is important that the “clean” and “less-clean” space determinations be established using infection control risk assessment considerations."},{"id":641,"category":"General Business : Ventilation","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/general-business-faq.html","question":"What is a HEPA filter and why would I want to use a portable HEPA air cleaner?","response":"Research shows that the particle size of SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, is around 0.1 micrometer (µm). However, the virus generally does not travel through the air by itself. These viral particles are human-generated, so the virus is trapped in respiratory droplets and droplet nuclei (dried respiratory droplets) that are larger. Most of the respiratory droplets and particles exhaled during talking, singing, breathing, and coughing are less than 5 µm in size. By definition, a High Efficiency Particulate Air (HEPA) filter is at least 99.97% efficient at capturing particles 0.3 µm in size. This 0.3 µm particle approximates the most penetrating particle size (MPPS) through the filter. HEPA filters are even more efficient at capturing particles larger and smaller than the MPPS. Thus, HEPA filters are no less than 99.97% efficient at capturing human-generated viral particles associated with SARS-CoV-2.\nPortable HEPA filtration units that combine a HEPA filter with a powered fan system are a great option for auxiliary air cleaning, especially in higher risk settings such as health clinics, medical testing locations, workout rooms, or public waiting areas. Other settings that could benefit from portable HEPA filtration can be identified using typical risk assessment parameters, such as community incidence rates, facemask compliance expectations and room occupant density. In choosing a portable HEPA unit, you want to select a system that is appropriately sized for the area in which it is installed. One way to do this for room air cleaners is to select a HEPA fan system with a Clean Air Delivery Rate (CADR) [See EPA’s Guide To Air Cleaners In The Homepdf iconexternal icon] that meets or exceeds the square footage of the room in which it will be used. The larger the CADR, the faster it will clean the room air. If the room in which the air cleaner will be used is taller than 8 feet, choose an air cleaner with a proportionally higher CADR than that based simply on square footage. While these systems do not bring in outdoor dilution air, they are very effective at cleaning air within spaces to reduce the concentration of airborne particulates, including SARS-CoV-2 viral particles. Thus, they give effective air exchanges without the need for conditioning outdoor air.\nHEPA fan systems can be used as stand-alone units, or many larger units allow flexible ductwork to be attached to the air inlet and/or outlet (note that larger ducted units don’t fall under the “room air cleaner” description and may not have a CADR rating). Using ductwork and placing the HEPA system strategically in the space can help provide desired clean-to-less-clean airflow patterns where needed. Ducted HEPA systems can also be used to establish direct source capture interventions for patient treatment and /or testing scenarios (See CDC/NIOSH discussion on Ventilated Headboard). Depending on the size of the HEPA fan/filter units and how the facility in which they are being used is configured, multiple small portable HEPA units deployed to high risk areas may be more useful than one large HEPA unit serving a combined space.\nExample 2:  The room described in Example 1 is now augmented with a portable HEPA air cleaning device with a CADR of 145 cfm (Qhepa = 145 cfm). The added air movement within the room improves overall mixing, so assign k = 3. How much time is saved to achieve the same 99% reduction in airborne contaminants by adding the portable HEPA device to the room?\nThe addition of the HEPA filter device provides additional clean air to the room.  Here, the clean volumetric air flow rate (Q) is:  Q = Qe + Qhepa = 72 cfm + 145 cfm = 217 cfm.\nACH = [Q x 60] / (room volume) = (217 cfm x 60) / (12’ x 10’ x 9’) = 13,020/1080 = 12.06 ACH (round down to 12).\nUsing Table B.1, the perfect mixing wait time based on 12 ACH and a 99% reduction of airborne particles is 23 minutes.\nUsing the mixing factor of 3, the estimated wait time for 99% reduction of airborne contaminants in the room is 3 x 23 = 69 minutes.  Thus, the increased ACH and lower k value associated with the portable HEPA filtration unit reduced the wait time from the original 5 hours and 45 minutes to only 1 hour and 9 minutes, saving a total of 4 hours and 36 minutes before the room can be safely reoccupied.\nIn conclusion, adding the portable HEPA unit increased the effective ventilation rate and improved room air mixing, resulting in an 80% reduction in time for the room to be cleared of potentially-infectious airborne particles."},{"id":642,"category":"General Business : Ventilation","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/general-business-faq.html","question":"Does germicidal ultraviolet (GUV) disinfection kill the virus that causes COVID-19?","response":"Yes.\nGermicidal Ultraviolet (GUV), or Ultraviolet Germicidal Irradiation (UVGI), is a disinfection tool used in many different settings, such as residential, commercial, educational, and healthcare. The technology uses ultraviolet (UV) energy to inactivate (kill) microorganisms, including viruses, when designed and installed correctly.\nThere is still a lot to learn about SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, and the possibility of airborne viral particles and spread. However, GUV can inactivate viruses in the air and on surfaces*. The design and sizing of effective GUV disinfection systems requires specific knowledge and experience.\nBe sure to seek consultation with a reputable GUV manufacturer or an experienced GUV system designer prior to installing GUV systems. These professionals can assist by doing necessary calculations, making fixture selections, properly installing the system, and testing for proper operation specific to the setting.\n*Note: CDC’s recommendation for primary surface disinfection in occupied environments is to follow the CDC/EPA guidance for surface disinfection."},{"id":643,"category":"General Business : Ventilation","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/general-business-faq.html","question":"What are types of germicidal ultraviolet (GUV) for cleaning and disinfection in the workplace?","response":"Upper-room GUV\nUpper-room (or upper-air) GUV uses specially designed GUV fixtures mounted on walls or ceilings to create a disinfection zone of ultraviolet (UV) energy that is focused up and away from people. These fixtures disinfect air as it circulates from mechanical ventilation, ceiling fans, or natural air movement. The advantage of upper-room GUV is that it disinfects the air closer to and above people who are in the room. Since the 1980s, GUV systems have been widely used for control of tuberculosis (TB). The CDC guidance Environmental Control for Tuberculosis: Basic Upper-Room Ultraviolet Germicidal Irradiation Guidelines for Healthcare Settingspdf icon provides information on appropriate GUV system design, related safe operation, and maintenance. Based on data from other human coronaviruses, a GUV system designed to protect against the spread of TB should be effective at inactivating SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, and therefore prevent spread. GUV systems usually require a few GUV fixtures to be effective. For example, a rectangular-shaped waiting room with 10–30 occupants will require 2–3 upper-air GUV fixtures. Of note, the potential for reflection of UV energy into the lower occupied space is a potential safety concern with upper-room GUV systems. However, a reputable GUV manufacturer or an experienced GUV system designer should know the precautionary techniques to prevent harmful UV exposures to people in the space. [Potential Application: Can be used in any indoor environment; most useful in spaces highly occupied with people who are or may be sick.]\nIn-Duct GUV\nIn-duct GUV systems are installed within a heating, ventilation, and air-conditioning (HVAC) system. These systems are designed to serve one of two purposes:\n\nCoil treatment GUV keeps HVAC coils, drain pans, and wetted surfaces free of microbial growth. These devices produce relatively low levels of UV energy. This energy is continually delivered 24 hours a day, which is why they are effective. Coil treatment GUV devices are not designed for disinfecting the air and should not be installed for the purpose of air disinfection. [Potential Application: Can be used to reduce HVAC maintenance and improve operational efficiency within large, commercial HVAC systems or residential HVAC systems; not recommended for inactivating airborne pathogens.]\nAir disinfection GUV systems can be effective at inactivating airborne pathogens as they flow within the HVAC duct. HVAC air disinfection GUV systems generally require more powerful UV lamps or a greater number of lamps, or both, to provide the necessary GUV required to inactivate pathogens in a short period of time. Air disinfection systems are often placed downstream of the HVAC coils. This location keeps the coil, drain pan, and wetted surfaces free of microbial growth and also disinfects the moving air. [Potential Application: Can be used inside any HVAC system to disinfect infectious airborne pathogens.]\n\n\nFar-UV (or Far-UVC)\nFar-UV is one of many emerging technologies that have become popular during the COVID-19 pandemic. While standard GUV fixtures emit UV energy at a wavelength around 254 nanometers (nm), far-UV devices use different lamps to emit UV energy at a wavelength around 222 nm. Aside from the wavelength, a major difference between the two technologies is that standard GUV systems are specifically designed to avoid exposing people to the UV energy, while many far-UV devices are marketed as safe for exposing people and their direct environment to UV energy. A review of peer-reviewed literature indicates that far-UV wavelengths can effectively inactivate microorganisms, including human coronaviruses, when appropriate UV doses are applied. Questions remain about the mechanisms of killing microorganisms and overall safety. Far-UV might prove to be effective at disinfecting air and surfaces, without some of the safety precautions required for standard GUV. Far-UV devices are best viewed as new and emerging technology. [Potential Application: Yet to be determined.] Consumers considering an emerging technology such as Far-UV can research the proposed system. Ask the vendor to provide proof of effectiveness and performance that demonstrates a clear protective benefit. Engage with a ventilation engineer, and if the engineer recommends installing such a system, obtain a guarantee as to expected disinfection performance. When evaluating evidence of system effectiveness, place emphasis on research publications over anecdotal claims and consider the following questions:\n\nAre there independent studies that prove the desired performance of the technology?\nDid the study environments represent your environment and intended use?\nHave performance results been published in a scientific or medical journal?\nWas the technology evaluated for potential adverse health effects or occupational exposures?\nWhere is the technology being used?"},{"id":644,"category":"General Business : Ventilation","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/general-business-faq.html","question":"Many new air disinfection devices are being marketed for their ability to inactivate the virus that causes COVID-19. How can I tell if they work as advertised?","response":"CDC does not provide recommendations for, or against, any manufacturer or product. There are numerous devices being heavily marketed to provide air cleaning during the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic. Some of the most common are ionization and/or dry hydrogen peroxide devices. Some devices even include both technologies. While variations of these technologies have been around for decades, relative to other air cleaning or disinfection technologies, they have a less-documented track record when it comes to cleaning/disinfecting large and fast volumes of moving air within heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) systems or even inside individual rooms. This does not necessarily imply the technologies do not work as advertised. However, in the absence of an established body of peer-reviewed evidence showing proven efficacy and safety under as-used conditions, the technologies are still considered by many to be “emerging.” As with all emerging technologies, consumers are encouraged to exercise caution and to do their homework. Consumers should research the technology, attempting to match any specific claims against the intended use of the product. Consumers should request testing data that quantitively demonstrates a clear protective benefit and occupant safety under conditions consistent with the intended use. Preferably, the documented performance data under as-used conditions should be available from multiple sources, some of which should be independent, third party sources. Unsubstantiated claims of performance or limited case studies with only one device in one room and no reference controls should be questioned. At a minimum, if you are considering the acquisition and use of these devices, you will want to be sure the equipment meets UL 867 standard certification (Standard for Electrostatic Air Cleaners) for production of acceptable levels of ozone, or preferably UL 2998 standard certification (Environmental Claim Validation Procedure (ECVP) for Zero Ozone Emissions from Air Cleaners) which is intended to validate that no ozone is produced."},{"id":645,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"Should I wear a respirator in public?","response":"Most often, spread of respiratory viruses from person-to-person happens among close contacts (within 6 feet). Recent studies indicate that people who are infected but do not have symptoms likely also play a role in the spread of COVID-19. CDC recommends everyday preventive actions to prevent the spread of respiratory viruses, such as avoiding people who are sick, avoiding touching your eyes or nose, and covering your cough or sneeze with a tissue. People who are sick should stay home and not go into crowded public places or visit people in hospitals. Workers who are sick should follow CDC guidelines and stay home when they are sick."},{"id":646,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"What is a respirator?","response":"A respirator is a personal protective device that is worn on the face or head and covers at least the nose and mouth. A respirator is used to reduce the wearer’s risk of inhaling hazardous airborne particles (including infectious agents), gases or vapors. Respirators, including those intended for use in healthcare settings, are certified by the CDC/NIOSH."},{"id":647,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"What is an N95 filtering facepiece respirator (FFR)?","response":"An N95 FFR is a type of respirator which removes particles from the air that are breathed through it. These respirators filter out at least 95% of very small (0.3 micron) particles. N95 FFRs are capable of filtering out all types of particles, including bacteria and viruses."},{"id":648,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"What makes N95 respirators different from facemasks (sometimes called a surgical mask)?","response":"Infographic: Understanding the difference between surgical masks and N95 respiratorspdf icon\nN95 respirators reduce the wearer’s exposure to airborne particles, from small particle aerosols to large droplets. N95 respirators are tight-fitting respirators that filter out at least 95% of particles in the air, including large and small particles.\nNot everyone is able to wear a respirator due to medical conditions that may be made worse when breathing through a respirator. Before using a respirator or getting fit-tested, workers must have a medical evaluation to make sure that they are able to wear a respirator safely.\nAchieving an adequate seal to the face is essential. United States regulations require that workers undergo an annual fit test and conduct a user seal check each time the respirator is used. Workers must pass a fit test to confirm a proper seal before using a respirator in the workplace.\nWhen properly fitted and worn, minimal leakage occurs around edges of the respirator when the user inhales. This means almost all of the air is directed through the filter media.\nUnlike NIOSH-approved N95s, facemasks are loose-fitting and provide only barrier protection against droplets, including large respiratory particles. No fit testing or seal check is necessary with facemasks. Most facemasks do not effectively filter small particles from the air and do not prevent leakage around the edge of the mask when the user inhales.\nThe role of facemasks is for patient source control, to prevent contamination of the surrounding area when a person coughs or sneezes.  Patients with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 should wear a facemask until they are isolated in a hospital or at home. The patient does not need to wear a facemask while isolated."},{"id":649,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"What is a Surgical N95 respirator and who needs to wear it?","response":"A surgical N95 (also referred as a medical respirator) is recommended only for use by healthcare personnel (HCP) who need protection from both airborne and fluid hazards (e.g., splashes, sprays). These respirators are not used or needed outside of healthcare settings. In times of shortage, only HCP who are working in a sterile field or who may be exposed to high velocity splashes, sprays, or splatters of blood or body fluids should wear these respirators, such as in operative or procedural settings. Most HCP caring for confirmed or suspected COVID-19 patients should not need to use surgical N95 respirators and can use standard N95 respirators.\nIf a surgical N95 is not available for use in operative or procedural settings, then an unvalved N95 respirator may be used with a faceshield to help block high velocity streams of blood and body fluids."},{"id":650,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"My employees complain that Surgical N95 respirators are hot and uncomfortable - what can I do?","response":"The requirements for surgical N95 respirators that make them resistant to high velocity streams of body fluids and help protect the sterile field can result in a design that has a higher breathing resistance (makes it more difficult to breath) than a typical N95 respirator. Also, surgical N95 respirators are designed without exhalation valves which are sometimes perceived as warmer inside the mask than typical N95 respirators. If you are receiving complaints, you may consider having employees who are not doing surgery, not working in a sterile field, or not potentially exposed to high velocity streams of body fluids wear a standard N95 with an exhalation valve."},{"id":651,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"My N95 filtering facepiece respirator has an exhalation valve. Is that okay? Will it protect both me and others?","response":"Yes, an N95 filtering facepiece respirator will protect you and provide source control to protect others. A NIOSH-approved N95 filtering facepiece respirator with an exhalation valve offers the same protection to the wearer as one that does not have a valve. As source control, findings from NIOSH research suggest that, even without covering the valve, N95 respirators with exhalation valves provide the same or better source control than surgical masks, procedure masks, cloth masks, or fabric coverings. In general, individuals wearing NIOSH-approved N95s with an exhalation valve should not be asked to use one without an exhalation valve or to cover it with a face covering or mask. However, NIOSH-approved N95 respirators with an exhalation valve are not fluid resistant. Therefore, in situations where a fluid resistant respirator is indicated (e.g., in surgical settings), individuals should wear a surgical N95 or, if a surgical N95 is not available, cover their respirator with a surgical mask or a face shield.  Be careful not to compromise the fit of the respirator when placing a facemask over the respirator."},{"id":652,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"Can I use an elastomeric respirator as source control?","response":"Until more is understood on exhalation valves, elastomeric respirators with unfiltered exhalation valves should not be used as source control in surgical and other healthcare settings due to concerns that air coming out of the exhalation valve may contaminate the sterile field. The NIOSH Certified Equipment List identifies the elastomeric respirators without exhalation valves or with filtered exhalation valves that may be used in surgical settings."},{"id":653,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"How can I tell if a respirator is NIOSH-approved?","response":"The NIOSH approval number and approval label are key to identifying NIOSH-approved respirators. The  NIOSH approval label can be found on or within the packaging of the respirator or sometimes on the respirator itself. The required labeling of NIOSH-Approved N95 filtering facepiece respiratorspdf icon  includes the NIOSH name, the approval number, filter designations, lot number, and model number to be printed on the respirator. You can verify that your respirator approvals are valid by checking the NIOSH Certified Equipment List (CEL)."},{"id":654,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"How do I know if a respirator is falsely advertising NIOSH-approval?","response":"When NIOSH becomes aware of counterfeit respirators or those misrepresenting NIOSH approval on the market, these respirators are posted on the Counterfeit Respirators / Misrepresentation of NIOSH-Approval webpage to alert users, purchasers, and manufacturers."},{"id":655,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"How do I know if my respirator is expired?","response":"NIOSH does not require approved N95 filtering facepiece respirators (FFRs) be marked with an expiration date. If an FFR does not have an assigned expiration date, you should refer to the user instructions or seek guidance from the specific manufacturer on whether time and storage conditions (such as temperature or humidity) are expected to have an effect on the respirator’s performance and if the respirators are nearing the end of their shelf life."},{"id":656,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"What do I do with an expired respirator?","response":"In times of increased demand and decreased supply, consideration can be made to use N95 respirators past their intended shelf life. However, the potential exists that the respirator will not perform to the requirements for which it was certified. Over time, components such as the strap and nose bridge may degrade, which can affect the quality of the fit and seal. Prior to use of N95 respirators, the HCP should inspect the respirator and perform a seal check. Additionally, expired respirators may potentially no longer meet the certification requirements set by NIOSH. For further guidance, visit Release of Stockpiled N95 Filtering Facepiece Respirators Beyond the Manufacturer-Designated Shelf Life: Considerations for the COVID-19 Response."},{"id":657,"category":"Personal Protective Equipment : Respirators","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/respirator-use-faq.html","question":"What methods should healthcare facilities consider in order to avoid unintentional loss of PPE during COVID-19?","response":"Monitoring PPE supply inventory and maintaining control over PPE supplies may help prevent unintentional product losses that may occur due to theft, damage, or accidental loss. Inventory systems should be employed to track daily usage and identify areas of higher than expected use.  This information can be used to implement additional conservation strategies tailored to specific patient care areas such as hospital units or outpatient facilities.  Inventory tracking within a health system may also assist in confirming PPE deliveries and optimizing distribution of PPE supplies to specific facilities."},{"id":658,"category":"Retirement Communities and Independent Living Facilities : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/retirement/faq.html","question":"What actions can residents and staff take to prevent the spread of COVID-19?","response":"Encourage residents and staff to take everyday preventive actions to prevent the spread of respiratory illnesses. Actions include staying home when sick; appropriately covering coughs and sneezes; cleaning and then disinfecting frequently touched surfaces; and washing hands often with soap and water."},{"id":659,"category":"Retirement Communities and Independent Living Facilities : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/retirement/faq.html","question":"How can my retirement community or independent living facility prepare for COVID-19?","response":"Administrators should take the following actions to prevent a COVID-19 outbreak in their community or facility:\n\nPromote social distancing\n\nCancel public or group activities and events\nInform workers and volunteers to avoid close contact with residents\nWhen possible, limit visitors and volunteers to essential persons\nAdvise residents to stay home and avoid public places\nAlter schedules to reduce mixing (e.g., stagger meal, activity, arrival/departure times)\n\n\nSupport residents in preparing\n\nEstablish the ‘buddy’ system to ensure residents stay connected.\nEncourage residents to have extra medications and supplies.\nIdentify residents with unique needs and work with them to tailor these strategies.\nFind ways to support residents in managing stress and anxiety.\nInform residents using print materials and high-visibility posters\n\n\nEncourage everyone to take everyday preventive actions to prevent the spread of respiratory illnesses.\n\nCover coughs and sneezes\nClean and disinfect frequently touched surfaces\nWash hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds\nEnsure hand hygiene supplies (e.g., hand sanitizer containing at least 60% alcohol) are readily available in all buildings.\n\n\nMonitor for cases and take action when someone is sick.\n\nScreen workers and when possible volunteers\nAsk residents to self-monitor for symptoms\nReview the usual absenteeism patterns at your facility among staff, so you can identify if the rate of absenteeism increases.\nImplement flexible sick-leave policies and actively encourage sick employees to stay home\nCoordinate with local health facilities if you suspect a resident or staff member may have COVID-19"},{"id":660,"category":"Retirement Communities and Independent Living Facilities : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/retirement/faq.html","question":"What resources does CDC have available to share with facilities?","response":"Share resources with the community to help them understand COVID-19 and steps they can take to protect themselves:\n\nCDC COVID-19 business guidance\nCDC COVID-19 healthcare guidance\nCDC COVID-19 household guidance\nCDC Make a Kit\nCDC’s health communication resources\nCDC offers several free handwashing resources that include health promotion materials and information on proper handwashing technique."},{"id":661,"category":"Retirement Communities and Independent Living Facilities : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/retirement/faq.html","question":"Does CDC have recommendations for cleaning and disinfecting surfaces?","response":"Clean high-touch surfaces and objects regularly (for example, daily or after each use) and after you have visitors in your home. Focus on high- touch surfaces and objects (doorknobs, tables, light switches, phones, remote controls and countertops) with cleaners that you typically use. Practice strict infection control procedures if there is a case in your facility.\nFollow CDC’s Cleaning Recommendations for Communities."},{"id":662,"category":"Retirement Communities and Independent Living Facilities : Planning and Preparedness : If there is a case in the facility","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/retirement/faq.html","question":"What should administrators do if a resident or staff shows symptoms of COVID-19?","response":"Ask residents to actively monitor (at least daily) for COVID-19 symptoms, including fever and respiratory symptoms (shortness of breath, new or change in cough). Administrators should work with local health authorities to establish procedures for those who become sick. Sick residents should avoid contact with individuals who are healthy. If you think someone may have COVID-19, ask them to self-isolate and you should contact local health officials."},{"id":663,"category":"Retirement Communities and Independent Living Facilities : Planning and Preparedness : If there is a case in the facility","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/retirement/faq.html","question":"What should administrators do if there is a case of COVID-19 in our facility?","response":"Work with local health authorities to communicate the possible exposure to residents, staff, and visitors. Clean and disinfect all shared facilities and high-touch surfaces. Limit visitors to essential staff  and visitors. Staff and, when possible, visitors should be screened for signs and symptoms of COVID-19 before entering the facility. Residents will need to actively monitor their health for COVID-19 symptoms. Cancel group activities. Residences that become ill should be advised to call the medical facility in advance of their visit. See CDC’s full interim guidance for more details."},{"id":664,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What steps should I take to prepare my facility?","response":"Because of close contact and the number of people in correctional and detention facilities (including prisons and jails), staff and people who are incarcerated are at greater risk for the spread of germs. To help your facility prepare for the possible spread of COVID-19, update your emergency operations plan. This includes:\n\nAdding key COVID-19 prevention strategies and posting information in the facility on how to limit the spread of germs.\nReminding staff to stay home when sick.\nIdentifying points of contact for local public health agencies.\nIdentifying physical locations (dedicated housing areas and bathrooms) where you can medically isolate incarcerated persons, as well as where to quarantine known close contacts of people with COVID-19.\n\nFollow guidance on medical isolation and quarantine.\nMedical isolation and quarantine locations should be separate.\n\n\nOffering flu shots to staff and people who are incarcerated, because limiting cases of flu can help speed the identification of people with COVID-19.\nDeveloping ways to continue providing critical services, such as mental health support.\nEnsuring adequate stocks of hygiene, cleaning, and medical supplies.\n\nHygiene: Soap (preferably liquid to promote use), tissues, and hand drying supplies, as well as hand sanitizers, when possible. Ensure no-cost access to soap.\nCleaning: EPA-registered disinfectantsexternal icon effective against the virus that causes COVID-19\nMedical supplies: Supplies for daily clinic needs, personal protective equipment (PPE), and testing\n\n\nCreating and testing communications plans to share critical information.\nSetting up systems to safely transfer people between facilities and identifying alternative strategies to in-person court appearances, when possible.\n\nPrevent confirmed and suspected COVID-19 cases and their close contacts from being transferred between jurisdictions and facilities unless necessary for medical evaluation, medical isolation/quarantine, clinical care, extenuating security concerns, or to prevent overcrowding.\n\n\nPlanning for staff absenteeism.\n\nFollow CDC guidance on recommended PPE for staff who will have direct contact with an individual with possible COVID-19 infection, or infectious materials. Make contingency plans for the likely event of PPE shortages.\nFollow the CDC Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) and monitor the guidance website regularly for updates for staff evaluating and providing care for confirmed or suspected COVID-19 cases. When no on-site healthcare capacity is available, make a plan for how to ensure that people suspected to have COVID-19 will be medically isolated, evaluated, tested (if indicated), and provided medical care. Contact and collaborate with your state, local, tribal and territorial health departments for more specific guidance."},{"id":665,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"How can I lower the chance that my staff will get COVID-19?","response":"The best way to protect your staff is to prevent exposure. Start by:\n\nStaying informed about updates to CDC guidance via the CDC COVID-19 website.\nMaking sure staff are aware of COVID-19 symptoms and requiring staff with any flu-like symptoms to stay home (or be sent home if they develop symptoms while at the facility).\nOffering telework for staff when feasible, and exploring ways to revise duties that require face-to-face interaction for staff at high-risk for severe illness.\nEnsuring staff use everyday preventive actions (such as washing hands, avoiding touching their eyes, nose, and mouth, covering their cough).\nManaging and monitoring staff absenteeism.\n\nAlert local public health officials about large increases in staff absenteeism, particularly if absences appear due to respiratory illnesses (like the common cold or the flu, which have symptoms similar to COVID-19).\n\n\nOffering flu shots to staff, as limiting cases of flu can speed up the identification of people with COVID-19.\nStocking and providing supplies that help prevent the spread of germs.\nRoutinely cleaning and disinfecting the facility.\nConsult CDC guidance on recommended PPE for persons in direct contact with COVID-19 cases.\n\nReview the Occupational Safety and Health Administration websiteexternal iconexternal icon and guidance for businesses and employers to identify any additional strategies the facility can use within its role as an employer.\nStaff evaluating and providing care for people with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 should follow the CDC Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) and monitor the guidance website regularly for updates to these recommendations. Facilities without on-site health care capacity should make a plan for how they will ensure that suspected COVID-19 cases will be medically isolated, evaluated, tested (if indicated), and provided medical care. Contact and collaborate with your state, local, tribal, and territorial health departments for more specific guidance."},{"id":666,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"How can I lower the chance that people who are incarcerated will get COVID-19?","response":"The best way to prevent illness among people who are incarcerated is to prevent exposure to the virus that causes COVID-19. Start by:\n\nStaying informed about updates to CDC guidance via the CDC COVID-19 website.\nMaking sure people who are incarcerated are aware of COVID-19 symptoms and remind them to notify staff right away if they might be sick.\nPosting information about and ensuring they use everyday preventive actions (such as washing hands, avoiding touching their eyes, nose, and mouth, covering their cough).\nStocking up and providing free access to soap (preferably liquid soap to promote use), tissues, and hand drying supplies, as well as hand sanitizer (where permitted based on security restrictions).\nConducting temperature checks and screening all new entrants, staff, and visitors for flu-like symptoms during the last 24 hours, and any contact they may have had with someone infected with COVID-19 in the last 14 days.\nOffering flu shots to people who are incarcerated, as limiting cases of flu can help speed the identification of people with COVID-19.\nRoutinely cleaning and disinfecting surfaces and objects that are frequently touched."},{"id":667,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"How can I find out if the virus has spread to the local community close to my facility?","response":"You can get up-to-date information about local COVID-19 activity by keeping in touch with your local and state public health officialsexternal iconexternal icon, and keeping up-to-date with the CDC website."},{"id":668,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What steps should I take to protect my staff and people who are incarcerated if there is spread of COVID-19 in the local community close to my facility?","response":"If COVID-19 is known to be spreading in the local community close to your facility, but there are no confirmed cases among people who are incarcerated, staff, or visitors who have been inside the facility within the past 14 days:\n\nImplement operational actions:\n\nRestrict non-essential transfers of people between facilities and systems.\nUse alternative strategies to limit in-person court appearances where possible.\nConsider suspending co-pays for incarcerated persons seeking medical evaluation for COVID-19 symptoms.\nRequire staff to stay home if they are sick.\nConsider suspending visitation or offering non-contact visits only.\nDo not allow non-essential vendors, volunteers, or tours into the facility.\nConsider suspending work release programs.\n\n\n\n\nClean and disinfect the facility:\n\nUse CDC recommendations for cleaning and disinfection during the COVID-19 response to routinely clean and disinfect surfaces and objects that are frequently touched, especially in common areas.\nUse household cleaners and EPA-registered disinfectants effective against the virus that causes COVID-19external iconexternal icon\n\n\nFocus on good hygiene:\n\nRemind staff, visitors, and people who are incarcerated to use everyday preventive actions (such as washing hands, avoiding touching their eyes, nose, and mouth, covering their cough).Provide free access to soap (preferably liquid soap) and access to running water, hand dryers, tissues, and no-touch trash cans, when possible.\n\n\nContinually restock hygiene supplies throughout the facility.\nConsider increasing the number of staff and/or other people who are trained to clean common areas to ensure they are cleaned on a continual basis.\nConduct screenings for symptoms and fever on all new entrants, staff, and visitors prior to entering the facility and follow guidance.\nUse options to increase social distancing (increasing the physical space between people in the facility, ideally at least 6 feet between people, regardless of whether or not they have symptoms):\n\nIncrease space between people who are incarcerated in holding cells and when in line.\nStagger mealtimes and time in recreation spaces.\nLimit interactions in large group settings and group programs.\nWhen possible, place beds at least 6 feet apart and have people sleep head-to-foot.\nFind a separate space to check people for COVID-19 that is close to each housing unit instead of having people who are sick walk through the facility to be medically evaluated.\nRemind staff to keep 6 feet apart from an individual with respiratory symptoms when possible.\n\n\n Communicate regularly:\n\nProvide up-to-date information and remind and encourage people who are incarcerated and staff to report COVID-19 symptoms to staff right away."},{"id":669,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What should be included in my screening procedures for new entrants to the facility?","response":"New entrants should undergo temperature screening in addition to the following verbal screening questions:\n\n“Today or in the past 24 hours, have you had any of the following symptoms? Fever, felt feverish, or had chills? Cough? Difficulty breathing?”\n\nIf yes, give them a clean, disposable facemask, separate them from others, and notify medical staff. Ensure only trained personnel wearing recommended PPE have contact with individuals who have or may have COVID-19.\nFacilities without on-site healthcare staff should contact their state, local, tribal, and/or territorial health department to coordinate effective medical isolation and necessary medical care.\n\n\n“In the past 14 days, have you had contact with a person known to be infected with the novel coronavirus (COVID-19)?”\n\nIf yes (but no COVID-19 symptoms): Quarantine the individual and monitor for symptoms two times per day for 14 days. During quarantine, facility staff should follow guidance on quarantine, and monitor the person for symptoms two times per day for 14 days.\nFacilities without on-site health care staff should contact their state, local, tribal, and/or territorial health department to coordinate effective medical isolation and necessary medical care."},{"id":670,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What is a safe way to perform temperature checks?","response":"Staff performing temperature checks should follow these steps:\n\nWash hands thoroughly.\nPut on a face mask, eye protection (goggles or disposable face shield that fully covers the front and sides of the face), gown/coveralls, and a single pair of disposable gloves.\nCheck the person’s temperature.\n\n\n\n\nIf performing a temperature check on multiple individuals, ensure that a clean pair of gloves is used for each individual and that the thermometer has been thoroughly cleaned in between each check.\nIf disposable or non-contact thermometers are used and the screener did not have physical contact with an individual, gloves do not need to be changed before the next check. If non-contact thermometers are used, they should be cleaned routinely as recommended by CDC for infection control.\n\n\n\n\nRemove and discard PPE.\nWash hands thoroughly."},{"id":671,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"Should I allow visitors into the facility if there is spread of COVID-19 in the community close to my facility?","response":"If there is spread of COVID-19 in the community close to your facility, consider suspending contact visits. If contact visits continue, all potential visitors should be asked:\n\n“Today or in the past 24 hours, have you had any of the following symptoms? Fever, felt feverish, or had chills? Cough? Difficulty breathing?”\n“In the past 14 days, have you had contact with a person known to be infected with the novel coronavirus (COVID-19)?”\n\nStaff should also perform temperature checks for all visitors and volunteers. Any visitor who answers yes to one of these questions or who declines screening should not be allowed into the facility. When possible, facilities should let potential visitors know about these rules before they travel to the facility. Facilities can place posters in visiting areas and ask people who are incarcerated to inform their family members and visitors about these rules."},{"id":672,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"How should the facility be cleaned to limit spread of the virus?","response":"Cleaning with products containing soap or detergent reduces germs on surfaces and objects by removing contaminants and may also weaken or damage some of the virus particles, which decreases risk of infection from surfaces. Cleaning high touch surfaces and shared objects once a day is usually enough to sufficiently remove virus that may be on surfaces unless someone with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 has been in your facility. For more information on cleaning your facility regularly and cleaning your facility when someone is sick, see Cleaning and Disinfecting Your Facility."},{"id":673,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What should I do if a person who is incarcerated in my facility may have COVID-19?","response":"If you think someone who is incarcerated in the facility is sick with COVID-19 (see COVID-19 symptoms), activate your emergency plan and notify local public health officials. Ensure that the sick person is wearing a clean, disposable facemask, and separate the sick person from others, ideally within an individual housing space and bathroom. Provide them with tissues for when they cough or sneeze, and a lined trash receptacle when possible.\nStaff evaluating and providing care for confirmed or suspected COVID-19 cases should follow the CDC Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) and monitor the guidance website regularly for updates to these recommendations. Facilities without on-site healthcare staff should contact their state, local, tribal, and/or territorial health department to coordinate effective isolation and necessary medical care. Ensure only trained personnel wearing recommended personal protective equipment (PPE) have contact with or transport individuals who have or may have COVID-19.\nPeople who are incarcerated and have COVID-19 should be placed under medical isolation in a separate room, ideally with solid walls and a solid door that closes fully. If not available, refer to the full guidance document for other options for medical isolation. If multiple people become ill with COVID-19:\n\nMake every effort to house each ill person individually, with their own bathroom. Refer to the full guidance document for additional options if individual spaces are not available.\nPrioritize those at high risk for complications of COVID-19 (older adults, people with severe underlying chronic medical conditions) for individual spaces that are available.\n\nTo prevent further spread:\n\nUse options for virtual court appearances, if possible.\nSuspend group gatherings.\nLimit non-medical transfers of people within and between facilities. Ensure that anyone transferred out is screened for symptoms and contact with a COVID-19 case before leaving the facility.\nEnsure that release planning includes screening for COVID-19 symptoms and contact with a case. Coordinate with local public health officials if releasing a symptomatic person to the community.\nUse multiple social distancing strategies.\nHandle laundry and food items of possible or confirmed cases of COVID-19 with recommended PPE.\nSuspend visitation or offer non-contact visitation only.\nConsider quarantining all new entrants for 14 days before they enter the facility. (Make sure that new entrants under quarantine are housed separately from other incarcerated people already under quarantine due to contact with a COVID-19 case.)\nIf releasing someone to a community facility (e.g., a homeless shelter), contact the facility’s staff to ensure adequate time for them to prepare to continue medical isolation, and coordinate with local public health officials.\n\nProvide clear information to staff and people who are incarcerated about the presence of COVID-19 cases within the facility. Close contacts of the sick person (who have been within 6 feet of the sick person or had direct contact with infectious droplets, such as from a cough or sneeze) should be placed under quarantine for at least 14 days. Follow CDC guidance on quarantining close contacts of people with COVID-19.\nIf separate spaces for individual quarantined people are not available, refer to the full guidance document for other options. Monitor symptoms twice per day and move anyone developing symptoms to medical isolation right away (after ensuring they are wearing a face mask). Quarantined people at high risk for complications of COVID-19 (older adults, people with severe underlying chronic medical conditions) should not be housed with other quarantined people if at all possible."},{"id":674,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What should I do if one of my staff might have COVID-19?","response":"If you think someone on your staff is sick with COVID-19 (see COVID-19 symptoms), activate your emergency plan and notify public health officials. Give them a clean, disposable facemaskpdf icon and send them home right away. Close contacts of the sick person (who have been within 6 feet of the sick person or have had direct contact with infectious droplets, such as from a cough or sneeze) should self-quarantine at for 14 days home and follow CDC recommended steps for people who are sick with COVID-19 symptoms."},{"id":675,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What is the best way to clean and disinfect my facility after a confirmed case of COVID-19?","response":"Clean and Disinfect Your Facility When Someone is Sick\nIf there has been a sick person or someone who has COVID-19 in your facility within the last 24 hours, you should clean and disinfect the spaces they occupied.\nBefore cleaning and disinfecting\n\nClose off areas used by the person who is sick and do not use those areas until they have been cleaned and disinfected.\nWait as long as possible (at least several hours) before you clean and disinfect.\n\nWhile cleaning and disinfecting\n\nOpen doors and windows and use fans or HVAC (heating, ventilation, and air conditioning) settings to increase air circulation in the area.\nUse products from EPA List Nexternal icon according to the instructions on the product label.\nWear a mask and gloves while cleaning and disinfecting.\nFocus on the immediate areas occupied by the person who is sick or diagnosed with COVID-19 unless they have already been cleaned and disinfected.\nVacuum the space if needed. Use a vacuum equipped with high-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filter and bags, if available.\n\nWhile vacuuming, temporarily turn off in-room, window-mounted, or on-wall recirculation heating, ventilation, and air conditioning systems to avoid contamination of HVAC units.\nDo NOT deactivate central HVAC systems. These systems provide better filtration capabilities and introduce outdoor air into the areas that they serve.\n\n\n\n\nIt is safe to wash dirty laundry from a person who is sick with COVID-19 with other people’s items, if needed.\nEnsure safe and correct use and storage of cleaning and disinfectant products, including storing such products. Store these products securely and use the necessary PPE.\n\n \n\nTime since person who was sick or diagnosed with COVID-19 was in the facility\n\n\nTime since person who was sick or diagnosed with COVID-19 was in the facility\nWhat to do\n\n\nLess than 24 hours\nClean and disinfect the space\n\n\nMore than 24 hours\nCleaning is enough. You may choose to also disinfect depending on certain conditions or everyday practices required by your facility\n\n\nMore than 3 days\nNo additional cleaning (beyond regular cleaning practices)"},{"id":676,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"Should I allow visitors into the facility?","response":"If there is a case of COVID-19 in your facility, suspend contact visitation programs. Instead, use virtual visitation when possible."},{"id":677,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What do medical staff need to know about caring for a person with COVID-19 in my facility?","response":"Facilities should ensure that incarcerated individuals receive medical evaluation and treatment at the first sign of COVID-19 symptoms. Staff evaluating and providing care for confirmed or suspected COVID-19 cases should follow the CDC Interim Clinical Guidance for Management of Patients with Confirmed Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) and monitor the guidance website regularly for updates to these recommendations. Facilities without on-site healthcare staff should contact their state, local, tribal, and/or territorial health department to coordinate effective medical isolation and necessary medical care. Facilities should have a plan in place to safely transfer persons with complications from COVID-19 to a local hospital if they require care beyond what the facility is able to provide. When evaluating and treating persons with symptoms of COVID-19 who do not speak English, provide a translator when possible. Spanish and Simplified Chinese materials are available for those who need them."},{"id":678,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What steps do I need to take to implement quarantine in my facility?","response":"Close contacts of a sick person (who have been within about 6 feet of the sick person or have had direct contact with infectious droplets, such as from a cough or sneeze) should be placed under quarantine for 14 days to determine if they develop symptoms. CDC has developed guidance on quarantining close contacts of people with COVID-19. Be sure to monitor symptoms twice a day and move anyone developing symptoms to medical isolation right away, after ensuring that they are wearing a face mask. Individuals under quarantine should stay within the quarantine space, including when eating their meals, using the bathroom, and receiving medical evaluation. Laundry of people in quarantine can be washed with the laundry of others. Individuals handling laundry should wear recommended PPE, should not shake the laundry, and should clean their hands often.\nIdeally, people under quarantine due to contact with a COVID-19 case should be housed individually. If separate spaces in a facility are not available, refer to CDC’s full guidance document for correctional and detention centers for other options. People at high risk for complications of COVID-19 (older adults, people with severe underlying chronic medical conditions) should not be housed with other quarantined people if at all possible. Facilities without enough space or without onsite healthcare capacity should coordinate with local public health officials.\nIndividuals in quarantine can be released from quarantine back to their previous housing arrangement in the facility if they have not developed symptoms during the 14-day time period."},{"id":679,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"How can I lower the chance that I will get COVID-19?","response":"The best way to prevent illness is to take steps to avoid being exposed to this virus. Start by ensuring you and others around you use everyday preventive actions (such as washing hands often, avoiding touching your eyes, nose, and mouth, and covering your cough). Read How to Protect Yourself to learn more.\nIf there is spread of COVID-19 in the community close to the facility, you will be asked daily about symptoms over the last 24 hours and any contact you had with someone infected with COVID-19 in the last 14 days. Your temperature will also be checked daily."},{"id":680,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"Do I have a greater chance of getting COVID-19?","response":"Staff and people incarcerated in correctional and detention facilities are at greater risk for some illnesses, such as COVID-19, because of the close living arrangements inside the facility. The virus is thought to spread mainly from person-to-person, through respiratory droplets produced when an infected person coughs or sneezes. These droplets can land in the mouths or noses of people who are nearby or possibly be inhaled into the lungs. It may be possible that a person can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes, but this is not thought to be the main way the virus spreads. This is why washing your hands regularly and avoid close contact with other people when possible prevents illness."},{"id":681,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What should I do if I think I may be sick with COVID-19?","response":"If you think you have been exposed to COVID-19 and develop a fever or symptoms of respiratory illness, such as cough or difficulty breathing, stay home. If you are at work, alert your supervisor right away and go home. Read What To Do if You Are Sick to learn more."},{"id":682,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What does it mean to be in quarantine?","response":"Anyone who has close contact with a person with COVID-19 will need to stay away from other people for at least 14 days to see whether symptoms develop. If you are a close contact of a person with COVID-19, you should self-quarantine at home by staying in a separate room away from others. Read Caring for Yourself at Home and What To Do if You Are Sick to learn more."},{"id":683,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What do I need to know about COVID-19?","response":"For information on what you need to know about COVID-19, please visit What You Need to Know about COVID-19 if You are Incarcerated/Detained pdf icon[PDF – 253 KB] | Spanish version pdf icon[PDF – 227 KB]"},{"id":684,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"How can I lower the chance that I will get COVID-19?","response":"The best way to prevent illness is to take steps to avoid being exposed to this virus. Start by ensuring you and others around you use everyday preventive actions (such as washing hands often, avoiding touching your eyes, nose, and mouth, and covering your cough). Read How to Protect Yourself to learn more."},{"id":685,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"Do I have a greater chance of getting COVID-19?","response":"People in correctional and detention facilities are at greater risk for some illnesses, such as COVID-19, because of close living arrangements with other people. The virus is thought to spread mainly from person-to-person, through respiratory droplets produced when an infected person coughs or sneezes. These droplets can land in the mouths or noses of people who are nearby or be launched into the air and inhaled into someone’s lungs. It is possible that a person can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or eyes; however, this is not the most likely way the virus spreads."},{"id":686,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What should I do if I think I may be sick with COVID-19?","response":"If you think you have been exposed to COVID-19 and develop a fever or symptoms of respiratory illness, such as cough or difficulty breathing, alert facility staff right away to make sure you receive medical care and protect the people around you from being exposed to the virus."},{"id":687,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What does it mean to be in quarantine?","response":"Anyone who has close contact with a person with COVID-19 will need to stay away from other people for at least 14 days to make sure they aren’t sick as well. This means that they will be placed in a room separate from others, or just with other people who have also been exposed to the same sick person. During this time, they will be checked for COVID-19 symptoms. If testing is available, a person in quarantine may be tested several times until medical staff are sure they do not have the virus."},{"id":688,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"Is it ok for people to visit me?","response":"Anyone who has had flu-like symptoms in the last 24 hours or has been in contact with someone who has or is suspected to have COVID-19 in last 14 days should not visit a correctional or detention facility. All visitors will be screened for symptoms and contact with someone with COVID-19. Staff will also perform temperature checks on all visitors. Visitors should contact the facility about their rules on visits before they travel. If a person in the facility has COVID-19, visitors may not be allowed to enter the facility. Instead, non-contact visits can be used, when possible."},{"id":689,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail : People Being Released from Prison and Jail","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"When I get out of prison or jail during the COVID-19 pandemic (worldwide disease outbreak), what steps should I take to protect myself and others from COVID-19?","response":"You may have received a COVID-19 test in prison or jail. If you test negative, you probably were not infected at the time they took your sample. The test result only means that you did not have COVID-19 at the time of testing. Also, you may have been exposed to COVID-19 between the time you were last tested and the time you got out. So, you should stay away from others (quarantine) as much as you can for 14 days after release to protect yourself and others. Visit Test for current infection.\nIf you get sick with COVID-19 during the 14 days you are staying away from others, ask for a COVID-19 test. If you do not have a doctor, contact a health center or health department. See how under the next question: “After I get out of prison or jail,  where can I get help during the COVID-19 pandemic?”\nSymptoms of COVID-19 include\n\n\nSymptoms of COVID-19\n\n\nFever/chills\nCough\nFeeling tired\nHaving a hard time breathing\nPain in the head or body\nLoss of taste or smell\nSore throat\nStuffy or runny nose\nNausea/vomiting\nDiarrhea\n\n\n\n\nDuring quarantine it is best to stay alone in a private living space, if you can, to avoid contact with other people. Ideally, your space should include your own bedroom and bathroom. Before you are released, contact friends or family to find a place to stay. If you cannot find space with family or friends, find homeless shelters in the area.\nIf you can find housing before you are released, set up a space with clothing, food, medicine, cleaning supplies, and any other items you may need while in quarantine. Get things that will help protect you and others from getting COVID-19 once you are released. Items include face masks, hand sanitizer, soap, and paper towels, or a cloth towel that only you use or that you change often. Visit COVID-19 prevention link to learn more about how to protect yourself and others.\nYou may also need other items to help you get health and social services once you get out. Before release, ask a prison or jail worker about how to get these things upon release:\n\nPrison ID card, or birth certificate or social security card\nSmall supply of your medicines\nCopy of your medical records\n\nIf you can, ask a doctor or nurse; if there is not a doctor or nurse, ask a prison or jail worker."},{"id":690,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail : People Being Released from Prison and Jail","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"After I get out of prison or jail, where can I get help during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"The COVID-19 pandemic has changed many parts of life. For example, some stores and offices may have closed, changed their hours, or you may need to make an appointment to visit. You may want to contact offices or businesses before you visit. Court appearances may be held through video calls.\nSocial services, such as healthcare, food, and housing assistance, can support you after your release to help you adjust during the COVID-19 pandemic. Many cities have a phone line you can contact by dialing 2-1-1 or by visiting the 2-1-1 websiteexternal icon where you can also get help.\n \nYour library or community center may offer free phone and internet, or\naccess these resources through a smart phone.\n \nHealthcare services: You can contact your local health departmentexternal icon if you\n\nGet sick with COVID-19\nHave questions about COVID-19 and the pandemic\nNeed low-cost or free healthcare services in your area\n\nAccess to healthcare is important, especially if you are near someone with COVID-19 or get sick with COVID-19. Some health centers provide healthcare for little or no cost. Contact your local clinic to learn more about which services they offer during the COVID-19 pandemic. Check to see if you can sign up for Medicareexternal icon and/or Medicaidexternal icon to help pay for healthcare costs and services.\n \nFood: Many people struggle to buy or find food where they live, especially during the COVID-19 pandemic. Meal sites, food banks and other services may help  you and your family during this time.\n \nStress and coping: Being released from prison or jail can be very tough. The COVID-19 pandemic may add stress to your situation. Visit managing stress and coping during COVID-19 and How Right Now resiliencyexternal icon for help.\nGet help right away in a crisis:\n\nCall 911\nDisaster Distress Helpline: 1-800-985-5990 (press 2 for Spanish), or\ntext TalkWithUs for English or text Hablanos for Spanish to 66746\nSpanish speakers in Puerto Rico can text Hablanos to 1-787-339-2663\nNational Suicide Prevention Lifeline: 1-800-273-TALK (8255) for English,\n1-888-628-9454 for Spanish\nNational Domestic Violence Hotline: 1-800-799-7233 or text LOVEIS to 22522\nNational Child Abuse Hotline: 1-800-4AChild (1-800-422-4453) or text 1-800-422-4453\nNational Sexual Assault Hotline: 1-800-656-HOPE (4673)\n\n \nTransportation: Getting to and from places, such as the doctor’s office or clinic, can be tough. The COVID-19 pandemic may affect your local public transportation schedule or routes. If you take a bus or train, wear a face mask and stay at least 6 feet (about two arm lengths) from other people. As much as you can, try not to touch items such as handrails, credit card machines, elevator buttons, or benches. If you must touch these items, wash your hands as soon as you can for 20 seconds with soap and water, or use hand sanitizer that contains at least 60% alcohol. Visit Transportation_during_COVID19 for more information.\n \nAccess to phones and internet: Many clinics, hospitals, counseling services, and substance use treatment providers now offer appointments through phone and video calls to protect patients from getting exposed to COVID-19. Some people may not have phone or internet services because it costs too much. For people without the internet right now, the links below are for when you do have internet.\n \n\n\nDescription of Links\n\n\nDescription of the link \nURL\n\n\nWhat are the symptoms of COVID-19?\nhttps://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/symptoms-testing/symptoms.html\n\n\nWhere can I find information about how to protect myself and others from COVID-19?\nhttps://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/prevent-getting-sick/prevention.html\n\n\nHow can I get information on social services?\nCall 2-1-1.\nhttps://www.211.org/external icon\n\n\nHow do I contact the Department of Motor Vehicles (DMV) office?\nTo access health and social services, you need personal identification, or ID.\nCall 1-844-872-4681 to connect you to your local DMV officeexternal icon before you visit to know the hours of operation during the COVID-19 pandemic.\n\n\nWhere can I find a health center?\nLocal health department or federally qualified health centers: 1-800-232-4636\nCommunity Health Centers: 1-800-318-2596\nHRSA Locator: https://findahealthcenter.hrsa.gov/external icon\n\n\nWhere can I find information about Medicare?\nMedicare: 1-800-MEDICARE (1-800-633-4227)\nTTY 1-877-486-2048https://www.medicare.gov/medicare-coronavirusexternal icon\n\n\nWhere can I find information about Medicaid?\nMedicaid: 1-877-267-2323\nTTY: 1-866-226-1819\nhttps://www.medicaid.gov/medicaid/eligibility/index.htmlexternal icon\n\n\nHow can I deal with stress during COVID-19?\nhttps://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/daily-life-coping/managing-stress-anxiety.html\nCDC Foundation site to address feelings of grief, loss, and worry during COVID-19 https://howrightnow.org/external icon\n\n\nHow can I get help for alcohol and substance use?\nStress can lead to alcohol and substance use. If you need help, including medicine for opioid use disorder such as buprenorphine or methadone, contact your local behavioral treatment centersexternal icon for help.\nNational Harm Reduction Coalition\nhttps://harmreduction.org/external icon\nhttps://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/daily-life-coping/stress-coping/alcohol-use.html\nhttps://www.samhsa.gov/find-treatmentexternal icon\n\n\nIf I need help getting food resources during COVID-19, where can I go?\nHunger Hotline: 1-866-3-HUNGRY\n1-877-8-HAMBRE (for Spanish) or Text 97779 with a question that includes a keyword such as “food” or “meals”https://www.cdc.gov/nutrition/resources-publications/food-and-food-system-resources-during-covid-19-pandemic.html\n\n\nHow can I protect myself when using transportation during COVID-19?\nhttps://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/daily-life-coping/using-transportation.html\n\n\nWhere can I find support for veterans during COVID-19, including those who need housing assistance?\nDepartment of Veteran’s Affairs: 1-800-698-2411, TTY: 711\nVeteran’s Crisis Line: 1-800-273-TALK (8255) or\ntext: 8388255https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/daily-life-coping/stress-coping/veterans.htmlU.S. Department of Veterans Affairs: Veterans Justice Outreach Program https://www.va.gov/homeless/vjo.aspexternal icon"},{"id":691,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail : People Being Released from Prison and Jail : Family Members of People Who Are Incarcerated at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"My family member doesn't have access to the internet. How can I provide them information on COVID-19?","response":"A printable resource is available at What You Need to Know about COVID-19 if You are Incarcerated/Detained pdf icon[PDF – 253 KB] | Spanish version pdf icon[PDF – 227 KB] that you can print and send to your family member.​"},{"id":692,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail : People Being Released from Prison and Jail : Family Members of People Who Are Incarcerated at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"Do people who are incarcerated (in prison, jail, or detention facilities) have a greater chance of getting COVID-19 than others?","response":"Incarcerated and detained people spend almost all of their time within congregate environments where groups of people share the same space, which increases the chance for COVID-19 to spread once introduced. The virus that causes COVID-19 is thought to spread mainly from person-to-person through respiratory droplets produced when an infected person coughs, sneezes, or talks. These droplets can land in the mouths or noses of people who are nearby or possibly be inhaled into someone’s lungs. Spread is more likely when people are in close contact with one another (within about 6 feet). It is possible that a person can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes; however, this is not the most likely way the virus spreads. COVID-19 may also be spread by people who are not showing symptoms. Learn more about how COVID-19 spreads."},{"id":693,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail : People Being Released from Prison and Jail : Family Members of People Who Are Incarcerated at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"What does it mean if someone I know is in quarantine?","response":"Anyone who has had close contact with a person with COVID-19 will need to be put into quarantine for 14 days. This means that they will be placed in a room separate from others, until staff are sure that they don’t have symptoms. If symptoms develop during the 14-day period, and/or the person in quarantine tests positive for COVID-19, they should be placed under medical isolation and evaluated. If symptoms do not develop and they do not test positive for COVID-19, quarantine restrictions can be lifted, or removed, after the 14-day period ends. Quarantine procedures may differ by facility."},{"id":694,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail : People Being Released from Prison and Jail : Family Members of People Who Are Incarcerated at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"Is it ok for me to visit?","response":"To help protect each visitor’s health and the health of staff, family members, or friends inside the facility, contact visits are discouraged during the COVID-19 pandemic. You should not visit a correctional or detention facility if you:\n\nHave had COVID-19 or COVID-19 symptoms and have not yet met the criteria to discontinue home isolation\nHave been in contact with someone who has had COVID-19 in the last 14 days\nHave been in contact with someone who is suspected of having COVID-19 in the last 14 days\n\nPrior to a planned visit, you should make sure that visitation has not been suspended and review the facility’s rules about visits. If there is someone in the facility who has COVID-19, visitors might not be allowed to enter the facility. Some facilities may arrange for non-contact visits when possible, and staff may screen and perform temperature checks on all visitors. You should also wear cloth face coverings. Wearing cloth face coverings may be difficult for people with sensory, cognitive, or behavioral issues and is not recommended for children under 2 years or anyone who has trouble breathing or is unconscious, incapacitated, or otherwise unable to remove the covering without assistance."},{"id":695,"category":"Correctional and Detention Facilities : Administrators at Correctional and Detention Facilities : Staff at Correctional and Detention Facilities : People in Prison or Jail : People Being Released from Prison and Jail : Family Members of People Who Are Incarcerated at Correctional and Detention Facilities","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/correction-detention/faq.html","question":"If a family member or friend is returning home soon (during the COVID-19 pandemic) from a correctional or detention facility, how should a household prepare to receive them and maintain everyone’s safety?","response":"Depending on the steps facilities are taking and the length of stay, people released from a facility may have had screenings for COVID-19 symptoms, temperature checks, or even a test—a pre-release planning process. The family member or friend may have also been offered information and resources on how to prevent COVID-19. If they were sick at the time of release, they may have been linked to community resources to make sure they follow proper medical isolation and have access to medical care.\nThere are things that family members and people who share housing can do to promote a healthy home and prevent getting sick. You’re encouraged to find a room where the person can stay alone for at least 14 days and monitor their symptoms. During that time, they should limit contact with others within and outside the home, particularly people who are at higher risk for severe illness from COVID-19 like older adults and those with underlying medical conditions. They should avoid providing care for children during this time, if possible. Friends and family should keep a distance of at least 6 feet, and everyone should consider wearing a cloth face covering, especially when going out in public. Finally, frequent handwashing, as well as cleaning and disinfecting frequently touched surfaces, are also important.\nAdditional information is available regarding the prevention of COVID-19 for people who share a small apartment  or live in a household with large or extended families. If the person who was just released, or anyone in your household, develops symptoms or tests positive for COVID-19, please follow CDC recommendations for what to do if you become sick or have to care for someone who is sick."},{"id":696,"category":"Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html","question":"What actions should I take to plan for an outbreak?","response":"Creating an emergency plan for mass gatherings and large community events, such as concerts and sporting events, can help protect the health of your staff, attendees, and the local community. This planning should include:\n\nEncouraging staff and attendees to stay home if sick.\nDeveloping flexible refund policies for attendees.\nProviding supplies for attendees and staff that can be used to help prevent the spread of germs.\nConsulting local public health officials about your event."},{"id":697,"category":"Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html","question":"How many guests can safely attend a conference, sporting event, concert, or other community event?","response":"CDC does not have a limit or recommend a specific number of attendees for these types of events and instead encourages event organizers to focus on ways to limit people’s contact with each other. Each event organizer will need to determine the appropriate number for their setting in collaboration with local health officials. They should also check state, county, and city rules regarding any current restrictions limiting the number of attendees at events.\nIn general, the number that is chosen should allow individuals to remain at least 6 feet apart from each other. Rather than focusing on an ideal number, event organizers and administrators should focus on the ability to reduce and limit contact between attendees, staff, and others. In general, the more people you interact with, the more closely you interact with them, and the longer that interaction, the higher your risk of getting and spreading COVID-19. Indoor spaces are more risky than outdoor spaces because indoors, it can be harder to keep people at least 6 feet apart and the ventilation is not as good as it is outdoors."},{"id":698,"category":"Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html","question":"Does CDC have recommendations on how to maintain 6 feet between attendees during events?","response":"Yes. CDC recommends several strategies for this. For instance, organizers can:\n\nLimit attendance or seating capacity to allow for social distancing, or host smaller events in larger rooms.\nBlock off rows or sections of seating in order to space people at least 6 feet apart.\nUse multiple entrances and exits and discourage crowded waiting areas.\nEliminate lines or queues if possible or encourage people to stay at least 6 feet apart by providing signs or other visual cues such as tape or chalk marks.\nProvide physical guides, such as tape on floors or sidewalks and signs on walls, to ensure that individuals remain at least 6 feet apart in lines and at other times (such as guides for creating one-way routes).\nPrioritize outdoor activities where social distancing can be maintained as much as possible.\nOffer online attendance options in addition to in-person attendance to help reduce the number of attendees.\nConsider limiting the number of people who occupy the restroom at one time to allow for social distancing.\nDo not allow lines or crowds to form near the restroom. Take steps to ensure that individuals can stay at least 6 feet apart from each other."},{"id":699,"category":"Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html","question":"Should organizers test all attendees and staff for COVID-19 before they can enter an event?","response":"CDC does not recommend testing all attendees and staff before allowing them to enter. Testing all event attendees and staff for COVID-19 before allowing them to enter the venue has not been systematically studied. It is unknown if entry testing at event venues provides any additional reduction in person-to-person transmission of the virus beyond what would be expected with other preventive measures (such as social distancing, wearing cloth face coverings, hand washing, enhanced cleaning and disinfection).\nCDC does recommend conducting health checks such as temperature screening and/or symptom checking of staff and attendees safely and respectfully, and in accordance with any applicable privacy laws and regulations."},{"id":700,"category":"Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html","question":"Does CDC recommend all event attendees wear masks?","response":"Yes. CDC recommends that people wear masks in public settings and when around people who don’t live in their household, especially when other social distancing measures are difficult to maintain. CDC recommends that organizers require staff to wear masks and encourage attendees ahead of events to bring and wear masks at the event. Masks are most essential when physical distancing is difficult (such as when moving within a crowd or audience). Masks offer some protection to the wearer and are also meant to protect those around the wearer, in case they are infected with the virus that causes COVID-19. Masks are not surgical masks or respirators. They are not personal protective equipment.\nMasks are strongly encouraged in settings where individuals might raise their voices (such as shouting, chanting, singing). Provide all staff with information on proper use, removal, and washing of masks. Advise staff that masks should not be placed on:\n\nBabies or children younger than 2 years old\nAnyone who has trouble breathing\nAnyone who is unconscious, incapacitated, or otherwise unable to remove the mask without assistance"},{"id":701,"category":"Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html","question":"What actions can staff and attendees take to prevent the spread of COVID-19?","response":"Encourage staff and attendees to take everyday preventive actions to help prevent the spread of respiratory illnesses, such as COVID-19. This includes:\n\nCleaning your hands often.\nAvoiding close contact with people who are sick.\nStaying home when you are sick.\nCovering coughs and sneezes with a tissue or the inside of your elbow.\nCleaning and disinfecting frequently touched surfaces.\nUsing a mask in public, especially when it may be difficult to maintain a distance of at least six feet from other people."},{"id":702,"category":"Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html","question":"How should staff clean the facility before and during the event to limit spread of the virus?","response":"Cleaning with products containing soap or detergent reduces germs on surfaces and objects by removing contaminants and may also weaken or damage some of the virus particles, which decreases risk of infection from surfaces. Cleaning high touch surfaces and shared objects once a day is usually enough to sufficiently remove virus that may be on surfaces unless someone with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 has been in your facility. For more information on cleaning your facility regularly and cleaning your facility when someone is sick, see Cleaning and Disinfecting Your Facility"},{"id":703,"category":"Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html","question":"What are things to consider when determining if an event needs to be postponed or canceled?","response":"Consult with local public health officials and continually assess, based on current conditions, whether to postpone, cancel, or significantly reduce the number of attendees (if possible) at an event or gathering. When determining if you should postpone or cancel a large gathering or event, consider the:\n\nOverall number of attendees or crowd size.\nNumber of attendees who are at higher risk of developing serious illness from COVID-19. This includes older adults and people with underlying health problems such as lung or heart disease and diabetes.\nHow close together attendees will be at the event.\nAmount of spread in local community and the communities from where your attendees are likely to travel.\nNeeds and capacity of the local community to host or participate in your event."},{"id":704,"category":"Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html","question":"Is there information I can share with staff and attendees about COVID-19?","response":"Share these resources to help people understand COVID-19 and steps they can take to help protect themselves:\n\nPrevention and Treatment\nWhat to Do If You Are Sick\nGroups at Higher Risk\nFAQs: Pregnant People and COVID-19\nFAQs: Coronavirus Disease-2019 (COVID-19) and Children\nHandwashing: A Family Activity\nHandwashing: Clean Hands Save Lives\nConsiderations for Restaurants and Bars\nConsiderations for Animal Activities at Fairs, Shows, and Other Events"},{"id":705,"category":"Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness : Confirmed case of COVID-19 at an event","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html","question":"What steps should I take if an attendee or staff person develops symptoms of COVID-19 while at the event?","response":"If a staff member or attendee becomes sick at your event, separate them from others as soon as possible and until they can go home. Provide them with clean, disposable facemaskspdf iconpdf icon to wear, if available. If not available, provide them with a cloth face covering, which can be improvised if needed from a tee shirt, bandana or other clothing, as well as a tissue or some other way to cover their coughs and sneezes. If needed, contact emergency services for those who need emergency care. Public transportation, shared rides, and taxis should be avoided for sick persons. Be sure to contact local public health officials regarding the possible case of COVID-19 at your event and how to communicate with staff and attendees about possible exposure to the virus. Read more about preventing the spread of COVID-19 if someone is sick."},{"id":706,"category":"Event Organizers & Individuals : Planning and Preparedness : Confirmed case of COVID-19 at an event","source":"https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/community/large-events/event-planners-and-attendees-faq.html","question":"What is the best way to clean and disinfect the event space after a confirmed case of COVID-19 at my event?","response":"CDC has guidance for cleaning and disinfecting rooms and areas where a person with suspected or confirmed COVID-19 has visited. See Environmental Cleaning and Disinfection Recommendations."},{"id":707,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is the FDA doing to respond to the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"The FDA, along with other federal, state, and local agencies and public health officials across the country and internationally, plays a critical role in protecting public health during the COVID-19 pandemic. FDA staff are working around the clock to support development of  medical countermeasures and are providing regulatory advice, guidance, and technical assistance to advance the development and availability of vaccines, therapies, diagnostic tests and other medical devices for use diagnosing, treating, and preventing this novel virus. The FDA continues to monitor the human and animal food supply and take swift action on fraudulent COVID-19 products."},{"id":708,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is an emergency use authorization and how is it being used to respond to COVID-19?","response":"In certain types of emergencies, the FDA can issue an emergency use authorization, or EUA, to provide more timely access to critical medical products (including medicines and tests) that may help during the emergency when there are no adequate, approved, and available alternative options.\nThe EUA process is different than FDA approval, clearance, or licensing because the EUA standard may permit authorization based on significantly less data than would be required for approval, clearance, or licensing by the FDA. This enables the FDA to authorize the emergency use of medical products that meet the criteria within weeks rather than months to years. \nEUAs are in effect until the emergency declaration ends but can be revised or revoked as we evaluate the needs during the emergency and new data on the product’s safety and effectiveness, or as products meet the criteria to become approved, cleared, or licensed by the FDA.\nLearn more about EUAs in this video\nRead more about COVID-19 tests \nFind a community-based testing site"},{"id":709,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"How can I prevent COVID-19?","response":"The best way to prevent illness is to avoid being exposed to the virus. The CDC recommends everyday preventive actions to help prevent the spread of respiratory diseases. They include: \nWash your hands often with plain soap and water. The CDC recommends washing your hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds, especially after you have been in a public place, or after blowing your nose, coughing, or sneezing. If soap and water are not available, the CDC recommends using an alcohol-based hand sanitizer that contains at least 60 percent alcohol. Learn more about safely using hand sanitizer.\nCover your mouth and nose with a cloth face covering or non-surgical mask when around others. Find more information about how to select, wear, and clean your mask.\nGet the COVID-19 vaccine when it is offered to you. Once you are fully vaccinated, you may be able to start doing some things that you had stopped doing because of the pandemic.\nFollow CDC guidance on large gatherings, social distancing and mask wearing, based on if you are fully vaccinated or not.\nLearn how to protect your family in this Consumer Update and the importance of getting your flu vaccine."},{"id":710,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Should I wear a face covering or mask when I go out in public?","response":"The CDC recommends wearing masks in public when other social distancing measures are difficult to maintain. Effective February 2, 2021, masks are required on planes, buses, trains, and other forms of public transportation traveling into, within, or out of the United States and in U.S. transportation hubs such as airports and stations. Read more about the CDC’s Mask Requirement.\nThe FDA has authorized the emergency use of face masks, including cloth face coverings, that meet certain criteria for use as source control by the general public and health care personnel in accordance with CDC recommendations during the COVID-19 public health emergency. The FDA also regulates other medical devices, including personal protective equipment (PPE) such as surgical masks and N95 respirators. The CDC recommends that PPE should be reserved for use by health care workers, first responders, and other frontline workers whose jobs put them at much greater risk of acquiring COVID-19. \nRead more about types of face masks and the FDA’s emergency use authorization for non-surgical face masks."},{"id":711,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What treatments are available for COVID-19?","response":"On October 22, 2020, the FDA approved the antiviral drug Veklury (remdesivir) for use in adults and pediatric patients (12 years of age and older and weighing at least 40 kg) for the treatment of COVID-19 requiring hospitalization. Veklury should only be administered in a hospital or in a healthcare setting capable of providing acute care comparable to inpatient hospital care.  \nThis approval does not include the entire population that had been authorized to use Veklury under an Emergency Use Authorization (EUA) originally issued on May 1, 2020. In order to ensure continued access to the pediatric population previously covered under the EUA, the FDA revised the EUA for Veklury to permit the drug’s use by licensed healthcare providers for the treatment of suspected or laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 in hospitalized pediatric patients 3.5 kg to less than 40 kg or hospitalized pediatric patients less than 12 years of age weighing at least 3.5 kg. For additional information on the authorized use of Veklury under the EUA, refer to the Fact Sheet for Healthcare Providers.\nClinical trials assessing the safety and efficacy of Veklury (remdesivir) in this pediatric patient population are ongoing. \nThe National Institutes of Health provides more information about treatment options.\nPeople with COVID-19 should receive supportive care to help relieve symptoms. People with mild symptoms are able to recover at home. If you experience a medical emergency such as trouble breathing, call 911 and let the operator know you may have COVID-19. Never take a prescription medicine or drug if it is not prescribed for you by your doctor for your health condition."},{"id":712,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Can I prevent or treat COVID-19 by using disinfectant sprays, wipes, or liquids on my skin? Can I inject, inhale, or ingest (swallow) disinfectants to prevent or treat COVID-19?","response":"No. Disinfectants should not be used on human or animal skin. Disinfectants may cause serious skin and eye irritation. \nDisinfectants are dangerous for people to inject, inhale, or ingest. If you breathe, inject, or swallow disinfectants you may be seriously hurt or die. If someone near you swallows, injects, or breathes a disinfectant, call poison control or a medical professional immediately.\nDisinfectant products such as sprays, mists, wipes, or liquids are only to be used on hard, non-porous surfaces (materials that do not absorb liquids easily) such as floors and countertops, or on soft surfaces such as mattresses, sofas, and beds.\nView the current list of disinfectants that meet EPA’s criteria for use against SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19."},{"id":713,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Does spraying people with disinfectant lower the spread of COVID-19?","response":"Currently there are no data showing that spraying people with aerosolized disinfectants, or having people walk through tunnels or rooms where disinfectant is in the air, can treat, prevent, or lower the spread of COVID-19.\nSurface disinfectants should not be used on people or animals. Disinfectant products, such as sprays, mists, wipes, or liquids are only to be used on hard, non-porous surfaces (materials that do not absorb liquids easily) such as floors and countertops, or on soft surfaces such as mattresses, sofas, and beds. CDC provides information regarding disinfectant practices for surfaces in the Reopening Guidance for Cleaning and Disinfecting Public Spaces, Workplaces, Businesses, Schools, and Homes. \nHuman antiseptic drugs, such as hand sanitizers, are intended for use on human skin, but are not intended for aerosolization (to be sprayed in the air in very small droplets).  Due to serious safety concerns, including the risk of inhalational toxicity and flammability, the FDA’s temporary policies for alcohol-based hand sanitizers during the COVID-19 public health emergency specifically do not apply to aerosol sprays.  In addition, hand sanitizers are intended for use on the hands, and should never be used over larger body surfaces, swallowed, or inhaled."},{"id":714,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Will Miracle Mineral Solution (MMS) cure COVID-19?","response":" No. Miracle Mineral Solution does not cure COVID-19 and has not been approved by the FDA for any use. The solution, when mixed as directed, forms industrial bleach that may cause serious and potentially life-threatening side effects. FDA took action against Genesis II Church of Health and Healing for unlawfully distributing Miracle Mineral Solution for the treatment of COVID-19 and other diseases. Learn more: Danger: Don’t Drink Miracle Mineral Solution or Similar Products."},{"id":715,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Is hand sanitizer effective against COVID-19?","response":"The best way to prevent the spread of infections and decrease the risk of getting sick is by washing your hands with plain soap and water, advises the CDC. Washing hands often with soap and water for at least 20 seconds is essential, especially after going to the bathroom; before eating; and after coughing, sneezing, or blowing one’s nose. If soap and water are not available, CDC recommends consumers use an alcohol-based hand sanitizer that contains at least 60% alcohol."},{"id":716,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Why has the FDA placed alcohol-based hand sanitizers from Mexico on import alert?","response":"During the coronavirus pandemic, the FDA has seen a sharp increase in hand sanitizer products from Mexico that were labeled to contain ethanol (also called ethyl alcohol) but, among other concerns, tested positive for methanol contamination. Methanol (or wood alcohol) can be toxic when absorbed through the skin and life-threatening when ingested. Methanol is not an acceptable ingredient in hand sanitizer.\nRecently, the FDA placed all alcohol-based hand sanitizers from Mexico on a country-wide import alert to help prevent entry into the U.S. of potentially dangerous products until we can review the product’s safety. An import alert informs field staff the FDA has sufficient evidence to detain products (at the border/import site) that appear to violate laws and regulations without physical examination. FDA analyses of alcohol-based hand sanitizers from Mexico found that 84 percent of the samples we analyzed from April through December 2020 were not in compliance with FDA regulations.\nImport alerts:\nHelp prevent potentially violative products from being distributed in the United States;\nHelp free-up agency resources to examine other shipments;\nProvide uniform information to FDA field offices across the country;\nProvide the importer the opportunity to show that the products being imported into the United States are in compliance with the FDA's laws and regulations.\nTo stay informed, visit the FDA’s Hand Sanitizers and COVID-19 page. Also, take our hand sanitizer quiz."},{"id":717,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Where can I buy hand sanitizer? Can I make my own hand sanitizer?","response":"Many retail stores and pharmacies sell hand sanitizers. However, we understand that many stores may not have hand sanitizers available to buy. To help increase the availability of hand sanitizers, the FDA has issued guidance for the temporary preparation of alcohol-based hand sanitizers by some companies and pharmacies during the COVID-19 public health emergency. \nThe FDA does not recommend that consumers make their own hand sanitizer. If made incorrectly, hand sanitizer can be ineffective, and there have been reports of skin burns from homemade hand sanitizer. The agency lacks verifiable information on the methods being used to prepare hand sanitizer at home and whether they are safe for use on human skin.\nSee the Q&A for Consumers: Hand Sanitizers and COVID-19 and Safely Using Hand Sanitizer for more information."},{"id":718,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What do I do if I get a rash or other reaction to hand sanitizer?","response":"Call your doctor if you experience a serious reaction to hand sanitizer. The FDA encourages consumers and health care professionals to report adverse events experienced with the use of hand sanitizers to the FDA’s MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program:\nComplete and submit the report online; or\nDownload and complete the form, then submit it via fax at 1-800-FDA-0178.\nInclude as much information as you can about the product that caused the reaction, including the product name, the manufacturer, and the lot number (if available).\nSee Q&A for Consumers: Hand Sanitizers and COVID-19 and Safely Using Hand Sanitizer for more information."},{"id":719,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is the risk of using a hand sanitizer that contains methanol (wood alcohol) or 1-propanol?","response":"Methanol exposure can result in nausea, vomiting, headache, blurred vision, permanent blindness, seizures, coma, permanent damage to the nervous system or death. Although people using these products on their hands are at risk for methanol poisoning, young children who accidentally swallow these products and adolescents and adults who drink these products as an alcohol (ethanol) substitute are most at risk.\nSwallowing or drinking a hand sanitizer with 1-propanol can result in decreased breathing and heart rate, among other serious symptoms, and can lead to death. Hand sanitizer with 1-propanol contamination can irritate your skin (or eyes, if exposed). Although it is rare, some people have reported allergic skin reactions. Learn more about methanol and 1-propanol toxicities."},{"id":720,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What should I do with hand sanitizer that contains methanol (wood alcohol) or 1-propanol?","response":"If you have one of the products the FDA's do-not-use list of hand sanitizers, you should immediately stop using it and dispose of the product, ideally in a hazardous waste container. Do not pour these products down the drain or flush them. Contact your local waste management and recycling center for more information on hazardous waste disposal. Learn how to search FDA’s hand sanitizer do-not-use list, including a description of how to search for manufacturers and distributors on the label."},{"id":721,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What should people do if they have been exposed to hand sanitizer with potential methanol or 1-propanol contamination?","response":"People who have been exposed to contaminated hand sanitizer and are experiencing symptoms should seek immediate medical treatment for potential reversal of toxic effects.\nFDA encourages health care professionals, consumers and patients to report adverse events or quality problems experienced with the use of hand sanitizers to FDA’s MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program (please provide the agency with as much information as possible to identify the product):\nComplete and submit the report online; or\nDownload and complete the form, then submit it via fax at 1-800-FDA-0178."},{"id":722,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Products online claim to prevent or treat COVID-19. Where can I report websites selling products with fraudulent claims?","response":"The FDA advises consumers to be beware of websites and stores selling products that claim to prevent, treat, or cure COVID-19. If you have a question about a product sold online that claims to treat, prevent, or cure COVID-19, talk to your health care provider or doctor.\nWatch this video and read this Consumer Update to learn how to protect yourself and your family from coronavirus fraud. \nPlease report websites selling products with fraudulent claims about treatment or prevention of COVID-19. If you have experienced a bad reaction to a product sold with COVID-19 claims, report it to the FDA’s MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program:\nComplete and submit the report online; or\nDownload and complete the form, then submit it via fax at 1-800-FDA-0178.\nInclude as much information as you can about the product that caused the reaction, including the product name, the manufacturer, and the lot number (if available)."},{"id":723,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Am I at risk for serious complications from COVID-19 if I smoke cigarettes?","response":"Yes. Data shows that when compared to never smokers, cigarette smoking increases the risk of more severe illness from COVID-19, which could result in hospitalization, the need for intensive care, or even death. Smoking cigarettes can cause inflammation and cell damage throughout the body, and can weaken your immune system, making it less able to fight off disease.\nThere’s never been a better time to quit smoking. If you need resources to help you quit smoking, the FDA’s Every Try Counts campaign has supportive tips and tools to help you get closer to quitting for good."},{"id":724,"category":"General Information","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"If I vape tobacco or nicotine am I at risk for complications from COVID-19?","response":"E-cigarette use can expose the lungs to toxic chemicals, but whether those exposures increase the risk of COVID-19 or the severity of COVID-19 outcomes is not known. However, many e-cigarette users are current or former smokers, and cigarette smoking increases the risk of respiratory infections, including pneumonia."},{"id":725,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is the FDA’s role in approving vaccines and what is being done to produce a COVID-19 vaccine?","response":" FDA regulates vaccines. Vaccines undergo a rigorous review of laboratory, clinical and manufacturing data to ensure the safety, effectiveness, and quality of these products. Vaccines approved for marketing may also be required to undergo additional studies to further evaluate the vaccine and often to address specific questions about the vaccine's safety, effectiveness, or possible side effects.\nOn December 11, 2020, the FDA issued an Emergency Use Authorization (EUA) for the use of the Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 Vaccine. On December 18, 2020, the FDA issued an EUA for the use of the Moderna COVID-19 Vaccine. And on February 27, 2021 the FDA issued an EUA for the use of the Janssen COVID-19 Vaccine. The issuance of an EUA is different than an FDA approval (licensure) of a vaccine.\nIn determining whether to issue an EUA for a product, the FDA evaluates the available evidence and assesses any known or potential risks and any known or potential benefits. And if the benefit-risk assessment is favorable, the product is made available during the public health emergency. Once a manufacturer submits an EUA request for a COVID-19 vaccine, the FDA then evaluates the request and determines whether the relevant statutory criteria are met, taking into account the totality of the scientific evidence about the vaccine that is available to the agency.\nIn addition to supporting product development for high priority COVID-19 vaccines, the FDA continues to expedite clinical trials for additional vaccine candidates, providing timely advice to and interactions with vaccine developers.\nVaccine developers can find more information about the review process here."},{"id":726,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is a biological medical product or a biologic?","response":"Biological products include a wide range of products such as vaccines, blood and blood components, allergenics, somatic cells, gene therapy, tissues, and recombinant therapeutic proteins. Biologics can be composed of sugars, proteins, or nucleic acids or complex combinations of these substances, or may be living entities such as cells and tissues."},{"id":727,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Are there any vaccines or other medical products available to prevent COVID-19?","response":"Yes. The FDA issued emergency use authorizations for three COVID-19 vaccines. \nAdditionally, the FDA is working with other vaccine developers, researchers, and manufacturers to help expedite the development and availability of medical products such as additional vaccines, monoclonal antibodies, and other drugs to prevent or treat COVID-19.  \nFor information about vaccine clinical trials for COVID-19 visit clinicaltrials.gov and the COVID-19 Prevention Network. Note: The information on clinicaltrials.gov is provided by the sponsor or principal investigator of a clinical trial. The listing of a study on the site does not reflect evaluation or endorsement of the trial by the Federal government."},{"id":728,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"How does FDA ensure the quality of COVID-19 vaccines and other medical products authorized for emergency use in the United States?","response":"The FDA takes its responsibility for helping to ensure the quality of manufacturing of vaccines and other medical products for use during this pandemic very seriously. The agency is using a variety of inspectional tools to help ensure that products being produced in different facilities meet the high-quality standards that Americans have come to expect. It is important to note that even when companies use contract manufacturing organizations, it is ultimately the responsibility of the company that holds the emergency use authorization to ensure that the quality standards of the FDA are met. No product can be distributed by manufacturers until the FDA authorizes its distribution from the facility that is manufacturing it. The FDA will continue to work with companies to ensure that the quality standards that it expects for products distributed under an emergency use authorization are met, and will continue to work diligently to help bring needed medical products in a timely manner to Americans during this public health emergency."},{"id":729,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"How do I report COVID-19 vaccine side effects?","response":"If you experience a severe allergic reaction or any life-threatening symptoms such as trouble breathing, call 911, or go to the nearest hospital. \nCall the vaccination provider or your health care provider if you have any side effects that bother you or do not go away. Report vaccine side effects to FDA/CDC Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS). The VAERS toll-free number is 1-800-822-7967 or report online to https://vaers.hhs.gov/reportevent.html. Please include the name of the vaccine in the first line of box #18 of the report form. \nYou may also be given an option to enroll in v-safe. V-safe is a new voluntary smartphone-based tool that uses text messaging and web surveys to check in with people who have been vaccinated to identify potential side effects after COVID-19 vaccination. V-safe asks questions that help CDC monitor the safety of COVID-19 vaccines. V-safe also provides second-dose reminders if needed and live telephone follow-up by CDC if participants report a significant health impact following COVID-19 vaccination. For more information on how to sign up, visit: www.cdc.gov/vsafe."},{"id":730,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Can the FDA help me get a COVID-19 vaccine?","response":"No. The FDA’s authority includes authorizing or approving COVID-19 vaccines for use in the United States, but the FDA is not responsible for vaccine distribution. Go to the CDC website to find your state and local health departments who are responsible for COVID-19 vaccine distribution. All questions and concerns should be sent to your state government or local health department. The U.S. government’s goal is to have enough COVID-19 vaccine doses for all people in the United States who choose to be vaccinated.\nIf you are contacted directly by someone who says they are from the FDA about a COVID-19 vaccine appointment, it is a scam. The Federal Trade Commission has easy tips on how to avoid COVID-19 vaccine scams. The FDA encourages you to report a potential COVID-19 drug or medical product scam on our website."},{"id":731,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Does COVID-19 present a risk to the safety of the nation’s blood supply?","response":"In general, respiratory viruses are not known to be transmitted by blood transfusion, and there have been no reported cases of transfusion-transmitted coronavirus."},{"id":732,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Can SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, be transmitted by blood transfusion?","response":"In general, respiratory viruses are not known to be transmitted by blood transfusion, and there have been no reported cases of transfusion-transmitted coronavirus."},{"id":733,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What steps are being taken to protect the U.S. blood supply from SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19?","response":"Blood donors must be healthy and feel well on the day of donation. Routine blood donor screening measures that are already in place should prevent individuals with respiratory infections from donating blood. For example, blood donors must be in good health and have a normal temperature on the day of donation.\nDonors are instructed to contact the donor center if they become ill after donation, so that their blood or plasma will not be used. Even when a donor develops COVID-19 after donation, however, there have been no cases of COVID-19 linked to donor blood or products made from blood.   \nThe FDA has provided additional information to blood establishments on its website."},{"id":734,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Why aren’t blood centers testing donors for SARS-CoV-2?","response":" At this time, the FDA does not recommend using laboratory tests to screen blood. Someone who has symptoms of COVID-19, including fever, cough, and shortness of breath, is not healthy enough to donate blood. Standard screening processes already in place will mean that someone with these symptoms will not be allowed to donate."},{"id":735,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Is it safe for me to donate blood during the coronavirus pandemic?","response":"If you are healthy and interested in donating blood, the FDA encourages you to contact a local donation center to make an appointment. One way to make a difference during a public health emergency is to donate blood if you are able. \nAABB: www.aabb.org; +1.301.907.6977\nAmerica’s Blood Centers: www.americasblood.org\nAmerican Red Cross: www.redcrossblood.org; +1.800.RED CROSS (+1.800.733.2767)\nArmed Services Blood Program: www.militaryblood.dod.mil; +1.703.681.8024\nBlood Centers of America: www.bca.coop"},{"id":736,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Can COVID-19 be transmitted through human cells, tissues, or cellular and tissue-based products (HCT/Ps)?","response":"Respiratory viruses, in general, are not known to be transmitted by implantation, transplantation, infusion, or transfer of human cells, tissues, or cellular or tissue-based products (HCT/Ps). The potential for transmission of COVID-19 by HCT/Ps is unknown at this time. There have been no reported cases of transmission of COVID-19 via HCT/Ps.\nRoutine screening measures are already in place for evaluating clinical evidence of infection in HCT/P donors. Read more about HCT/Ps."},{"id":737,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is convalescent plasma and why is it being investigated to treat COVID-19?","response":"Convalescent refers to anyone recovering from a disease. Plasma is the yellow, liquid part of blood that contains antibodies. Antibodies are proteins made by the body in response to infections.  Convalescent plasma from patients who have already recovered from coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) may contain antibodies against COVID-19. The FDA has issued an emergency use authorization for the use of convalescent plasma in hospitalized patients. It is being investigated for the treatment of COVID-19 patients. Based on scientific evidence available, the FDA concluded this product may be effective in treating COVID-19 and that the known and potential benefits of the product outweigh the known and potential risks of the product for patients hospitalized with COVID-19. Learn more about donating from this video."},{"id":738,"category":"Vaccines, Biologics, Human Tissues, and Blood Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"I recently recovered from COVID-19, can I donate convalescent plasma?","response":"COVID-19 convalescent plasma must only be collected from recovered individuals if they are eligible to donate blood. Individuals must have had a prior diagnosis of COVID-19 documented by a laboratory test and meet other laboratory criteria. Individuals must have fully recovered from COVID-19, with complete resolution of symptoms for at least 14 days before donation of convalescent plasma. You can ask your local blood center if there are options to donate convalescent plasma in your area. Learn more about how to donate."},{"id":739,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What does it mean to be an FDA-approved drug?","response":"FDA approval of a drug means that the agency has determined, based on substantial evidence, that the drug is effective for its intended use, and that the benefits of the drug outweigh its risks when used according to the product’s approved labeling. The drug approval process takes place within a structured framework that includes collecting clinical data and submitting an application to the FDA. Learn more about the FDA’s Drug Review Process."},{"id":740,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is the FDA’s role in regulating potential treatments during a public health emergency?","response":"The FDA carries out many activities to protect and promote public health during a public health emergency, including helping to accelerate the development and availability of potential treatments, protecting the security of drug supply chains, providing guidance to food and medical device manufacturers, advising developers on clinical trial issues, and keeping the public informed with authoritative health information.\nThe FDA is committed to supporting the development of new drugs, and the potential repurposing of existing drugs, to address COVID-19 by working with potential drug makers and sponsors to rapidly move products into clinical trials, helping to ensure that trials are properly designed and safe, and protecting the public from potentially unsafe products.\nRead more about FDA efforts to accelerate treatments and other actions related to coronavirus."},{"id":741,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Are there any FDA-approved drugs (medicines) for COVID-19?","response":"Yes, the FDA has approved Veklury (remdesivir) for certain COVID-19 patients. Read more about the approval here.\nAdditionally, during public health emergencies, the FDA may in certain circumstances authorize use of unapproved drugs or unapproved uses of approved drugs for life-threatening conditions when there are no adequate, approved, and available options and other conditions are met. This is called an Emergency Use Authorization (EUA).\nResearchers are studying new drugs, and medicines that are already approved for other health conditions, as possible treatments for COVID-19. The FDA created the Coronavirus Treatment Acceleration Program (CTAP) to use every available method to move new treatments to patients. Additionally, the FDA is working with the National Institutes of Health, drug manufacturers, researchers, and other partners to accelerate the development process for COVID-19 treatments. FDA’s Sentinel System is being used to monitor the use of drugs, describe the course of illness among hospitalized patients, and evaluate the treatment impact of therapies actively being used under real-world conditions.\nFor information about clinical trials for COVID-19 treatments visit clinicaltrials.gov and the COVID-19 Prevention Network. Note: The information on clinicaltrials.gov is provided by the sponsor or principal investigator of a clinical trial. The listing of a study on the site does not reflect evaluation or endorsement of the trial by the Federal government."},{"id":742,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Is Veklury (remdesivir) approved by the FDA to treat COVID-19?","response":"Yes, on October 22, 2020, the FDA approved Veklury (remdesivir) for certain COVID-19 patients. Read more about the approval here."},{"id":743,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Is Olumiant (baricitinib) approved by the FDA to treat COVID-19?","response":"No. Olumiant is not FDA-approved for the treatment of COVID-19. However, the FDA issued an emergency use authorization (EUA) authorizing Olumiant for emergency use by healthcare providers, in combination with Veklury (remdesivir), for the treatment of suspected or laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 in hospitalized adults and pediatric patients 2 years of age or older requiring supplemental oxygen, invasive mechanical ventilation, or extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO).  \nFor more information see Frequently Asked Questions on the Emergency Use Authorization for Olumiant (baricitinib) in Combination with Veklury (remdesivir) for Treatment of Mild to Moderate COVID-19."},{"id":744,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Is bamlanivimab, a monoclonal antibody, FDA-approved to treat COVID-19?","response":"No. Bamlanivimab is not FDA-approved to treat any diseases or conditions, including COVID-19. On November 9, 2020, FDA issued an emergency use authorization (EUA) for bamlanivimab for the treatment of mild to moderate COVID-19 in adults and pediatric patients with positive results of direct SARS-CoV-2 viral testing who are 12 years and older weighing at least 40kg, and who are at high risk for progressing to severe COVID-19 and/or hospitalization. \nSince the initial authorization of bamlanivimab administered alone for emergency use, there has been a sustained increase in SARS-CoV-2 viral variants across the U.S. that are resistant to bamlanivimab alone. Given the frequency of these particular viral variants, and since current testing technologies are not available to ascertain whether a particular patient who has tested positive for coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is infected with a viral variant prior to initiation of treatment, there is an increased risk of treatment failure when bamlanivimab is administered alone. \nBased on the totality of scientific evidence available, the Agency concluded that the known and potential benefits of bamlanivimab administered alone no longer outweigh the known and potential risks for the product. Therefore, FDA determined that the criteria for issuance of an EUA are no longer met and revoked the EUA for bamlanivimab administered alone for the treatment of COVID-19 on April 16, 2021. Read more about this action."},{"id":745,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Are the monoclonal antibodies, casirivimab and imdevimab, FDA-approved to treat COVID-19?","response":"No. Casirivimab and imdevimab are not FDA-approved to treat any diseases or conditions, including COVID-19. However, the FDA issued an emergency use authorization (EUA) for casirivimab and imdevimab to be administered together for the treatment of mild to moderate COVID-19 in adults and pediatric patients (12 years of age or older weighing at least 40 kilograms [about 88 pounds]) with positive results of direct SARS-CoV-2 viral testing and who are at high risk for progressing to severe COVID-19. This includes those who are 65 years of age or older or who have certain chronic medical conditions. Learn more about casirivimab and imdevimab for COVID-19."},{"id":746,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Are the monoclonal antibodies, bamlanivimab and etesevimab, FDA-approved to treat COVID-19?","response":"No. Bamlanivimab and etesevimab are not FDA-approved to treat any diseases or conditions, including COVID-19. However, the FDA issued an emergency use authorization (EUA) for bamlanivimab and etesevimab to be administered together for the treatment of mild to moderate COVID-19 in adults and pediatric patients (12 years of age or older weighing at least 40 kilograms [about 88 pounds]) with positive results of direct SARS-CoV-2 viral testing and who are at high risk for progressing to severe COVID-19. This includes those who are 65 years of age or older or who have certain chronic medical conditions. Learn more about bamlanivimab and etesevimab for COVID-19."},{"id":747,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is a monoclonal antibody?","response":"Monoclonal antibodies are laboratory-produced molecules that act as substitute antibodies that can restore, enhance or mimic the immune system's attack on cells. Monoclonal antibodies for COVID-19 may block the virus that causes COVID-19 from attaching to human cells, making it more difficult for the virus to reproduce and cause harm. Monoclonal antibodies may also neutralize a virus."},{"id":748,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Where are infusions of monoclonal antibody treatments available?","response":"The following websites contain information regarding access to monoclonal antibody treatments for COVID-19:\nHHS Protect Public Data Hub – Therapeutics Distribution\nNational Infusion Center Association (NICA)\nMonoclonal antibody treatments for COVID-19 may only be administered in settings in which health care providers have immediate access to medications to treat a severe infusion reaction, such as anaphylaxis, and have the ability to activate the emergency medical system (EMS), if necessary. Please speak with your doctor or contact your local or state public health department for more information."},{"id":749,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Are chloroquine phosphate or hydroxychloroquine sulfate approved by the FDA to treat COVID-19?","response":"No. Hydroxychloroquine sulfate and some versions of chloroquine phosphate are FDA-approved to treat malaria. Hydroxychloroquine sulfate is also FDA-approved to treat lupus and rheumatoid arthritis.\nOn March 28, 2020, the FDA issued an emergency use authorization (EUA) for chloroquine phosphate and hydroxychloroquine sulfate to treat adults and adolescents hospitalized with COVID-19 for whom a clinical trial was not available or participation was not feasible. Based on FDA’s continued review of the scientific evidence available, the criteria for an EUA for chloroquine phosphate and hydroxychloroquine sulfate as outlined in Section 564(c)(2) of the FD&C Act are no longer met. As a result, the EUA for these two drugs was revoked on June 15, 2020. Read more about this action."},{"id":750,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Should I take chloroquine phosphate used to treat disease in aquarium fish to prevent or treat COVID-19?","response":"No. Products marketed for veterinary use, “for research only,” or otherwise not for human consumption have not been evaluated for safety or effectiveness and should never be used by humans. The FDA is aware that chloroquine phosphate is marketed to treat disease in aquarium fish, but these products have not been evaluated by the FDA to determine if they are safe, effective, properly manufactured, and adequately labeled. The agency continues to work with online marketplaces to remove these items, and many have been removed based on these efforts. Patients should not take any form of chloroquine unless it has been prescribed by a licensed health care provider. Chloroquine products also should not be given to pets or livestock unless prescribed by a veterinarian."},{"id":751,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Are antibiotics effective in preventing or treating COVID-19?","response":"No. Antibiotics do not work against viruses; they only work on bacterial infections. Antibiotics do not prevent or treat COVID-19, because COVID-19 is caused by a virus, not bacteria. Some patients with COVID-19 may also develop a bacterial infection, such as pneumonia. In that case, a health care professional may treat the bacterial infection with an antibiotic."},{"id":752,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Should I take ivermectin to prevent or treat COVID-19?","response":"No. While there are approved uses for ivermectin in people and animals, it is not approved for the prevention or treatment of COVID-19. You should not take any medicine to treat or prevent COVID-19 unless it has been prescribed to you by your health care provider and acquired from a legitimate source. \nA recently released research article described the effect of ivermectin on SARS-CoV-2 in a laboratory setting. These types of laboratory studies are commonly used at an early stage of drug development. Additional testing is needed to determine whether ivermectin might be appropriate to prevent or treat coronavirus or COVID-19. Read more about ivermectin."},{"id":753,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is the FDA doing to protect people from products making fraudulent COVID-19 claims?","response":"We have established a cross-agency team dedicated to closely monitoring for fraudulent COVID-19 products. In response to internet scammers, the FDA has taken – and continues to take – actions to stop those selling unapproved products that fraudulently claim to prevent, treat, diagnose or cure COVID-19. The FDA and the Federal Trade Commission (FTC) issue warning letters to companies and individuals that are unlawfully selling unapproved products with fraudulent COVID-19 claims. The FDA also has taken enforcement action against certain sellers that continued to illegally market products for prevention or treatment of COVID-19. \nAdditionally, the FDA also has reached out to major retailers to ask for their help in monitoring online marketplaces for fraudulent COVID-19 products. You can report websites selling fraudulent medical products to the FDA through our website, by phone at 1-800-332-1088, or email to FDA-COVID-19-Fraudulent-Products@fda.hhs.gov. Read more in the consumer update on fraudulent products."},{"id":754,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Will there be drug shortages due to COVID-19?","response":"The FDA has been closely monitoring the supply chain with the expectation that the COVID-19 outbreak would likely impact the medical product supply chain, including potential disruptions to supply or shortages of critical medical products in the U.S. \nWe have been reaching out to manufacturers as part of our approach to identifying potential disruptions or shortages. We will use all available tools to react swiftly and mitigate the impact to U.S. patients and health care professionals when a potential disruption or shortage is identified.\nFind real-time information about drug shortages.\nLearn more in our drug shortages frequently asked questions."},{"id":755,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":" Am I at risk for COVID-19 from taking FDA-approved drugs made outside the United States?","response":"Currently, there is no evidence to support transmission of COVID-19 associated with imported goods, including food and drugs for humans and pets. There have not been any cases of COVID-19 in the United States associated with imported goods. Learn more about the FDA’s Import Program and Importing COVID Supplies."},{"id":756,"category":"Drugs (Medicines)","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Who should I contact with drug-related questions?","response":"If you have additional questions, call the FDA’s Division of Drug Information at (855) 543-3784 or email us at druginfo@fda.hhs.gov."},{"id":757,"category":"Medical Devices Including Tests for COVID-19","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Is there a test for COVID-19?","response":"Yes, the FDA has issued Emergency Use Authorizations (EUAs) for different types of COVID-19 tests. Some tests are used to diagnose the virus that causes COVID-19 infection whereas other tests are used to detect a recent or prior COVID-19 infection. There are 2 different types of COVID-19 diagnostic tests -- molecular tests and antigen tests. Molecular tests detect the virus that causes COVID-19, SARS-CoV-2. Antigen tests detect specific proteins made by the virus. Tests that detect recent or prior COVID-19 infection are called antibody or serology tests. The EUAs allow the emergency use of tests during the COVID-19 emergency when the FDA determines certain criteria are met. These criteria include that the test may be effective at diagnosing COVID-19 and that the known and potential benefits outweigh the known and potential risks. Read more about COVID-19 tests and find a community-based testing site."},{"id":758,"category":"Medical Devices Including Tests for COVID-19","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"How are people tested for COVID-19?","response":"Most tests to diagnose COVID-19 require a swab of your nose, or the part of the throat behind the nose, by a health care provider. Some tests use saliva (spit) or other types of samples. For most FDA-authorized tests, the swab or sample must be sent to a lab for analysis. Some tests allow the patient to collect the sample at home and then send it to a lab for analysis. Some tests can be analyzed at the point-of-care, such as in a doctor’s office or health clinic. The FDA has also authorized some at-home tests that allow a person to collect their sample and run the test completely at home without sending anything to a lab. Some tests can be purchased online or in a store without a prescription, but they may not be available everywhere. Learn more about Coronavirus Disease 2019 Testing Basics."},{"id":759,"category":"Medical Devices Including Tests for COVID-19","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Are there any at-home tests for COVID-19?","response":"Yes. There are now FDA-authorized COVID-19 tests available for purchase online or in a store that can be used completely at home. At-home tests allow you to collect your own sample and test it with a system that gives you results in minutes at home.\nAdditionally, the FDA has authorized some tests that can be purchased online or in a store that allow you to collect your own sample and then send it to a laboratory for analysis."},{"id":760,"category":"Medical Devices Including Tests for COVID-19","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"When will other diagnostic tests for COVID-19 be authorized?","response":"The FDA is actively working with test developers and issues Emergency Use Authorizations (EUAs) frequently for EUA requests with sufficient supporting data."},{"id":761,"category":"Medical Devices Including Tests for COVID-19","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is the difference between the types of tests available for SARS-CoV-2?","response":"There are two different types of tests – diagnostic tests and antibody tests.\nA diagnostic test can show if you have an active coronavirus infection and should take steps to quarantine or isolate yourself from others. Currently there are two types of diagnostic tests – molecular (RT-PCR) tests that detect the virus’s genetic material, and antigen tests that detect specific proteins on the surface of the virus. Samples are typically collected with a nasal or throat swab, or saliva collected by spitting into a tube.\nAn antibody test looks for antibodies that are made by the immune system in response to a threat, such as a specific virus. Antibodies can help fight infections. Antibodies can take several days or weeks to develop after you have an infection and may stay in your blood for several weeks after recovery. Because of this, antibody tests should not be used to diagnose an active coronavirus infection. At this time, researchers do not know if the presence of antibodies means that you are immune to the coronavirus in the future. While there is a lot of uncertainty with this new virus, it is also possible that, over time, broad use of antibody tests and clinical follow-up will provide the medical community with more information on whether or not, and how long, a person who has recovered from the virus is at lower risk of infection if they are exposed to the virus again. Samples are typically blood from a finger stick or blood draw. Learn more about antibody tests. \nLearn more about the different types of tests and the steps involved in the FDA’s Consumer Update on Coronavirus Testing Basics."},{"id":762,"category":"Medical Devices Including Tests for COVID-19","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Should I purchase personal protective equipment such as facemasks or N95 respirators for me and my family?","response":"No. Surgical masks and N95s need to be reserved for use by health care workers, first responders, and other frontline workers whose jobs put them at much greater risk of acquiring COVID-19. The cloth face coverings recommended by CDC are not surgical masks or N95 respirators. Surgical masks and N95s are critical supplies that must continue to be reserved for health care workers and other medical first responders, as recommended by CDC."},{"id":763,"category":"Medical Devices Including Tests for COVID-19","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Is there a shortage of personal protective equipment (PPE) such as gloves, masks, and N95 respirators or of ventilators?","response":" The FDA has been working closely with PPE and ventilator manufacturers to understand their supply capabilities during this pandemic. The agency is also aware of challenges throughout the supply chain that are presently impacting the availability of PPE products and is taking steps to mitigate shortages that health care facilities are already experiencing. \nThe FDA issued new guidance to give ventilator manufacturers and non-medical device manufacturers more flexibility to start making new ventilators and parts. We adjusted our screening of PPE  and medical devices at U.S. ports of entry to expedite imports of legitimate products into the U.S. With CDC we took action to make more respirators, including certain N95s, available to health care personnel for use in health care settings. Read more about PPE.\nThe FDA encourages manufacturers and health care facilities to report any supply disruptions to the device shortages mailbox at deviceshortages@fda.hhs.gov."},{"id":764,"category":"Medical Devices Including Tests for COVID-19","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Can 3D printing be used to make PPE?","response":"Personal protective equipment (PPE) includes protective clothing, gowns, gloves, face shields, goggles, face masks, and respirators or other equipment designed to protect the wearer from injury or the spread of infection or illness. While it is possible to use 3D printing to make certain PPE, there are technical challenges. 3D-printed PPE may provide a physical barrier, but 3D-printed PPE are unlikely to provide the same fluid barrier and air filtration protection as FDA-cleared surgical masks and N95 respirators. The CDC has recommendations for how to optimize the supply of face masks. Find more information about 3D printing during the COVID-19 pandemic."},{"id":765,"category":"Medical Devices Including Tests for COVID-19","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"I built a DIY ventilator using instructions I found on the internet. May I sell it?","response":"DIY ventilator makers may request that their product be added to the  Emergency Use Authorization (EUA) that the FDA issued on March 24, 2020, to legally market the product in the U.S. Instructions on how to do so, and the criteria for ventilator safety, performance and labeling, may be found in the Letter of Authorization and Appendix A for the EUA related to ventilators, anesthesia gas machines modified for use as ventilators, positive pressure breathing devices modified for use as ventilators, ventilator tubing connectors, and ventilator accessories."},{"id":766,"category":"Medical Devices Including Tests for COVID-19","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Who should I contact if I have questions about medical devices or need more information?","response":"Please see Contacts for Medical Devices During the COVID-19 Pandemic.\nIf you need information about the development of a test for SARS-CoV-2, please see our FAQs on Testing for SARS-CoV-2."},{"id":767,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is the FDA’s role in helping to ensure the safety of the human and animal food supply?","response":"To protect public health, the FDA monitors domestic firms and the foods that they produce. The FDA also monitors imported products and foreign firms exporting to the United States. The FDA protects consumers from unsafe foods through research and methods development; inspection and sampling; and regulatory and legal action."},{"id":768,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Will there be food shortages?","response":"In some cases the inventory of certain foods at your grocery store might be temporarily low before stores can restock. Food production and manufacturing generally are widely dispersed throughout the U.S., however; there is a significant shift in where consumers are buying food during the pandemic. While food use in large-scale establishments, such as hotels, restaurants, sports arenas/stadiums and universities suddenly declined, the demand for food at grocery stores increased.  \nThe FDA has issued temporary guidance to provide flexibility in packaging and labeling requirements to support food supply chains and get foods to the consumer retail marketplace. The FDA is closely monitoring the food supply chain for any shortages in collaboration with industry and our federal and state partners. We are in regular contact with food manufacturers and grocery stores. Watch a video on food safety and availability during the coronavirus pandemic."},{"id":769,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Why is the FDA providing flexibility to food manufacturers, under limited circumstances during the COVID-19 public health emergency, to make minor changes in ingredients without reflecting those changes on the package label?","response":"Due to limited shortages of specific ingredients and foods, or unexpected supply chain disruptions in some industries, food manufacturers may need to make small changes to some ingredients during the COVID-19 public health emergency. Manufacturers may not be able to relabel their products to reflect these minor changes on the food label without slowing down the processing or distribution of the food.\nTo avoid slowing down food processing or distribution during the coronavirus pandemic, the FDA issued a guidance titled \"Temporary Policy Regarding Certain Food Labeling Requirements During the COVID-19 Public Health Emergency: Minor Formulation Changes and Vending Machines.\"  The temporary policy provides food manufacturers with flexibility to make minor formulation changes in certain, limited circumstances without making conforming label changes on packages as long as any substitutions or omissions of ingredients do not pose a health or safety issue (such as allergens), and do not cause significant changes in the finished product."},{"id":770,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What do I need to know about the temporary policy for food labeling of minor ingredient changes during the COVID-19 public health emergency if I have food allergies?","response":"Although the temporary policy allows some flexibility, the eight major food allergens under the Food Allergen Labeling and Consumer Protection Act (FALCPA) of 2004 cannot be substituted for labeled ingredients by manufacturers without a corresponding label change. While the temporary policy does not list all ingredients known to cause sensitivities in some people, manufacturers should avoid substituting ingredients with major food allergens or with ingredients recognized as priority allergens (such as sesame, celery, lupin, buckwheat, molluscan shellfish, and mustard) in other parts of the world without a label change. These flexibilities are intended to remain in effect only for the duration of the COVID-19 public health emergency in the United States. However, when this public health emergency is over, extensions may be needed if the food and agriculture sectors need additional time to bring supply chains back into regular order. For more information please see more Questions and Answers on FDA’s Temporary Policy on Food Labeling Changes During the COVID-19 Pandemic."},{"id":771,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Will there be animal food shortages?","response":"There are no nationwide shortages of animal food, although in some cases the inventory of certain foods at your grocery store might be temporarily low before stores can restock. Animal food production and manufacturing are widely dispersed throughout the United States and no widespread disruptions have been reported in the supply chain."},{"id":772,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What are the most important things I need to know to keep myself and others safe when I go to the grocery store during the pandemic?","response":"There are steps you can take to help protect yourself, grocery store workers and other shoppers, such as wearing a face covering, practicing social distancing, and using wipes on the handles of the shopping cart or basket. Read more tips in Shopping for Food During the COVID-19 Pandemic - Information for Consumers."},{"id":773,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Are food products produced in the United States or other countries affected by COVID-19 a risk for the spread of COVID-19?","response":"There is no evidence to suggest that food produced in the United States or imported from countries affected by COVID-19 can transmit COVID-19."},{"id":774,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Can I get the coronavirus from food, food packaging, or food containers and preparation area?","response":"Currently there is no evidence of food, food containers, or food packaging being associated with transmission of COVID-19.  Like other viruses, it is possible that the virus that causes COVID-19 can survive on surfaces or objects. \nIf you are concerned about contamination of food or food packaging, wash your hands after handling food packaging, after removing food from the packaging, before you prepare food for eating and before you eat. Consumers can follow CDC guidelines on frequent hand washing with soap and water for at least 20 seconds; and frequently clean and disinfect surfaces.\nIt is always important to follow the 4 key steps of food safety—clean, separate, cook, and chill."},{"id":775,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":" Is the U.S. food supply safe?","response":"Currently there is no evidence of food or food packaging being associated with transmission of COVID-19.   \nUnlike foodborne gastrointestinal (GI) viruses like norovirus and hepatitis A that often make people ill through contaminated food, SARS-CoV-2, which causes COVID-19, is a virus that causes respiratory illness and not gastrointestinal illness, and foodborne exposure to this virus is not known to be a route of transmission.\nIt may be possible that a person can get COVID-19 by touching a surface or object that has the virus on it and then touching their own mouth, nose, or possibly their eyes, but this is not thought to be the main way the virus spreads. It’s always important to follow the 4 key steps of food safety—clean, separate, cook, and chill."},{"id":776,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Is the U.S. animal food supply safe?","response":"Currently there is no evidence of animal food or food packaging being associated with transmission of COVID-19.\nFoodborne exposure to the virus that causes COVID-19 is not known to be a route of transmission."},{"id":777,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Can I get COVID-19 from a food worker handling my food?","response":"Currently, there is no evidence of food or food packaging being associated with transmission of COVID-19. However, the virus that causes COVID-19 is spreading from person-to-person in some communities in the U.S. The CDC recommends that if you are sick, stay home until you are better and no longer pose a risk of infecting others. \nAnyone handling, preparing and serving food should always follow safe food handling procedures, such as washing hands and surfaces often."},{"id":778,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Should food workers who are ill stay home?","response":"CDC recommends that employees who have symptoms of acute respiratory illness stay home and not come to work until they are free of fever (100.4° F [37.8° C] or greater using an oral thermometer), signs of a fever, and any other symptoms for at least 24 hours, without the use of fever-reducing or other symptom-altering medicines (e.g. cough suppressants). Employees should notify their supervisor and stay home if they are sick. We recommend that businesses review CDC’s interim guidance for businesses and employers for planning and responding to coronavirus disease.  Also see the FDA’s Retail Food Protection: Employee Health and Personal Hygiene Handbook."},{"id":779,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Should food facilities (grocery stores, manufacturing facilities, restaurants, etc.) perform any special cleaning or sanitation procedures for COVID-19?","response":"CDC recommends routine cleaning of all frequently touched surfaces in the workplace, such as workstations, countertops, and doorknobs. Use the cleaning agents that are usually used in these areas and follow the directions on the label. CDC does not recommend any additional disinfection beyond routine cleaning at this time. \nView the current list of products that meet EPA’s criteria for use against SARS-CoV-2, the cause of COVID-19.  \nRestaurants and retail food establishments are regulated at the state and local level. State, local, and tribal regulators use the Food Code published by the FDA to develop or update their own food safety rules. Generally, FDA-regulated food manufacturers are required to maintain clean facilities, including, as appropriate, clean and sanitized food contact surfaces, and to have food safety plans in place.   Food safety plans include a hazards analysis and risk-based preventive controls and include procedures for maintaining clean and sanitized facilities and food contact surfaces. See: FSMA Final Rule for Preventive Controls for Human Food."},{"id":780,"category":"Food Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is the FDA doing to respond to foodborne illnesses during the COVID-19 pandemic?","response":"The virus that causes COVID-19 is a virus that causes respiratory illness. Viruses like norovirus and hepatitis A that can make people sick through contaminated food usually cause gastrointestinal or stomach illness. Currently there is no evidence of food, food containers, or food packaging being associated with transmission of COVID-19.  \nThe CDC, FDA, and USDA continue to work with state and local partners to investigate foodborne illness and outbreaks during the COVID-19 pandemic. The FDA’s Coordinated Outbreak Response and Evaluation (CORE) Network manages outbreak response, as well as surveillance and post-response activities related to incidents involving multiple illnesses linked to FDA-regulated human food products. During this coronavirus outbreak, CORE’s full-time staff will continue to operate to prepare for, coordinate and carry out response activities to incidents of foodborne illnesses. \nThe FDA’s Center for Veterinary Medicine manages outbreak response for animal food and is similarly staffed and prepared to respond to incidents of foodborne illness in animals."},{"id":781,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What is the FDA’s role in regulating animal drugs, animal food (including pet food), and animal medical devices?","response":"The FDA approves and regulates animal drugs to ensure they are safe and effective. In addition, the FDA helps ensure that animal food (including pet food) is safe and truthfully labeled. The FDA has post-market authority over veterinary medical devices."},{"id":782,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Can I give my pet COVID-19? Can I get COVID-19 from my pet or other animals?","response":"There is a very small number of pets around the world reported to be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19 after having contact with a person with COVID-19. Based on the limited information currently available, the risk of animals spreading COVID-19 to people is considered low. \nUntil we learn more about how this virus affects animals, treat pets as you would other human family members to protect them from a potential infection.\nDo not let pets interact with people outside the household.\nKeep cats indoors when possible to prevent them from interacting with other animals or people.\nWalk dogs on a leash, maintaining at least 6 feet (2 meters) from other people.\nAvoid dog parks or public places where a large number of people gather.\nTalk to your veterinarian if your pet gets sick or if you have any concerns about your pet’s health. Learn more about Pet Safety & COVID-19."},{"id":783,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Is there a test for COVID-19 in pets? If so, has it been approved by the FDA?","response":"Certain veterinary diagnostic laboratories have developed diagnostic tests for SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, for use in pets if needed. \nDiagnostic tests for animals are regulated differently than those for humans. The FDA does not require approval or clearance of a 510(k), PMA, or any other pre-market submission for devices, including diagnostic tests, intended for animal use. The FDA does, however, have post-market regulatory oversight over devices intended for animal use and can take appropriate regulatory action if an animal device is misbranded or adulterated.\nCertain private, state, and university veterinary diagnostic laboratories have developed diagnostic tests for SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19, for use in dogs and cats. The FDA is also aware of at least two veterinary tests for COVID-19 in pets developed by commercial laboratories initially for internal surveillance, but the agency has not evaluated the validity of these tests. The tests are not currently available for routine testing. The decision to test pets should be made collaboratively between local, state, or federal public and animal health officials."},{"id":784,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Should I get my pet tested for COVID-19?","response":"Routine testing of pets for COVID-19 is not recommended at this time. There is currently no evidence that animals are a source of COVID-19 infection in the United States. Based on the limited information available to date, the risk of pets spreading the virus is considered to be low. If your pet is sick, consult your veterinarian. \nAnimal testing is reserved for situations when the results may affect the treatment or management of people and animals. If your veterinarian thinks your pet is a candidate for testing, they will consult the state veterinarian and public health officials. Do not contact your state veterinarians directly: they do not have the client/patient-veterinarian relationship that would allow them to fully understand the situation and they are also actively involved in other animal disease-related emergencies as well as response to COVID-19."},{"id":785,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"What animal species can get COVID-19?","response":"We currently don’t fully understand how COVID-19 affects different animal species. We are aware of a very small number of pets, including dogs, cats and a ferret reported to be infected with the virus that causes COVID-19 after close contact with people with COVID-19. \nLarge cats in captivity, including several lions and tigers in a New York zoo, a puma in South Africa, and tigers in a Tennessee zoo have tested positive for SARS-CoV-2, as have several gorillas  at the San Diego zoo, after showing signs of respiratory illness. It is suspected these animals became sick after being exposed to zoo employees with COVID-19.\nThe virus that causes COVID-19 has been reported in minks on farms in the Netherlands, Denmark, Spain, Italy, Sweden and the United States. Once the virus is introduced on a farm, spread can occur between mink as well as from mink to other animals on the farm (dogs, cats). Because some workers on these farms had COVID-19, it is likely that infected farm workers were the initial source of mink infections.\nRecent research shows that ferrets, cats, fruit bats, and golden Syrian hamsters can be experimentally infected with the virus and can spread the infection to other animals of the same species in laboratory settings. Mice, pigs, chickens, and ducks did not become infected or spread the infection based on results from these studies. Data from one study suggest that dogs are not as likely to become infected with the virus as cats and ferrets. These findings were based upon a small number of animals and do not indicate whether animals can spread infection to people.\nFor any animal that tests positive for SARS-CoV-2 at a private or state laboratory, USDA's National Veterinary Services Laboratories performs additional testing to confirm the infection and posts the results on this page: Cases of SARS-CoV-2 in Animals in the United States."},{"id":786,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Can pets carry the virus that causes COVID-19 on their skin or fur?","response":"Although we know certain bacteria and fungi can be carried on fur and hair, there is no evidence that viruses, including the virus that causes COVID-19, can spread to people from the skin, fur, or hair of pets.\nHowever, because animals can sometimes carry other germs that can make people sick, it’s always a good idea to practice healthy habits around pets and other animals, including washing hands before and after interacting with them and especially after cleaning up their waste.\nThere are no products that are FDA-approved to disinfect the hair or coats of pets, but if you do decide to bathe or wipe off your pet, first talk to your veterinarian about suitable products. Never use hand sanitizer, counter-cleaning wipes or other industrial or surface cleaners, as these can penetrate the skin or be licked off and ingested by your pet. If you have recently used any of these products on your pet, or your pet is showing signs of illness after use, contact your veterinarian and rinse or wipe down your pet with water."},{"id":787,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Are there any approved products that can prevent or treat COVID-19 in animals?","response":"No. Under the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic (FD&C) Act, “articles intended for use in the diagnosis, cure, mitigation, treatment, or prevention of disease in man or other animals” are drugs. The FDA has not approved any drugs for the diagnosis, cure, mitigation, treatment, or prevention of COVID-19 in animals. The U.S. Department of Agriculture’s (USDA) Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service (APHIS) Center for Veterinary Biologics (CVB) regulates veterinary biologics, including vaccines, diagnostic kits, and other products of biological origin. Similarly, APHIS CVB has not licensed any products to treat or prevent COVID-19 in animals.\nThe FDA has taken action against unapproved products claiming to prevent or cure COVID-19. The public can help safeguard human and animal health by reporting any products claiming to do so to FDA-COVID-19-Fraudulent-Products@fda.hhs.gov or 1-888-INFO-FDA (1-888-463-6332)."},{"id":788,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Is it true that animals, like dogs, cats, and cattle, get their own different types of coronavirus?","response":"Yes. Coronaviruses are a large family of viruses. Some coronaviruses like COVID-19 cause cold-like illnesses in people, while others cause illness in certain types of animals, such as cattle, camels, and bats. Some coronaviruses, such as canine and feline coronaviruses, only infect animals and do not infect humans. For example, bovine coronavirus causes diarrhea in young calves, and pregnant cows are routinely vaccinated to help prevent infection in calves. This vaccine is only licensed for use in cattle for bovine coronavirus and is not licensed to prevent COVID-19 in cattle or other species, including humans.\nDogs can get a respiratory coronavirus, which is part of the complex of viruses and bacteria associated with canine infectious respiratory disease, commonly known as “kennel cough.” While this virus is highly contagious among both domestic and wild dogs, it is not transmitted to other animal species or humans.\nMost strains of feline enteric coronavirus, a gastrointestinal form, are fought off by a cat’s immune system without causing disease. However, in a small proportion of these cats, the virus can cause feline infectious peritonitis (FIP), a disease that is almost always fatal.\nOther species, like horses, turkeys, chickens, and swine, can contract their own species-specific strains of coronavirus but, like the other strains mentioned above, they are not known to be transmissible to humans. More information is available in the American Veterinary Medical Association’s fact sheet about coronaviruses in domestic species."},{"id":789,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"If my pet previously had a species-specific coronavirus, does that make them more or less likely to get COVID-19?","response":"There are no data to suggest that current or previous infection with another strain of coronavirus would make your pet more or less likely to get COVID-19."},{"id":790,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"If my pet has been vaccinated for species-specific coronavirus, does that make them more or less likely to get COVID-19?","response":"Species-specific coronavirus vaccines are unlikely to work against this type of coronavirus because it is a new virus that is different from the species-specific strains of coronavirus targeted by the vaccine."},{"id":791,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"My pet has health problems and goes to the vet regularly for treatment. Should I be doing anything different to manage their health during the COVID-19 outbreak?","response":"While you should not avoid necessary visits to your veterinarian due to the COVID-19 outbreak, you should exercise reasonable caution just like you would if you were going to any other public place. If you are concerned about your own health or that of your pet when going to the veterinarian, contact their office in advance to discuss any recommended precautions."},{"id":792,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Is it safe to adopt pets from a shelter or rescue?","response":"There is no reason to think that any animals, including shelter or rescue pets, in the United States, might be a source of COVID-19. The virus that causes COVID-19 spreads mainly from person to person, typically through respiratory droplets from coughing, sneezing, or talking."},{"id":793,"category":"Animals, Pets and Animal Drug Products","source":"https://www.fda.gov/emergency-preparedness-and-response/coronavirus-disease-2019-covid-19/covid-19-frequently-asked-questions","question":"Are there going to be any animal drug shortages due to the COVID-19 outbreak?","response":"The FDA has been and is continuing to closely monitor how the COVID-19 outbreak may impact the animal medical product supply chain.\nWe have been reaching out to manufacturers as part of our approach to identifying potential disruptions or shortages. We will use all available tools to react swiftly to help mitigate the impact if a potential disruption or shortage is identified.\nLearn more on our Animal Drug Shortage Information page."}]}